<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=815}]"><cms:name>attending-fires-815</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Firefighting/Rescue - Attending Fires</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=815}]"><cms:name>attending-fires-815-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>firefighting, rescue, attending, fires</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=815}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>When you dial 999 and ask for the Fire Service, your call is sent to the emergency call handling centre which routes all calls for your area to Fire Control - calls are normally answered within 1 to 5 seconds. Control will confirm with you the address of the incident and help will be despatched to you immediately. </i></p><hr/><h2>
				How does Fire Control make this happen?
			</h2><p>
					  When your call is received, Control staff enter details in the Command
          and Control system. This system automatically finds the closest appliances
          and
      officers to respond, and activates the turnout system at the nearest fire
      station - turning on the audible alarms, part-time firefighters' personal
      alerters, lights at night and any other facilities connected to it. The
          address of the call is sent to the fire station teleprinter, the officers'
          pagers
  and, on selected vehicles, to mobile data terminals in the cabs of the appliances. 
				</p><p>
					Control initially mobilise to each incident with a specific response which
  is called a Pre-Determined Attendance (PDA). The PDA to an incident will vary
  considerably dependent on many considerations, such as:
				</p><ul>
				<li title="*">Location</li>
<li title="*">Type
    of Incident</li>
<li title="*">Type
    of Property (eg High Rise/Hospital)</li>
<li title="*">Crewing
    (personnel) required</li>
<li title="*">Equipment
    required</li>
</ul><h2>
				Communicating with the Firefighters
			</h2><p>
					  Fire and Rescue operate
    2 radio channels within their vehicles and all officers and appliances attending
    incidents can keep Control
          informed
      of where they are and what they are doing.
				</p><p>
					When they arrive at the
    incident, they may require more assistance and this is requested over the
    radio scheme. All requests for further assistance are
  monitored by Fire Control as they have a complete overview of all the resources
  which are available in the area and the neighbouring counties and can quickly
  mobilise additional fire engines to support those in attendance.
				</p><p>
					To ensure that all details, such as road and place names, are communicated
  accurately, Control use the nationally recognised phonetic alphabet.
				</p><h2>
				Maintaining cover at other fire stations
			</h2><p>
					  One of the important jobs that Fire Control staff have to do is to make
          sure that cover is maintained at fire stations so that, when further
          calls are
      received, Control staff will make standby moves, mobilising fire engines
  to fire stations to ensure that they are available for subsequent incidents.
				</p><h2>
				False Alarms
			</h2><p>
				  Every call and radio message is automatically recorded at the time. This
          recorded information can be used as evidence and people making malicious
          false alarm
      calls can be prosecuted. False calls can mean that fire engines mobilised
      to such occurrences can reduce availability and response times for real
          emergency situations.
			</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=815"> Providing Information
		(815)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
