<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=817}]"><cms:name>special-services-817</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Firefighting/Rescue - Special Services</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=817}]"><cms:name>special-services-817-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>firefighting, rescue, special, services</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=817}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The fire safety activities carried out by members of the Fire and Rescue Service are a combination of legal requirements, goodwill advice and the continuing process of Community education, the ultimate objective of which is to reduce the incidences of death and injury from fire and maintain a fire safe environment. </i></p><hr/><p>&quot;Fire Safety&quot; comprises
      a combination of responsibilities and obligations, ranging from
      legislative enforcement and community education to incident investigation
  and after fire care. </p><p>Fire Safety Inspectors throughout the area may make requirements, or give
    advice, in respect of a wide range of premises including sports grounds, hotels
    and places of work, such as offices, shops and factories. This responsibility
    is contained within a vast array of Acts and Regulations, including the Fire
    Precautions Act 1971 and the Fire Precautions (Workplace) (Amendment) Regulations
1999, to name but two.</p><p>Fire Safety Inspectors also advise other enforcing agencies such as Licensing
    Justices, Local Authorities and Health Authorities on the standards to be applied
    in premises like pubs and clubs, residential care homes, hospitals and houses
in multiple accommodation. </p><p>Amongst their many roles, Community Fire Safety Officers carry out higher
    risk Home Fire Safety Risk Assessments, as a way of ensuring that the most
    vulnerable members of the Community are identified and afforded the most appropriate
    protection. The protection, which may be provided in conjunction with other
    agencies such as Health and Social Services, may take the form of simple fire
    education, being provided with smoke alarms or ultimately residential sprinkler
systems. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=817"> Providing Information
		(817)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
