<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=819}]"><cms:name>securing-premises-after-incidents-819</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Firefighting/Rescue - Securing Premises After Incidents</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=819}]"><cms:name>securing-premises-after-incidents-819-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>firefighting, rescue, securing, premises, after, incidents</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=819}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If you have doubts about the suitability of your accommodation after the fire, contact your local Housing and Social Services regarding alternative accommodation, or your local Police who will endeavour to make contact on your behalf.
</i></p><hr/><h2>  How to protect your property </h2><p>  If your property is in
    an insecure condition...</p><p>Close all doors and windows as these are an open invitation to thieves.</p><p>Should windows or doors
    require boarding up, a contractor can be contacted through Yellow Pages to
    fulfil
    this service. As insurance policies differ widely,
    it is impossible to state definitely whether this will be covered by your
    policy. If you are a council tenant and require a 'boarding-up service',
    please contact the Council who
    will carry
  out the services free of charge.</p><p>Contact you local Police. Ensure that they know your property is empty and
  insecure and remove cash and valuables.</p><p>The Fire Brigade may use large sheets to protect your property. This is a
    temporary measure only and you should arrange to have them replaced within
a reasonable length of time.</p><h2>Insurance </h2><p>At the earliest date...
</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Contact your insurance company, inform them of the incident, obtain and complete
a claims form.</li>
			<li title="*"> They may wish to inspect your property before anything is moved. </li>
			<li title="*">Return the form to the address shown on the claims form. </li>
			<li title="*"> If you are uninsured,
    you may be able to get financial help or furniture, from your local Social
    Security Office.</li>
			<li title="*"> If you have money that is partially burned, it can be taken to a bank
  for replacement.</li>
			<li title="*">If you rent or lease the property, you may be required to contact
  the landlord or his agent. </li>
		</ul><h2>Power Supplies<br/>
</h2><h3>Electricity</h3><p>  If your internal supply has been affected, your Electricity Board
                    will have to re-connect the supply after a qualified electrician
                    has repaired
                    it (even if
                  only a temporary circuit) and notified the Board of completion.
<strong>Do not attempt to reconnect or turn on the supply yourself</strong>.</p><h3>Gas</h3><p>  If any of your gas appliances have been affected by fire, the Fire Service
        or British Gas will turn off or disconnect your supply. It is important that
        either British Gas or an approved installer inspects and rectifies any problems
in the system before any attempt is made to re-connect or turn on the supply.</p><h3>Water</h3><p>A plumber will be required if your water supply has been affected. <strong>Do not attempt to turn on your water until your system has been attended by the plumber.</strong>
		</p><p>Temporary lighting or heating units are potentially dangerous, especially
    if they have been unused or stored for some time. Do not forget to have these
    units checked by the manufacturer or qualified dealer before use. If you are
    unsure of the precautions to take when positioning or filling these appliances,
    contact the Fire Prevention Officer at your local Fire Station. Don't forget
when using these appliances to read and follow the manufacturer's instructions.</p><h2>The Clean Up <br/>
</h2><h3>Carpets and Rugs</h3><p> A wet/dry vacuum or water extractor cleaning machine is excellent for this job.
    It can be rented from various shops - look at the Yellow Pages. Allow them to
    dry out thoroughly.
</p><h3>Clothing</h3><p>
			<strong>Always read the label</strong>. If the clothing can withstand bleaching it can be treated
      with the following mixture: half a cup or domestic ammonia to 2 gallons
      of water. Rinse in vinegar (wear kitchen gloves). If the clothes require
      dry
    cleaning - contact a specialist shop for advice.</p><h3>Smells</h3><p> This is a complex problem due to the materials used in the home and those which
      have been involved in the fire. Contact a specialist cleaning company, or
    for less severe smells, use a room deodorising product.</p><h3>Ceilings and Walls</h3><p>  Unpapered walls may be washed down using a mild soap or detergent. Wash a small
      area at a time. Rinse with clean water immediately. Wallpaper cannot be effectively
      cleaned unless it is washable. Use a cloth soaked in a mild detergent and
    wrung out. Clean with water and repaste edges of paper if necessary.</p><h3>Furniture</h3><p>  For upholstered furniture, a wet/dry vacuum can be used or contact a specialist
      cleaning company from Yellow Pages. White spots on wood may be removed by
    turpentine or ammonia, then dry and polish.</p><h3>Food</h3><p>  If in doubt - throw it out. Fresh food should generally be thrown out if contaminated
      by smoke. Food in glass jars should be discarded if the jar is cracked
      and has been subjected to heat. Tinned food should be thrown out if the
      tin has
      bulged or been subjected to heat.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=819"> Providing Information
		(819)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
