<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=97}]"><cms:name>council-housing--crime-97</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Council Housing - Crime</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=97}]"><cms:name>council-housing--crime-97-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>council, housing, crime</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=97}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If any tenant is a victim of a crime, such as homophobic crime, racist crime, or general crime, they should contact the Police, but also advise the Council of the problem. </i></p><hr/><p>It is likely that if a crime is perpetrated against a tenant whilst in their home, or whilst in the vicinity of their home, the person commiting the crime may be in breach of their Conditions of Tenancy and it may be possible to either ensure that they do not repeat their actions or potentially that they could be evicted.</p><p>Another major crime is burglarly.  Most burglars are not master criminals. They're usually young men looking for an easy opportunity to get into a house without being seen.</p><p>Once they have been in and got away with it, they may be back again unless you do something. And there's lots you can do. Don't rely on one or two precautions. Here is a list of things that will help you beat the burglar! 
			</p><h2>Outside - Your First Line of Defence</h2><p>
			<strong>1. Walls and Fences </strong>
			<br/>
High fences are hard to climb, but they give a burglar cover once he's over. So keep them low. The best fences have a trellis on top - they're a beggar to climb. </p><p>
			<strong>2. Lighting </strong>
			<br/>
Get an outdoor light with a sensor that comes on when someone's around.</p><h2>Is Anybody Home? </h2><p>
			<strong>1. Lights </strong>
			<br/>
You can get plug-in timers for your lamps - and timers for your ceiling lights. Don't just light up the hall. Fool a burglar by lighting up the landing, bathroom, bedroom and living room too. Really fox him by varying the times each light comes on. </p><p>
			<strong>2. Sound Advice </strong>
			<br/>
Use a plug-in timer for a radio - make it a talk station rather than music. Radio 4 is good - it lasts all night. </p><p>
			<strong>3. Curtains </strong>
			<br/>
    Get a trusted neighbour to shut the curtains if you're away. You could return the favour some time!</p><h2>Help Yourself - Get Equipped</h2><p>
			<strong>1. Mortice Locks</strong>
			<br/>
Your front and back outside doors are thick enough for a five-lever mortice-lock. Make sure it's British Safety Standard BS3621.</p><p>
			<strong>2. Window Locks </strong>
			<br/>
  The best type for a wooden frame does not involve any of the window catches - it pulls the window onto the frame with a key. Fit two locks on a big window. 
			</p><p>
			<strong>3. Double Glazing </strong>
			<br/>
  The safest double glazing has bolts that shoot into the frame for extra security. Laminated glass is better than toughened because it stays in place when it's smashed - slowing a burglar down. It's safer for kids too because toughened glass shatters into tiny bits. 		</p><p>
			<strong>4. Patio Doors </strong>
			<br/>
  Make these safer with a purpose-made lock or a security bar. 		</p><p>
			<strong>5. French Windows </strong>
			<br/>
If both parts of your French windows open, and you only fit a lock to one - the other is a weak point. Consider mortice bolts for the top and bottom of each door. Fit them into the frame - not the other door.	</p><p>
			<strong>	6. Keys </strong>
			<br/>
Keep spares with a neighbour, friend or relative - not in the house. And never leave keys in the door. </p><p>
			<strong>					7. Dogs </strong>
			<br/>
Don't rely just on your dog to protect your home. Council tenants need permission to have dogs in certain types of property.			</p><p>
			<strong>8. House Alarms </strong>
			<br/>
  When alarms sound, most burglars grab what they can and run for it. Whichever type of alarm you choose, get a professional fit it. 			</p><h2>				Keep Them Out			</h2><p>
			<strong>1. Doorstep Crooks </strong>
			<br/>
  Some criminals won't go to the trouble of breaking into your home if they can just knock and be invited in. But don't get it out of proportion - you've probably had many genuine callers at your front door and not one trickster. Bogus callers come in all shapes and sizes: young kids, pregnant women, and men - from the overalled to the uniformed to the suited. 
			</p><p>
			<strong>
					2. Bogus officials </strong>
			<br/>
  Water board officials <strong>never</strong> need to come into your home to test water pressure or repair leaks - even in emergencies. If they ever do need to get in they must send you a letter first making an appointment. Gas and electricity meter readers want you to check their identity before you let them in. If in doubt, ring up and check. Genuine callers don't mind this in the least. Keep the phone numbers handy. Shut the door while you're checking - genuine callers don't mind! You could always join the password scheme so the meter reader gives you an arranged password when they call. 		</p><p>
			<strong>3. Look Before You Open </strong>
			<br/>
  Always look to see who's at the door before you open. 			</p><p>
			<strong>4. Door Viewer </strong>
			<br/>
  If your front door doesn't have glass, fit a spy-hole. Or get into the habit of looking through a window near the door to see who is calling. 			</p><p>
			<strong>5. Door Light </strong>
			<br/>
  An outside light over the door will help you see a caller in the dark. 			</p><p>
			<strong>6. Door Chain </strong>
			<br/>
If you need to open the door to make further checks, use a door chain or similar device.			</p><h2>				Remember... 			</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">					don't let people in until you know who they are      
				</li>
			<li title="*">					keep the door locked while you check their story
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">					if you let someone in, stay with them all the times
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">					never part with money or other things, whatever they say
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>If suspicious - ring the Police</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">					get more than one estimate for work
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">					official organisations usually write first
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">					check identity cards thoroughly
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">					don't let callers put pressure on you to let them in;
                
				</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>If in doubt - Keep Them Out!</strong>
			</li>
		</ul><h2>				Coded for Keeps 			</h2><p>
			<strong>1. Ultra-violet Marking </strong>
			<br/>
UV marker pens cost about &#xA3;1 from stationers and security shops. Use them to put your postcode and house number in invisible ink on the bottom of your valuables. If your things are found, the police can read your details under UV light and get things back to you. Redo this every year, as the writing fades. 			</p><p>
			<strong>2. Photographs </strong>
			<br/>
For small items like jewellery, photograph them against a ruler. A picture is worth a thousand words!		</p><h2>				Gardens and Sheds 			</h2><p>
			<strong>1. Shed Security </strong>
			<br/>
Remember to postcode anything of value in your shed. Your lawn mower will be harder for the burglar to sell on with your house number and postcode painted across it. 		</p><p>
			<strong>2. Padlocks </strong>
			<br/>
A good quality padlock - and the hasp and staple that go with it - is important on all sheds and garage side-doors. It's best to bolt the hasp and staple to the door and frame for extra strength.</p><p>
			<strong>3. Screw Heads </strong>
			<br/>
Smear glue over the heads of screws or use anti-tamper screws. 			</p><p>
			<strong>4. Bicycles </strong>
			<br/>
Lock bikes to something fixed or bulky like a ladder or workbench. 			</p><p>
			<strong>5. Garden Tools </strong>
			<br/>
Don't leave them lying around the garden, a burglar could use them to break in. 			</p><h2>				Home Watch 			</h2><p>				  Protecting your home is fine, but you will enjoy greater security and peace of mind if everyone around is working with you. An enthusiastic home watch scheme will deter burglars. Contact your local police station for help setting one up. 			</p><h2>				And Remember...			</h2><p>
			<strong>Prevention is better than cure.</strong>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=97"> Providing Information
		(97)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
