<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=55}]"><cms:name>batch-20-55</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Business rates - reductions relief

	</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=55}]"><cms:name>batch-20-55-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>business, rates, reductions, relief</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=55}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Revenues and Benefits/Finance</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>There are a number of different reductions available</i></p><hr/><h3>Transitional relief</h3><p>After each revaluation there is a period of transition. No bill is allowed to increase or decrease by more than a set percentage. Any property with a large increase or decrease in its rateable value will therefore come under the transitional relief scheme, which has the effect of phasing the valuation in over a period of time. If transitional relief applies to your rates bill, it will be applied automatically.</p><h3>Empty properties</h3><p>If a property is empty and unused, no business rates are normally payable for the first three months and 50% of the full bill is payable after this period has elapsed. Some types of business property are exempt from empty property rates. An exemption will automatically be applied to your bill, if appropriate, when you advise the council that the property has become empty. </p><h3>Charity relief</h3><p>Charities are entitled to an 80% reduction in their bills. The Council has the discretion to reduce the bill further. In addition, the council has the discretion to grant relief to some other types of non-profit making bodies. Application forms can be requested on-line.</p><h3>Rural rate relief</h3><p>If your business property is in a designated rural area, you may be able to claim rural rate relief. Application forms can be requested on-line.</p><h3>Hardship relief</h3><p>This discretionary relief can be granted by the council if you are experiencing hardship and your business is considered to be important to the local community.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=55"> Providing Information
		(55)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
