<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=313}]"><cms:name>batch-23-313</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Care/scan/community alarm services</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=313}]"><cms:name>batch-23-313-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Disabled</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>care, scan, community, alarm, services</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=313}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The community alarm service provides peace of mind for people who feel at risk in their own homes. It is a 24 hour 365 day monitoring service giving you the freedom to live your life independently knowing that you can obtain assistance when you need it.</i></p><hr/><p>If you would like to know more about the Community Alarm Service we will be pleased to arrange a free demonstration in your own home. Please contact us using the details above for more details.</p><h3>Who is the Service For</h3><p>The service is available to anyone who feels at risk in their own home because of age, disability, isolation, illness or vulnerability.</p><h3>How the Service Works</h3><p>The Community Alarm service works via a special alarm unit connected to the telephone line. The alarm unit has a built in button, which you press to obtain assistance, alternatively the alarm can be activated by a remote pendant which is worn around 
  the neck or on a wrist band. The range of the pendant allows use around the house and garden.</p><p>The person requiring assistance presses the built in alarm button or the body worn pendant, this send signals down the telephone line to the alarm centre where the specialist equipment is able to automatically tell staff who the call is coming from.</p><p>Your alarm call will be answered by one of our highly trained operators who will be able to speak to you without you having to lift the telephone receiver. In an emergency, the alarm operator will contact such persons as you previously agreed should be contacted in such circumstances, and/or the appropriate emergency service. You will be kept informed by our operators of any action being taken on your behalf.</p><p>Don't worry if you press the alarm by accident. The operator will enquire after your well-being and once satisfied that you do not require assistance, will terminate the call.</p><h3>Security</h3><p>The Community Alarm Service can be adapted to meet many needs. Victims of crime or those who fear burglary can feel reassured that assistance is available at the press of a button. Fixed alarm buttons can be installed at entrance doors giving clients the opportunity to call for assistance should there be an unwelcome visitor.</p><p>Alarms can also be installed in shops and offices giving staff a means of obtaining assistance, this is particularly useful where members of staff are working alone.</p><h3>Cost</h3><p>
			<span class="gen">enter details</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=313"> Providing Information
		(313)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
