<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=149}]"><cms:name>housing-3-149</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Fair rents inspection - homes in multiple occupation</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=149}]"><cms:name>housing-3-149-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>fair, rents, inspections, homes, multiple, occupation</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=149}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Rent Acts (Maximum Fair Rent) Order is a Statutory Instrument (secondary legislation introduced 
  by the Government) which came into effect on 1 February 1999. The Order made changes 
  to the way in which Rent Officers and Rent Assessment Committees register rents 
  following the assessment of fair rent for properties let since before 15 January 
  1989.</i></p><hr/><p>Inspections are carried out by this Authority into homes in multiple occupation and look for disrepair, inadequate facilities and means of escape, dangerous or defective lifts, general mis-management and overcrowding. The assessment may be used in addition to the determination by the Fair Rents Inspection, as the Rent Officer will consider whether your home has more rooms than the housing benefit rules say you need. </p><p>The Rent Officer is primarily responsible for the constitution and the working of rent assessment committees, which hear appeals from either landlords or tenants and determines appropriate rents for their property. The Rent Assessment Panel is a Non Departmental Public Body whose function is to determine appropriate rents for those properties in the private rented sector.</p><p>For further information about Fair Rents and Fair Rent inspections, please use the contact details above. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=149"> Providing Information
		(149)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
