<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=717}]"><cms:name>housing-3-717</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Landlords accreditation scheme</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=717}]"><cms:name>housing-3-717-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>landlords, accreditation, scheme</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=717}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Private landlords can benefit from belonging to a local accreditation 
  scheme</i></p><hr/><p>Local authorities up and down the country are increasingly taking 
  a strategic approach to the housing needs of everyone in their community. They recognise 
  the important role of the private rented sector in providing accommodation for a 
  diverse range of households. </p><p>As part of this new approach, many local authorities 
  are seeking to work with residential landlords and give them a stake in decisions 
  that affect them. This is being done in a number of ways. For example, by offering 
  landlords information that helps them to manage their properties better, by arranging 
  meetings or forums where landlords can exchange views with local authority officers 
  and, increasingly, by setting up voluntary accreditation schemes that recognise 
  and reward landlords who manage their properties to a good standard. </p><p>This information looks at the role of accreditation schemes 
  for landlords, the benefits of joining one and where to find more information. </p><h2>What is accreditation?</h2><p>A set of standards (or code) relating to the management or physical 
  condition of privately rented accommodation. Landlords who join a scheme and abide 
  by the standards are &quot;accredited&quot;. Accreditation schemes are voluntary. 
  There is no compulsion for landlords to join, but there may be many advantages.</p><h2>What types of accreditation are available? </h2><p>This may differ from area to area. No two accreditation schemes 
  are exactly the same. However, there are two main types - schemes that accredit 
  the person who manages the property and those that accredit the property itself. 
  Most schemes combine elements of both but the &quot;unit&quot; of accreditation 
  is normally the property. For example, schemes may include criteria relating to 
  property condition, management practices and the landlord's past management record. 
  The standards set by schemes also vary. Some set high standards from the outset, 
  whereas others seek to increase standards progressively over time.</p><h2>Do all of my properties have to be accredited? </h2><p>Most schemes that accredit properties do not require landlords 
  to include all the properties they let. However, landlords are encouraged to bring 
  other properties forward at a later stage. Schemes that accredit landlords usually 
  require them to submit all of their properties within the boundaries of the scheme 
  for approval. </p><h2>If accreditation is voluntary why should I join?</h2><p>There are a number of benefits common to all accreditation schemes 
  and many schemes offer other incentives as well. All accredited landlords benefit 
  from:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">the status of being publicly identified as a good landlord; 
    </li>
			<li title="*">distancing themselves from incompetent or unscrupulous landlords;</li>
			<li title="*">the business advantage of advertising their accredited status 
    to tenants who place emphasis on good quality and well managed accommodation. 
    </li>
		</ul><p>Incentives offered vary from scheme to scheme but may include: 
  </p><ul>
			<li title="*">a liaison officer who can help landlords to deal with any 
    department of the local authority, similar to a 'one stop shop'; </li>
			<li title="*">an improved relationship with housing benefit departments; 
    </li>
			<li title="*">information on housing management and access to training 
    and development opportunities; </li>
			<li title="*">consultation on proposals that may affect landlords, such 
    as changes to legislation or local housing strategies; </li>
			<li title="*">access to grants and loans to renovate properties to relevant 
    standards set by the scheme; </li>
			<li title="*">advice on how to tackle anti-social behaviour; </li>
			<li title="*">discounts and group purchase on goods and services such as 
    property insurance; and </li>
			<li title="*">access to rent deposit or rent guarantee schemes operated 
    by the council. </li>
		</ul><h2>What benefits are there for tenants? </h2><p>Tenants can benefit from knowing that if they choose to rent 
  from an accredited landlord, the property will be in good condition and the tenancy 
  will be managed to a good standard. </p><h2>What benefits are there for local communities? </h2><p>Accreditation schemes provide a range of benefits to local communities. 
  It is in everyone's interests if housing is well managed and kept in good condition. 
  A successful accreditation scheme can help to increase the supply of good quality 
  accommodation, to the benefit to existing tenants and potential tenants who may 
  not have considered renting privately in the past. It also helps to foster better 
  landlord/tenant relationships and reduces the need for intervention by council officers. 
  </p><h2>Who operates accreditation schemes? </h2><p>Most schemes are run by local authorities. In some areas schemes are run by other organisations 
  with an interest in housing provision. For example, universities may operate schemes 
  in areas where there is a large student population. The Northern Ireland Housing 
  Executive runs a scheme in Northern Ireland.</p><h2>Can letting agents join an accreditation scheme?</h2><p>The National Approved Letting Scheme is an accreditation scheme 
  which is open to all letting agents and estate agents who manage residential accommodation. 
  The scheme sets minimum service standards for agents and requires them to handle 
  their clients' money safely. More information can be found on the NALS website at 
 
		<a href="http://www.nalscheme.co.uk">
				<strong>www.nalscheme.co.uk</strong>
			</a>	.<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><h2>Can tenants be accredited too? </h2><p>Some schemes offer accreditation for tenants who agree to abide 
  by standards of responsible behaviour and respect their accommodation, neighbours 
  and the contractual agreement with their landlord. There are many advantages to 
  accredited tenant status when seeking alternative accommodation. </p><h2>Where can I find out more? </h2><p>Use the contact details above for advice about accreditation schemes operating in the area. </p><p>Alternatively, or for more general information about accreditation, 
  contact the
		<a href="http://www.anuk.org.uk">
				<strong>National Accreditation Network UK</strong>
			</a>	.  <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><p>The Office of the Deputy Prime Minister has published research 
  and good practice guidance on 
		<a href="http://www.odpm.gov.uk/stellent/groups/odpm_housing/documents/page/odpm_house_601792-01.hcsp">
				<strong>landlord accreditation schemes</strong>
			</a>	.<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=717"> Providing Information
		(717)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
