<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=418}]"><cms:name>batch-6-418</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Pollution control - contaminated land</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=418}]"><cms:name>batch-6-418-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>environmental, health, Pollution, control, contaminated, land</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=418}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Some land in this country has been contaminated in the past by industries such as:</i></p><hr/><ul>
  <li title="*">gasworks</li>
  <li title="*">tanneries</li>
  <li title="*">chemical works</li>
  <li title="*">landfills</li>
</ul><p>These are often called brownfield sites. </p><h3>The Problem</h3><p>Brownfield sites can be a problem for two reasons:</p><li title="*">There may be harmful substances in, on or under the land</li><li title="*">Water pollution might be caused by substances at the site</li><p>However, brownfield sites do not generally cause a problem unless they are redeveloped 
  for a different use.</p><h3>'Pollutant linkage'</h3><p>Land is only declared 'contaminated' if:</p><li title="*">it contains a source of pollution - the source and</li><li title="*">someone (or something) could be affected by the pollutant - the receptor and</li><li title="*">the pollution can get to the 'receptor' - the pathway</li><p>These three elements together are known as the pollutant linkage.</p><h3> Action required</h3><p>If you own or occupy contaminated land now, or you did in the past, you may be 
  responsible for cleaning up the pollution. You may still be responsible for cleaning 
  up the pollution after you have sold the land.</p><p>Some contamination can be a hazard to current occupants or neighbours and the law 
  says the problem must be put right immediately.</p><h3> Who pays?</h3><p>The law follows the 'polluter pays' principle - the person or organisation that 
  caused or permitted the contamination must pay to have it put right. If that person 
  or organisation is not known, then the current owner of the land may become responsible.</p><p>Owners and occupiers of domestic properties are not usually liable for these costs.</p><h3> Re-use of brownfield sites</h3><p>The approval of an application for redevelopment of these sites will only be granted 
  on condition that the contamination is cleaned up to a standard that makes it suitable 
  for the new use of the land.</p><p>You should obtain specialist advice from an environmental consultant or a specialist 
  lawyer before you buy or sell contaminated land. When you buy land in Elmbridge, 
  the Land Charges department at the local council will tell you if a site has been 
  declared 'contaminated land'.</p><h3> What the local council does about contaminated land</h3><p>The local council is responsible for enforcing the 'contaminated land' legislation. 
  The council:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">publishes a Contaminated Land Strategy, which says how it will find contaminated 
    sites in its area</li>
  <li title="*">carries out inspections of land that may be contaminated</li>
  <li title="*">finds out who is responsible for putting right the contamination and discusses 
    the problem with them</li>
  <li title="*">formally declares land contaminated</li>
  <li title="*">agrees the necessary action and makes sure it is done</li>
  <li title="*">keeps a Public Register of contaminated land sites, the action that was required 
    to put the problem right and any legal action that has been taken.</li>
</ul><p>In some cases the Environment Agency may take over the regulation of a site from 
  the council, once it has been declared as 'contaminated land'.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=418"> Providing Information
		(418)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
