<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=432}]"><cms:name>-432</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Dog Warden Service</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=432}]"><cms:name>-432-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience></cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>Dog, Warden, Service, environmental, health</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=432}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Dog Warden will help you if you lose your dog, and aims to help prevent
  stray dogs from being a danger in traffic or a nuisance to people.</i></p><hr/><p>In particular, the service aims to deal with problems caused by the four main
  symptoms of irresponsible dog ownership:-</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Noisy dogs </li>
  <li title="*">Aggressive dogs </li>
  <li title="*">Dog fouling </li>
  <li title="*">Straying dogs </li>
</ul><p>The first time a dog is caught straying, the dog wardens will try to trace
  the owners and return it.</p><p>Any other stray will be kept safely for up to seven days.</p><p>Any complaint regarding dogs straying on school premises or interfering with
  the flow of traffic will be dealt with urgently.</p><p>Any complaints about dogs will be responded to as quickly as possible, but
  always within 2 working days. The Dog Warden will act in the strictest confidentiality
  and keep you informed about what they are doing.</p><p>Some complaints cannot be dealt with by the Dog Warden. These will be passed
  quickly to the appropriate agency (e.g. the Police or RSPCA).</p><p>The Dog Warden will ensure the Council's legal duties are met, so far as dogs
  are concerned. They will also regularly patrol beaches and other areas covered
  by dog related by-laws, and put up anti-dog fouling stickers where needed.</p><p>If you have any questions or complaints, please contact the Dog Wardens.</p><h3>School Talks</h3><p>Part of our job is educational. Primary Schools in the <span class="gen">enter location</span> can
  arrange for a Dog Warden to visit and talk to pupils about all aspects of responsible
  dog ownership.</p><p>If you are a teacher at a school in the <span class="gen">enter location</span>, you can e-mail us
  for further details.</p><h3>Dogs on Beaches</h3><p>Dogs are banned from certain beaches during the summer season.</p><h3>Tag your dog!</h3><p>Your dog must wear a tag by law when out in a public place.</p><p>The first time we catch your dog straying we will return it to you, free of
  charge. But we can only do this if it is wearing a tag, or is microchipped.</p><p>If we catch a stray dog, and we can't trace the owner, we will keep it in
  boarding kennels at your expense. If you do not collect your dog within seven
  days, you will lose the right to reclaim it, and we will try to re-home it.</p><h3>Fouling Legislation!</h3><p>The Dog (fouling of land) Act 1996</p><p>The Dog (fouling of land) Act 1996 came into force on 1st May 1997.</p><p>This Act means that it is illegal to fail to clear up after your dog if it
  fouls any land which is open to the air and to which the public have access.</p><p>The penalty for contravening the Act is a <span class="gen">enter amount</span> &quot;on the spot&quot; fine
  or prosecution in the magistrates court.</p><p>You may purchase, at cost price, biodegradable plastic &quot;Doggy Bags&quot; from
  the public offices of the Council.</p><h3>The Dog Warden Service: </h3><ul>
  <li title="*">Responds to all complaints as soon as possible but always within 2 working
    days.</li>
  <li title="*">Responds urgently to sightings of stray dogs on school premises or interfering
    with traffic.</li>
  <li title="*">Collects and return your stray dog free of charge the first time it is
    collected, provided it has a collar and address tag.</li>
  <li title="*">Collects all other strays and keeps them safely for a maximum of seven
    days for collection by the owner (subject to the payment of a fee). We then
    work with local Re-homing charities and have an excellent record of successful
    home placements.</li>
  <li title="*">Promotes responsible dog ownership through talks to Primary schools and
    other groups.</li>
  <li title="*">Provides (at cost price) supplies of award winning &quot;doggy bags&quot; to
    dog owners.</li>
  <li title="*">Enforces dog-related by-laws and the Dogs (Fouling of Land) Act 1996.</li>
  <li title="*">Microchips dogs in promotion of responsible ownership.</li>
</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=432"> Providing Information
		(432)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
