<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=433}]"><cms:name>batch-6-433</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Renovation Grants</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=433}]"><cms:name>batch-6-433-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>Renovation, Grants, environmental, health</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=433}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We may be able to help you undertake repairs and improvements to your home if your situation meets our criteria and funding priorities.</i></p><hr/><p>House Renovation Grants may be available if your home is deemed unfit to live in and you, as owner/occupier, cannot afford to pay for essential repairs. Only the most serious defects qualify - such as the lack of a bath or an inside toilet, or the presence of extensive dampness, for example - and the applicant's income is taken into account when determining whether council assistance is appropriate. We have a policy in place to ensure these discretionary grants are fairly and properly awarded and comply with the Central Government scheme. This stipulates the conditions that must apply when grants are awarded.</p><p>Disabled Facilities Grants may be made for modifications to the homes of people with disabilities if the renovations will enable them to continue living at home or will improve their quality of life. The work might entail installing access ramps or replacing a bath with a shower, for example. We will need to carry out an assessment of the applicant's disability in order to decide the
  most appropriate modifications or adaptations to be made to the property.</p><p>Home Repair Assistance Grants can help with minor works. The scheme limits the grants to &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span> per application and they are available only to applicants on very low incomes who also meet certain other criteria.</p><p>Normally all these types of grants are made only to applicants who are freeholders or leaseholders of the property concerned. But private or housing association tenants may sometimes qualify for Disabled Facilities Grants or Home Repair
  Assistance Grants.</p><p>If you are eligible for our help, you will need to obtain estimates from two different contractors covering all of the works set out in the Grant Schedule. Once you have received confirmation from us that your application has been approved, you must use one of these two contractors to carry out the work or the council will not pay out the grant.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=433"> Providing Information
		(433)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
