<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=497}]"><cms:name>planning-497</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Town centre management - crime prevention</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=497}]"><cms:name>planning-497-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Householder</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>town, centre, management, crime, prevention</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=497}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>It is now widely recognised that there is a link between design and crime and that careful attention to the planning of towns and to the design of estates and individual buildings can help reduce crime. </i></p><hr/><h2>
				Government Policy
			</h2><p>
				Policy is set out in Circular 5/94 &quot;Planning Out 
  Crime&quot;, which states that planning proposals can help reduce crime, particularly 
  if they are considered as part of a strategic approach incorporating a wide range 
  of measures, including, for example, estate or town centre management and CCTV. 
  The Circular accepts that crime prevention is a 'material' planning consideration 
  which can legitimately be taken into account in preparing plans and deciding planning 
  applications. 
			</p><p>
				The circular suggests that if areas, such as town centres, 
  are occupied after dark, the presence of people produces informal supervision which 
  reduces vandalism and crime. A mix of users, including housing and entertainment 
  will ensure that the area does not become a deserted and therefore potentially threatening 
  environment. 
			</p><p>
				The regeneration of large housing estates should incorporate 
  measures such as diversification of tenure, the creation of smaller community areas, 
  the provision of facilities for the young and proposals to create a more attractive 
  environment, since it has been shown that packages of such measures are successful 
  in reducing crime. 
			</p><p>
				Detailed design measures can help reduce vandalism 
  and crime. Attractive, well cared for environments are less prone to vandalism, 
  but in some cases it is recognised that the need for crime prevention measures will 
  have to be balanced against visual amenity. Thus with landscaping it is important 
  to avoid planting which can screen wrong doers close to footpaths, but the use of 
  spiky bushes can help deter crime. Footpaths should be straight, wide, well lit 
  and well supervised by passers by and overlooking residents. Car parks should be 
  well lit and supervised where possible. Shutters on shops may be necessary but should 
  be attractively designed, for example with open grilles, to avoid 'dead' shopping 
  frontages and graffiti. 
			</p><p>
				Liaison between the developer, the planning authority 
  and the police can ensure that new developments have crime prevention measures built 
  into their design. 
			</p><h2>
				Suggested Guidelines
			</h2><p>
				It is suggested that the following guidelines be adopted and that they be 
  used in the preparation of development briefs and in the control of development. 
  
			</p><h3>General</h3><ul>
				
					<li title="*">Crime prevention should be taken into account in the planning of all developments.</li>
					<li title="*">The Police Architectural Liaison Officer should be consulted about major development 
    proposals. </li>
				
			</ul><h3>Town Centres</h3><ul>
				
					<li title="*">A mix of uses - shop, food and drink and entertainment, and residential should 
    be encouraged within centres to ensure the presence of people throughout day and 
    night, whilst avoiding undue concentrations of uses such as pubs, which could 
    give rise to public order problems.</li>
					<li title="*">Security shutters, where necessary, should be of an open grille design, integrated 
    into the design of the shopfront and should be painted to match. Special consideration 
    should be given within Conservation Areas. They are not appropriate on Listed 
    Buildings. </li>
				
			</ul><h3>Housing Estates</h3><ul>
				
					<li title="*">Larger estates should make provision for open spaces where children can play 
    in safety but without disturbing residents.</li>
					<li title="*">All public spaces - roads, footpaths and open spaces and play areas should be 
    well lit and overlooked by dwellings. Footpaths to the rear of properties should 
    be avoided where possible.</li>
					<li title="*">Private spaces, such as rear gardens, should be clearly demarcated by high walls 
    or fences.</li>
					<li title="*">Landscaping should avoid creating hiding places close to footpaths and spiky 
    bushes could be used to deter unwanted visitors. </li>
				
			</ul><h3>Commercial Development</h3><ul>
				
					<li title="*">Comments on landscaping as above.</li>
					<li title="*">Security considerations should be integrated into the design process and consideration 
    should be given to building design and security lighting as well as security fencing.</li>
				<li title="*">Fences should be attractive and robust and chain link 
  fences, concrete post and panel fences should be avoided in prominent locations.</li>
			</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=497"> Providing Information
		(497)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
