<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=499}]"><cms:name>planning-499</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Building Control</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=499}]"><cms:name>planning-499-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Householder</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>building, control</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=499}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Building Control system exists to make sure that buildings are properly designed and constructed so as to ensure the health, safety, welfare and convenience of people using them. </i></p><hr/><p>The current Building Regulations were introduced in 1991 and have subsequently been amended several times. The principal areas covered by the regulations are: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Structural stability - will the building safely carry anticipated loadings or will it fall down?!</li>
  <li title="*">Fire precautions - both controlling the materials used according to the degree of risk and making sure that buildings could be evacuated without loss of life in the event of a fire.</li>
  <li title="*">The prevention of dampness and condensation in buildings.</li>
  <li title="*">Sound resistance of walls and floors between dwellings.</li>
  <li title="*">Ventilation of habitable rooms and unheated voids.</li>
  <li title="*">Hygiene, sanitary appliances and drainage.</li>
  <li title="*">Heating appliances including the safe discharge of flue gasses.</li>
  <li title="*">Stairways, ramps and vehicle barriers.</li>
  <li title="*">Conservation of fuel and power. Is the building properly insulated etc.</li>
  <li title="*">Access to buildings and facilities for disabled people.</li>
  <li title="*">The safe positioning of glazing in windows and doors etc. </li>
</ul><p>Building control generally operates as a two-stage process, referred to as the Full Plans application. The first stage (known as the plan stage) involves the applicant submitting detailed plans for approval. These plans are very carefully checked by a Building Control Officer to ensure that all necessary information is shown, and that it complies fully with the Building Regulations. Wherever possible, applicants are given the opportunity to make amendments (if required) before either an approval, conditional approval or rejection is given. </p><p>The second stage (inspection stage) starts when work commences on site after which a series of site visits are made to check that the work proceeds in accordance with the plan, and hence complies with the regulations. </p><p>For more simple works an alternative, called the Building Notice application, is also available together with more specialised application types to meet specific needs.</p><p>If you require further information on Building Control, please use the details above to contact us. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=499"> Providing Information
		(499)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
