<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=512}]"><cms:name>planning-512</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Conservation and urban design planning - conservation advice</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=512}]"><cms:name>planning-512-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Householder</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>conservation, urban, design, planning, advice</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=512}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Section 69 of the Civic Amenities Act 1969 gives local 
  Councils the power to designate as Conservation Areas, &quot;areas of special architectural 
  or historic interest, the character or appearance of which it is desirable to preserve 
  or enhance&quot;. </i></p><hr/><p>
				Designation gives control over the demolition of buildings and 
  provides the basis for policies designed to preserve or enhance all the aspects 
  of character or appearance that define an area's special interest.
			</p><h2>
				How are Conservation Areas chosen for Designation?
			</h2><p>
				Conservation Areas vary, ranging from historic town centres to industrial and 
  rural villages.
			</p><p>
				They are designated usually because of their buildings 
  but they can also be designated because of their history, architecture, layout or 
  private spaces, such as gardens, parks and greens; trees or street furniture. Conservation 
  areas give broader protection than listing individual buildings and all features 
  within the area, listed or otherwise, are recognised as part of its character. 
			</p><h2>
				Who designates Conservation Areas?
			</h2><p>
The Council has the power to designate and it has designated areas where people 
  generally feel have a special character worth protecting or enhancing. 
			</p><h2>
				What does designation mean?
			</h2><p>
				Within a Conservation Area the Council has extra controls 
  over the following: 
			</p><h3>
				Demolition
			</h3><p>
				To fully demolish a building, or even parts of it, 
  needs Conservation Area consent. Generally we view an application from the stand point of trying to retain 
  the building so a b case needs to be made for its demolition. There are no 
  fees for this application and there is a right of appeal against refusal. 
			</p><h3>
				Minor developments
			</h3><p>
				In a conservation area, you need planning permission 
  for changes to buildings which would normally be permitted. Changes requiring consent 
  include cladding a building, inserting dormer windows, or putting up a satellite 
  dish visible from the street.
			</p><h3>
				Trees
			</h3><p>
				Anyone proposing to cut down, top or lop a tree in 
  a conservation area, whether or not it is covered by a tree preservation order, 
  has to give notice to the Council. The Council considers the contribution the tree 
  makes to the character of the conservation area and if necessary it will make a 
  tree preservation order to protect it. 
			</p><h2>
				What does the Council normally do in Conservation Areas?
			</h2><p>
				The Council consults widely on proposals affecting 
  a conservation area. This might include periodic enhancement schemes including proposals 
  to:
			</p><ul>
				
					<li title="*">Prepare development briefs for sites in conservation areas;</li>
					<li title="*">Ensure that new buildings harmonise with their neighbours;</li>
					<li title="*">Make environmental improvements;</li>
					<li title="*">Control advertisements and shop signs;</li>
					<li title="*">Ensure that traffic control measures harmonise with the character of the area.</li>
					<li title="*">Make grants available for the repair of buildings.</li>
				
			</ul><h2>
				What policies are used to control development?
			</h2><p>
				Our main body of conservation policy is in the Unitary 
  Development Plan which includes conservation policy with wider planning policies 
  for the area. Policies in the Conservation section generally presume against the 
  loss of features which add to the special interest of the areas. These policies 
  are used in the determination of planning applications in conservation areas. 
				
				 
			</p><p>
				Local residents and businesses generally are fully 
  aware that areas have been designated and how their character and appearance are 
  protected.
			</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=512"> Providing Information
		(512)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
