<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=539}]"><cms:name>road-markings-and-signage--cycle-lanes-and-routes-539</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Road Markings and Signage - Cycle Lanes and Routes</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=539}]"><cms:name>road-markings-and-signage--cycle-lanes-and-routes-539-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>road, markings, signage, cycle, lanes, routes</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=539}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Cycle Routes are principally indicated by signs and markings. They may be either on the carriageway, on footways either shared with or segregated from pedestrians, or specially designated cycle paths.  </i></p><hr/><h4>Toucan Signals </h4><p>  These are special traffic signals, similar to pelican crossings - they have a red man and green man to show when it is safe to cross - but they also have an extra signal, a green cycle. This means that cyclists need not dismount, but can cross over at the same time as pedestrians.</p><h4>Advanced Cycle Stop Lines</h4><p>Within ordinary traffic signalled junctions, there are two sets of stop lines on each approach. The one further from the signals is
for general traffic, and the one nearer to the signals is for cyclists. This is to give space for cyclists wishing to turn right to safely change from the nearside to the offside.</p><h4>Contra-Flow Cycle Lanes</h4><p>When a one-way street is introduced this gives little inconvenience for motorists, but can mean that cyclists have to travel much further. A contra-flow cycle lane lets a cyclist travel against the direction of flow of the one-way street in safety and offers a more convenient and direct route.</p><p>The problem is that for a safe contra flow lane, the cyclists must be segregated at each end from the oncoming traffic by a traffic island. This can only be done if the road is wide enough. It may also need to have a parking ban throughout the length of the contra flow lane. This can be difficult in some residential areas with limited off-street parking. </p><h4>&quot;Plug&quot; No Entry </h4><p>This is where a road is two way throughout its length except for a short length of one-way working at one end. This means that
entry into the road is banned at one end and traffic is only allowed to exit. To assist cyclists, a short gap allows cyclist to travel past the no-entry signs.</p><h4>Traffic Signage</h4><p>A full catalogue of traffic signage and road markings can be found on the 
		<a href="http://www.highwaycode.gov.uk/signs_index.shtml">
<strong>Highway Code</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span> website, which includes those that are applicable to cyclists.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=539"> Providing Information
		(539)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
