<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=543}]"><cms:name>road-markings-and-signage--speed-humps-543</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Road Markings and Signage - Speed Humps</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=543}]"><cms:name>road-markings-and-signage--speed-humps-543-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>road, markings, signage, speed, humps</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=543}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Council receives many requests from residents for these to be introduced in their roads to reduce speeds and improve safety. </i></p><hr/><p>There is usually opposition from the Police, Fire Brigade, Ambulance Service and Bus Companies to the use of speed control humps. The Emergency Services object because humps increase their attendance times for emergency calls, and thus risk the lives and property of the people. The Ambulance Service and Bus Companies object because of the discomfort and possible injury that may be caused to their passengers and the increased wear and tear on vehicles, particularly buses going over speed tables every day.</p><p> There are regulations governing the layout of speed control humps. There must be a form of &quot;slowing feature&quot; - usually formed by a change of priority (traffic entering the system has to turn sharp left or right into the road, or has to &quot;give way&quot;. Sometimes
    mini roundabouts are used at the start of a system of humps.</p><p>The shape of speed control humps are strictly regulated. They must be between 50mm and 100mm high, at least 2.75m long
    and extend over the full width of the road, except for a drainage channel at either end. They may have either flat tops or round tops. Many local authorities have adopted the 75mm high hump as a standard. This is because it has been found to reduce traffic to around 22 mph. The 100 mm high humps reduce speeds to 17 mph on the hump but speeds rise to 35 mph between the humps, causing excessive acceleration, braking and increased pollution. Flat topped humps can be of any length and are often known as &quot;speed tables&quot;. They are sometimes used to reduce the impact on long wheel base vehicles such as buses.</p><p>Speed control humps can lead to complaints about increased noise and sometimes increased vibration from traffic. They have
    however been proved to reduce traffic speed and they have been installed in many locations.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=543"> Providing Information
		(543)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
