<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=551}]"><cms:name>roads-and-highways--enforcement-551</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Roads and Highways - Enforcement</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=551}]"><cms:name>roads-and-highways--enforcement-551-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>roads, highways, enforcement</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=551}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Council has a duty to protect the public rights on the road and footpath network. The effectiveness of legislation in protecting the public is dependant on the compliance of others.</i></p><hr/><p>Officers from time to time are required to deal with businesses and individuals who for whatever reason breach the		 statutory protection relating to highways. The initial aim of officers is to assist businesses and others to comply with their 		legal obligations without unnecessary expense or hardship. However, ultimately, firm action will be taken against those who 		disregard the law.</p><p>Enforcement action areas include, Public Rights of Way, Highways and Highways Works associated with new 			developments.</p><p>Countryside staff have a duty to ensure that public rights of way are open and safe for use, free from obstruction and
      	clearly marked. They are responsible for checking that works requested of owners/occupiers of land eg. repair of stiles and 		clearance of crops have been carried out to a suitable standard.</p><p>The Council, as Highway Authority, has a duty to maintain adopted highways to safe and serviceable standards. Staff 		have to protect the rights of the public to the use and enjoyment of such highways by ensuring they are free from nuisance, 		danger, obstructions, unlawful stopping up, interference and encroachments.</p><p>Carriageways, footways, verges and footpaths serving new developments will be adopted by the Council and maintained
	      at public expense provided they have been constructed in accordance with the Authority's standards.</p><p>The Council, as Street Authority, has a duty to co-ordinate works on the highway, including the works of Statutory     		Undertakers, in the interests of safety, public convenience, the protection of the structure of the street and the integrity of 		apparatus in it.</p><p>The Council also has powers regarding the timing of Street Works and the restriction of such works within 12 months of 		the completion of substantial road works.</p><p>Staff ensure that the requirements contained in the New Roads and Street Works Act 1991, and its supporting Codes of 		Practice, including those for traffic management and reinstatements are carried out effectively and efficiently.</p><p>Officers may deal with matters informally or formally and the action may lead to prosecution.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=551"> Providing Information
		(551)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
