<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=552}]"><cms:name>roads-and-highways--weight-limits-552</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Roads and Highways - Weight Limits</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=552}]"><cms:name>roads-and-highways--weight-limits-552-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>roads, highways, weight, limits</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=552}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Weight restrictions can be imposed for structural or for environmental reasons. It is legal control on a specified vehicle weight or width, mainly on lorries, on certain roads and routes.</i></p><hr/><p>The restriction prevents large vehicles from using inappropriate roads, routes and areas in order to:</p><ul>
		<li title="*">Reduce danger to pedestrians and other road users</li>
		<li title="*">Prevent damage to buildings, roads and bridges</li>
		<li title="*">Preserve the character, amenity and environment of an area</li>
		<li title="*">Reduce and manage congestion on the roads</li>
		<li title="*">Procedures for implementation</li>
		<li title="*">Restrictions are subject to a Traffic Regulation Order (TRO) and the associated procedures (see Fact Sheet on Traffic Regulation Orders)</li>
		<li title="*">Regulatory signs are erected on site to give effect to the TRO and to assist the police in carrying out its enforcement</li>
		</ul><h4>Enforcement</h4><p>This is a matter for the Police. However, the Police have limited resources to enforce this type of restriction (especially
    environmental restrictions). Restrictions with &quot;except for access&quot; clauses quickly fall into disrepute and are notoriously difficult to enforce. However these are needed to permit HGV access to local shops, businesses, residential properties for deliveries/removals etc. For this reason, enforcement commands a low priority and therefore, where possible, physical measures should be introduced to prevent any abuse of the restrictions - the installation of signs alone are wholly ineffective. Restrictions will not be used if there is no suitable alternative route for the displaced traffic.</p><h4>Additional Considerations</h4><p>Where a Traffic Regulation Order restricts the use of a road, route or area to certain vehicles, the signing of a recommended
    alternative route will need to be considered.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=552"> Providing Information
		(552)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
