<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=657}]"><cms:name>batch-11-657</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Alley gating</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=657}]"><cms:name>batch-11-657-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>alley, gating</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=657}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>An effective deterrent against Burglars!</i></p><hr/><p>'Alley-Gating' is a very simple crime preventative measure which involves erecting steel, self locking gates to the ends of alley-ways and passages that are the responsibility of the home owners who live around them. There are a number of other advantages in addition to reducing the levels of burglaries which include:-</p><ul>
				<li title="*">Reduced opportunities for youths to cause annoyance - This could mean anything from drinking in the alleys to taking drugs.</li>
				<li title="*">Fewer problems of dog fouling by stray dogs</li>
				<li title="*">Safe play areas for children</li>
				<li title="*">Improved community spirit giving a sense of ownership of the alleys</li>
			</ul><h3>How to apply for and implement a successful 'alley-gating' scheme:-</h3><li title="*">Complete the application for grant funding and return it to us <span class="gen">enter address</span>
</li><li title="*">Check whether the alley that you wish to gate is unadopted. This is to ensure that what you will be doing is strictly within the law.</li><li title="*">Obtain signatures from all those affected by the gates to indicate that they are in approval to alley gates being erected. This is to ensure that no-one can claim that they were not in agreement.</li><li title="*">Once the order has been placed and the gates erected the original invoice should be sent to the Council. We will inspect the works and, provided they are satisfactory, will arrange for a cheque payable to the contractor to be forwarded back to yourself at which point payment can be made.</li><li title="*">You should also request a few extra sets of keys to the gates in case neighbours move and forget to leave their keys behind.</li><li title="*">Agree a system for wheelie-bin management with your neighbours. The refuse collection service will not keep copy keys and therefore all residents should ensure that the bins are placed outside of the gates on the day of collection and returned once they have been emptied. Consideration should also be given to the elderly and disabled who may struggle to move their bins. Arrangements should be made between all residents to assist those people that may require help. </li><p>Thought should also be given to an on-going maintenance fund for the gates. We would suggest that all residents contribute a small sum of a few pounds per year to be placed in a communal bank account to fund any maintenance or repairs that they may require.</p><p>Should you wish to engage a contractor direct then you must provide him with a copy of the Council's specification for gates which has been drafted with the help of the Police. The gates are security gates and are designed to last a number of years and to ensure conformity throughout the Council. The same specification should be used by all contractors.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=657"> Providing Information
		(657)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
