<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=352}]"><cms:name>credit-unions-352</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Credit Unions</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=352}]"><cms:name>credit-unions-352-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>credit, unions</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=352}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A Credit Union is a profit sharing, democratically run financial co-operative which offers convenient savings and low interest loans to its members. The members own and manage their credit union themselves.</i></p><hr/><p>
			<strong>The three main aims of
a Credit Union are:</strong>
		</p><ul>
			<li title="*">To encourage its members to save regularly.</li>
			<li title="*">To provide loans to members at very low rates
    of interest.</li>
			<li title="*">To provide members with help and
    support on managing their financial affairs (if required).</li>
		</ul><h2> What
are the benefits of a Credit Union?</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">It is an easy and convenient
        way to save and borrow.</li>
			<li title="*">It offers very low cost loans.</li>
			<li title="*">Insurance at no direct cost.</li>
			<li title="*">It's a way to learn new skills.</li>
		</ul><p>Credit unions can provide a focal point for a
    community by bringing people together, to work alongside each other for their
    own benefit and the benefit of the community as a whole with organised events,
family fun days, quizzes, etc. </p><p>A credit union can help to revive the local economy
    by keeping money in the community. Loans to Members can mean income for local
    shops and businesses.</p><h2>Who
supports Credit Unions?</h2><p>Churches, Community Groups, National Consumer Councils,
  Citizens Advice Bureau, Trading Standards, Police, Fire, Taxi Drivers, Local
  Authorities, etc.</p><h2>How do they work?
</h2><p>The members make regular savings, as little or
    as much as they wish. These savings then form a common pool of money from
    which loans are made to members. When members have been saving for a certain
    period of time (usually about 12 weeks) they can apply for a loan from the
    pool. Interest on the loan is charged at only 1% per month on the monthly
reducing balance. 12.68% Annual Percentage Rate (APR).  </p><h2>
			<strong>Who
can join a Credit Union?</strong>
		</h2><p>People who join a Credit Union must belong to
    what is called a &quot;Common Bond&quot;. This could be that you reside in a specified
    area, or you work for a particular employer or that you are a member of a
club or association. </p><p>Credit Unions welcome everybody from within the
    Common Bond regardless of income, employment status or age. </p><h2>How
do you join a Credit Union?</h2><p>If you wish to join a Credit Union but are unable
    to visit in person, the Council will arrange for a representative of the
    Credit Union Office to contact you. Please complete
the <strong>
				
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/352a">on-line
form</a>	
			</strong>. <span class="gen">link to online form</span>
		</p><h2>How
much do I have to save?</h2><p>Whatever you can afford
- &#xA3;5 a week, &#xA3;1 a week, 50p a week. The only requirement is that
you save regularly.</p><h2>Will
I get interest on my savings?</h2><p>As a Credit Union grows it may declare a dividend
    at the end of the financial year. It can pay a dividend of up to 8% a year,
    although it will be unlikely to be able to afford as much as this during
the first few years. </p><h2>How soon and how much can I borrow from the
Credit Union?</h2><p>Most credit unions expect you to save regularly
    for about 12 weeks before allowing a loan and any loan will be related to
    your savings in some way. </p><p> The amount you will be able to borrow will depend
    on how much you need, what you can afford to repay, and the credit union's
    policies. In the early days the credit union will allow small loans, becoming
    bigger as the credit union gets ber. </p><h2>Security</h2><p>Credit Unions have to be registered with the Financial
    Services Authority (FSA). </p><p>They are covered by the Credit Union Act 1979. </p><p>They are independently audited. </p><p>They are regularly monitored by the FSA. </p><p> Your business is private in the credit union
    because all members and Officers who have access to personal information
    must act in a confidential manner at all times.</p><h2>Are
they Insured?</h2><p>They are insured against
fraud and theft. </p><p>They provide life and loan protection insurance
    at no direct cost to the member payable to a nominated beneficiary. </p><p>The life savings insurance means that if you die,
    your beneficiary can receive up to twice the value of your shares. </p><p>   The loan protection insurance covers the amount of your loan outstanding. </p><h2>Where
do Credit Unions exist?</h2><p>In most of the world, credit unions are well established.
    Starting in Germany 150 years ago they spread throughout Europe, to North
    America, Canada, Asia and to Ireland. One third of the adults in Ireland
    are members of a credit union. Credit unions are steadily increasing throughout
    the UK both in communities and the work place (eg. Police Force, British
    Airways, Fire Service, local authority
employees etc.). </p><h2>Community
and Employee Credit Unions in the Area</h2><table width="90%" cellpadding="5" class="centre" summary="Community and Employee Credit Unions in the Area">
			<tr>
				<th>Name and Address   </th>
				<th>Hours of Business</th>
				<th>Venue</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table><h2>Other
Credit Union Sites</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.abcul.org/">The Association
            of British Credit Unions (ABCUL)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.aicu.co.uk/">The
            Association of Independent Credit Unions (AICU)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.nacuw.org.uk/">
					<strong>National Association of Credit Union Workers</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
			</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=352"> Applications for services
		(352)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
