<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=822}]"><cms:name>media-and-publicity-protocols-822</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Media and Publicity Protocols</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=822}]"><cms:name>media-and-publicity-protocols-822-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>media, publicity, protocols</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=822}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>In 2001, the national Code of Recommended Practice on Local Authority Publicity was amended to include changes in council constitutions introduced by the Local Government Act 2000. These amendments were approved by Parliament and a new Code has been issued. Local authorities are required to 'have regard to the provisions' of this Code in the way we approach communication. </i></p><hr/><p>The Code gives guidance on communications between communities, individual
  people and local authorities and aims to foster effective and impartial communication.</p><h2>Principles and Protocols</h2><p> The Council undertakes to maintain a full and
steady flow of information to the media so as to ensure:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Continued public awareness of
    the services provided by the authority and the functions it performs;</li>
<li title="*">Advance and ongoing publicity on matters
    of public interest;</li>
<li title="*">Those affected by the Council's decisions,
        policies and priorities are given the information to understand them
    and to have a real and informed say about them.</li>
</ul><p>The principle of executive decision-making and accountability will be bly reflected in the Council's media liaison arrangements. In particular: </p><ul>
<li title="*">Media statements on Executive
        decisions will be made by the appropriate Executive member (or their
        substitute), the Leader of the Council or issued on behalf of the entire
    Executive.</li>
<li title="*">Interviews on Executive decisions will only
        be given by the appropriate member of the Executive, their substitute
    or the Council Leader.</li>
<li title="*">The Executive will be given relevant support,
        advice and training to enable them to play a proactive role in presenting
        issues to the media, explain their work and manage controversial issues
    covered by the media.</li>
<li title="*">Where the press office is asked to draft
        press releases or letters on behalf of the Executive, such releases/letters
        will be of a factual nature and will contain nothing that could be construed
    as politically motivated or biased.</li>
<li title="*">All official Executive press releases will
    be issued by the Press Office in the standard format.</li>
</ul><p>The work of the Overview and Scrutiny panels is an important and integral part of the new political arrangements for the purposes of media liaison. In particular: </p><ul>
<li title="*">Media statements and interviews
          on Overview and Scrutiny matters will be made by the convenor of the
          relevant panel, their substitute or, if appropriate, by the chair of
      the Overview and  Scrutiny Management Board.</li>
<li title="*">Interviews on Overview and Scrutiny matters
          will be given by the convenor of the appropriate Overview and Scrutiny
          Panel, their substitute or, if appropriate, by the chair of the Overview
      and Scrutiny Management Board.</li>
<li title="*">Members of Scrutiny and overview panels
          and the Chair of the Overview and Scrutiny Management Board will be
          offered relevant support,advice and training to enable them to play
          a proactive role in presenting issues to the media and explain their
      work.</li>
<li title="*">Where a minority report is released by
          a member or members of an Overview and Scrutiny Panel, media statements
          will be the responsibility of those issuing the report.</li>
<li title="*">Where the press office is asked to draft
          press releases/letters on behalf of Overview and Scrutiny, such releases/letters
          will be of a factual nature and will contain nothing that could be
      construed as politically motivated or biased. </li>
<li title="*">All official Overview and Scrutiny press
      releases will be issued by the Press Office in the standard format.</li>
</ul><p> The work of local councillors will be recognised
    as an important contributor to the Council's community leadership role. In
particular:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Advice will be available to local
        members in promoting local issues through the media - with training made
        available</li>
<li title="*">Whilst it is legitimate for the Council to
        publicise local issues, the Council will not involve itself in any publicity
        which 'personalises' such issues and thereby appears to be designed to
        affect public support for a political party</li>
</ul><p>The continuing role of full Council will also be recognised in the Council's communication with the Media. In particular:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Media statements on policy and
        other matters which are the remit of full Council (other than the simple
    reporting of decisions taken) will be made by the Group Leaders</li>
<li title="*">Media enquiries on such matters will be referred
    to the Group Leaders</li>
<li title="*">Group leaders will be given relevant and
        appropriate support, advice and training to enable them to deal effectively
    with the media.</li>
<li title="*">The Executive Leader of the Council will
        be supported in making best use of the media to promote his or her special
        role as
    ambassador for the Council.</li>
</ul><p>  The work
    of regulatory bodies and committees (planning, licensing etc) is acknowledged
    as an important element, and key decisions and issues for decision will be
publicised in consultation with relevant spokespersons and lead officers.</p><p> The general policy of the Council will continue
        to be one of openness and accessibility towards the media. Although officers
        will not be allowed to comment to the media on Executive
        decisions  they may continue to speak to the media within clearly
        defined parameters on operational and other matters. These parameters
    are:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Where they have been specifically
            delegated to speak to the media by the Leader, Executive, relevant
        Executive Member or Chair of the relevant Overview/Scrutiny panel.</li>
<li title="*">On matters of clarification with reference
            to officer reports submitted for consideration to Executive, Scrutiny,
        full Council or to regulatory committees.</li>
<li title="*">To explain the operational detail of
        decisions and policies they are implementing.</li>
<li title="*">On issues pertaining to the exercise
        of professional judgement.</li>
<li title="*">Normally, only First or Second Tier Officers
            should speak to the media. On non-contentious matters where it would
            be more appropriate for this to be done by someone with specialist
            or technical knowledge, Directors/Heads of Service may delegate -
        but only to named individuals who have undergone media training.</li>
</ul><p> Council Media liaison will normally be carried
    out via the Council's Communications and Marketing team or other designated
communications staff with specific media liaison responsibilities.</p><ul>
<li title="*">All the Council's media contact
        will be professionally managed to meet the communication needs of the
    Council and of the media.</li>
<li title="*">To improve the quality of the Council's media
        output and response, all necessary support/advice/training will be offered.
        Media liaison will only be carried out by staff who have received training
    approved by the Communications and Marketing Manager.</li>
<li title="*">All news
        releases will be issued through the press office in standard format,
        or through designated departmental outlets with specialist media liaison
    responsibilities.</li>
<li title="*">Incoming press calls will be fielded initially
        by the press office or other designated communications staff who will
    respond on behalf of the Council where appropriate. </li>
<li title="*">Designated Press Officers are empowered to
        make statements on behalf of the Council, presenting the Council's position
        on high profile and other matters and helping build and protect the Council's
    reputation.</li>
</ul><p>
<strong> Underpinning all aspects of this protocol is the general principal, enshrined in Government legislation that the Council will not involve itself in any publicity which appears to be designed to affect public support for a political party.</strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">In addition to this general principal
        is a detailed Code of Recommended Practice on local authority publicity,
        issued by the Secretary of State, which highlights the factors to be
    borne in mind when taking decisions on publicity.</li>
<li title="*">Copies of this Code of Practice will be made
        available to Members and Officers, and will inform any discussion and
    decision.</li>
<li title="*">Paragraphs 38, 39 and 40 are particularly
    relevant, and are reproduced below:</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Individual Councillors</strong>
</p><li title="*">Publicity about individual
             councillors may include the contact details, the position they hold
             in the Council (for example, member of the Executive or Chair of
             Overview and Scrutiny Committee), and their responsibilities. Publicity
             may also include information about individual councillors' proposals,
             decisions and recommendations only where this is relevant to their
             position and responsibilities within the Council. All such publicity
             should be objective and explanatory, and whilst it may acknowledge
             the part played by individual councillors as holders of particular
             positions in the Council, personalisation of issues or personal
         image making should be avoided.</li><li title="*">Publicity should not be,
             or liable to misrepresentation as being, party political. Whilst
             it may be appropriate to describe policies put forward by an individual
             councillor which are relevant to her/his position and responsibilities
             within the Council, and to put forward her/his justification in
             defence of them, this should not be done in party political terms,
             using political slogans, expressly advocating policies of a particular
             political party or directly attacking policies and opinions of other
         parties, groups or individuals.</li><p>
<strong>Elections</strong>
</p><li title="*">The period between the notice
             of an election and the election itself should preclude proactive
             publicity in all its forms of candidates and other politicians involved
             directly in the election. Publicity should not deal with controversial
             issues or report views, proposals or recommendations in such a way
             that identifies them with individual members or groups of members.
             However, it is acceptable for the authority to respond in appropriate
             circumstances to events and legitimate service enquiries provided
             that their answers are factual and not party political. Members
             holding key political positions should be able to comment in an
             emergency or where there is a genuine need for a member level response
             to an important event outside the authority's control. Proactive
             events arranged in this period should not involve members likely
         to be standing for election.</li><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=822"> Providing Information
		(822)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
