<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=824}]"><cms:name>european-resource-procurement--european-funding-824</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>European Resource Procurement - European Funding</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=824}]"><cms:name>european-resource-procurement--european-funding-824-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>european, resource, procurement, funding</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=824}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The European Union budget is made up of a proportion of the VAT charged on goods and services in the Member States, a share of each countries Gross National Product and custom duties from non-EU countries on goods which are imported into the EU.&#xA0; </i></p><hr/><p>A large proportion
    of these resources are redistributed into four Structural Funds each used
    to promote the economic and social development of the regions perceived to
    be
    lagging behind. </p><p>A region may have access to one or more of the
four Structural Funds, depending on whether it has Objective 1 or 2 status; all
    regions have Objective 3 status. The four Structural Funds are:</p><ul>
    <li title="*">
<strong>

		<a href="#ERDF">The European Regional Development Fund (ERDF)</a>	
</strong>
</li>
<li title="*">
<strong>

		<a href="#ESF">The European Social Fund (ESF)</a>	
</strong>
</li>
<li title="*">
<strong>

		<a href="#EAGGF">European Agricultural Guidance and Guarantee
    Fund (EAGGF)</a>	
</strong>
</li>
<li title="*">
<strong>

		<a href="#FIFG">The Financial Instrument for Fisheries
    Guidance (FIFG)</a>	
</strong>
</li>
</ul><h2>

			The European Regional Development Fund (ERDF)</h2><p>The European Regional Development Fund (ERDF)
    was set up in 1975 to stimulate economic development in the least prosperous
regions of the European Union (EU).</p><p>The ERDF aims to improve economic prosperity and
  social inclusion by investing in projects to promote development and encourage
  the diversification of industry into other sectors in areas lagging
  behind. This fund is available in Objective 1 and 2 areas.</p><p>ERDF is aimed at economic regeneration projects 
promoted by the public sector. This involves:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Government Departments </li>
<li title="*">Regional Development Agencies 
      (RDAs)</li>
<li title="*">Local Authorities</li>
<li title="*">Further and Higher Education establishments</li>
<li title="*">Other public bodies</li>
<li title="*">Community and Voluntary Sector
      organisations</li>
</ul><p>In certain circumstances, the fund can help the 
  development of small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs). Private sector companies 
  are encouraged to present applications in partnership with a public sector body. 
  </p><p>
<strong>Individuals 
  may not apply</strong>
</p><p>There is no limit set for ERDF projects. Projects 
  may request up to 50% of the total costs from ERDF. The rest of the funding, 
  known as 'match funding' comes from other sources such as:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Regional Development Agencies </li>
<li title="*">Local Authorities</li>
<li title="*">Government schemes including the 
      Single Regeneration Budget</li>
<li title="*">Other Public Bodies</li>
<li title="*">The Private Sector</li>
<li title="*">Paid Staff and Volunteer time</li>
</ul><p>You can find a guide to potential sources of match funding on the DTI web site 
at <strong>

		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/">www.dti.gov.uk</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
</p><p>For
    further information on bidding for ERDF in this area, please contact <span class="gen">enter details</span>
    </p><h2>

			The European Social Fund (ESF)</h2><p>The ESF funds training, human resources and equal
opportunities schemes to promote employability of people in both Objective 1
    and
3 areas.</p><p>ESF is the main source of finance that the EU
uses to help create and protect jobs. It supports the National Action Plan
for Employment (NAP) which is produced every year. The NAP sets out the
main UK policies and initiatives in line with the European Employment
Strategy. It is written by the UK Government for England, Scotland, Wales
and Gibraltar.</p><p>The ESF is used to give financial support towards
    the running
costs of projects run by a variety of organisations. These projects can
include those for training, employment, education, research and childcare. ESF
also supports Government programmes, including New Deal.</p><p>The whole area of eligibility for European
funding is a complex one. If you meet the following criteria you may be
eligible to apply for European Social Funding.</p><p>You are a legally constituted organisation
          (i.e formed with a legal document such as an agreement of memorandum
          of association). Large companies are eligible to apply for ESF
          providing they work in partnership with small and medium sized enterprises
          (SMES) and at least 50% of the beneficiaries will be from SMES.</p><p>
<strong>Individuals cannot apply for European
    Social Fund money.</strong>
</p><p>Your organisation is involved in an activity in one of the supported measures
        and is currently in receipt of financial support from the public sector
        (typically 10% of total costs).</p><h3>Active Labour Market Policies</h3><p>
<strong>Measure 1: To provide advice, guidance,
          and support to enable people to develop active and continuous job search
    strategies and prevent them from moving into long term unemployment.</strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">Supporting additional measures
    to enhance the UK's active benefit regime</li>
<li title="*">Active and guidance</li>
<li title="*">Enhancing advice, guidance and community
    education through innovative systems and approaches</li>
<li title="*">Involving business in schools to encouraging
    employability and motivation</li>
<li title="*">Early interventions, including advice and
    guidance, using new forms of Information Technology</li>
<li title="*">Improving job brokerage to enable a better
    match between supply and demand</li>
 </ul><p>
<strong>Measure 2: To improve the employability of the unemployed returners and young people of working age through targeted intervention to enhance vocational and other key skills and remove external barrier to labour market entry. </strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">Providing support through integrated approaches,
        including the provision of vocational social and key skills including
    confidence building</li>
<li title="*">Job rotation initiates for the very long
    term unemployed</li>
<li title="*">Encouraging unemployed people to start their
    own businesses</li>
<li title="*">Encouraging local partnerships approaches
        to Intermediate labour markets projects and assisting unemployed people
    in the open labour market</li>
<li title="*">Improving the capacity for community development</li>
    </ul><h3>Equal Opportunities
    and Social Inclusion</h3><p>
<strong>Measure 1: To widen access to basic skills, directed at those groups disadvantaged, excluded or under-represented in the work place </strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">Supporting intensive interventions to meet
        the needs of the client group through vocational guidance, training
    and employment support measures.</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 2: To
          provide help to improve the employability and remove barriers to labour
          market entry for those groups disadvantaged in the labour market and
          to develop local responses to assist individuals with multiple disadvantage
    in the labour market who face the risk of social exclusion.</strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">Providing intensive support to enable target
    groups to reach levels of basic employability</li>
<li title="*">Supporting pre-entry training related to
    identified labour market needs</li>
<li title="*">Providing integrated packages which meet
    the needs of lone parents and returners</li>
<li title="*">Customised training related to labour market
    opportunities (including those specifies in the NWDA Strategies)</li>
<li title="*">Capacity building actions to ensure that
        ESF reaches those groups in the greatest need and to encourage local
    development and community delivery of ESF activities</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 3: To
          combat discrimination in thelabour market, in particular to combat
          race, disability and age discrimination and improve the employability
    of these groups.</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Researching into institutional discrimination
    and follow on actions to combat discrimination </li>
<li title="*">Supporting initiatives to improve recruitment
    and promotion systems to eliminate institutional discrimination</li>
    </ul><h3>Lifelong Learning</h3><p>
<strong>Measure 1: Promoting
          wider access and participation in lifelong learning (especially those
          groups least likely to take part in lifelong learning activities and
    lacking basic and key skills)</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Supporting collaborative action through Learning
        and Skills Councils, Local Learning Partnerships, Further and Higher
    Education Establishments and through SMEs</li>
<li title="*">Providing individuals with ICT skills</li>
<li title="*">Providing individuals with basic and key
        skills and reducing the risk of those with inadequate skills falling
    behind</li>
<li title="*">Extending access through more innovative
        means, including community and family, and through helping individuals
    develop and manage their own learning</li>
<li title="*">The identification and promotion of means
        which can open up access to learning for those adults currently least
    engaged with the education system</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 2: Improving
          employability through directing and supporting lifelong learning provisions
          that it is responsive to the changing needs of employers, such
    as in the fields of IT, management and the environment</strong>
</p><ul>
   <li title="*">Supporting businesses especially SMEs by
    equipping the workforce with the right skills</li>
<li title="*">Skills forecasting and ensuring that skills
    training relates to the RDA regional economic strategy</li>
<li title="*">Forging links between business and support
    networks</li>
</ul><h3>Adaptability
    and Entrepreneurship</h3><p>
<strong>Measure 1: To
          update and upgrade employee's vocational skills including basic and
    key skills</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Promoting employee development by updating
        and upgrading vocational skills, while considering new methods of delivering
        basic skills - provision of advice and guidance, training trainers and
    managers and promoting the effective use of ICT in SMEs</li>
<li title="*">Equipping workers threatened with redundancy
        with training and funding to turn good ideas in to viable businesses
    and supporting innovation and creativity.</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 2: To
    identify and meet emerging skill shortages, including higher level</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Identifying
        skill shortages within all sectors, including new skills emerging from
    the knowledge driven economy </li>
<li title="*">Providing training to meet identified skills
    shortages, including innovative methods of training delivery</li>
<li title="*">Promoting effective training investment by
        employers and improving the awareness of identified skill shortages with
    teachers in schools</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 3: Encouraging
          entrepreneurship of individuals and competitiveness of business, particularly
    SMEs</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Supporting SMEs to expand and create new
    employment opportunities </li>
<li title="*">Researching into new forms of work organisation
        - flexible working practices with consideration given to family friendly
        policies and strengthening the links between employers and educational
        or training institutions, especially in the fields of science, technology
    and research.</li>
<li title="*">Supporting individuals setting their own
        business such as advice on regulatory aspects, recruitment and business
    planning.</li>
</ul><h3>Improving Women's
    Participation in the Labour Market</h3><p>
<strong>Measure 1: To
    improve access to learning and remove barriers to employment</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Improving the quality and flexibility of
    local training including participation in lifelong learning partnerships </li>
<li title="*">Improving the relevance of skills training
    to local employment needs and opportunities</li>
<li title="*">Tackling barriers, such as childcare and
        other caring responsibilities, raising awareness and promoting family
    friendly policies</li>
<li title="*">Providing vocational training for one to
    enter non traditional occupations</li>
<li title="*">The development of entrepreneurs, especially
    amongst those who have been out of the labour force</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Measure 2: To
          research into issues related to gender discrimination in employment
    such as recruitment, pay, segregation and progression</strong>
</p><ul>
    <li title="*">Research and development of practical recommendations
        to combat occupational segregation, gender stereotyping and institutionalised
        discrimination on recruitment, pay, progression and other aspects of
    employment</li>
<li title="*">Activities to implement the recommendations
    arising from the above research</li>
</ul><p>
      Your application
        for funding is towards running costs only. Individual items exceeding &#xA3;1000
    are not eligible. Other ineligible costs include:</p><ul>
    <li title="*">loan and current account
      interest</li>
<li title="*">other financial charges</li>
<li title="*">consultancy fees for activities
      such as filling in applications, or management fees or commissions</li>
<li title="*">staff time spent filling in
      applications</li>
<li title="*">buying equipment or buildings
      (threshold currently &#xA3;1,000)</li>
<li title="*">costs of finance leases</li>
<li title="*">charging again for equipment or
      buildings which have previously attracted EU funding</li>
<li title="*">any expenditure that does not
      clearly relate to the project</li>
<li title="*">any expenditure which is not
      supported by written sources</li>
</ul><p>As this is a complex area you may wish to discuss
in greater detail your eligibility to apply for European Social Funding by
contacting us.</p><p>ESF pays for a proportion (usually 45%) of a
project's costs. The remaining amount (at least 55%) is known as match
funding. Match funding can come from both public and private sources but
at least 10% must be provided by a public body.</p><p>ESF will contribute to any actual eligible costs
spent in carrying out approved activity. These can include for example
staff and utilities (gas, electricity and water) costs. A full listing
of
ineligible costs is available in the guidance.</p><p>Application deadlines are set by GONW - often
    at
relatively short notice. For the latest information on the deadlines for
bidding please contact us.</p><p>Projects are scored, appraised and selected
through competitive bidding at the regional level.</p><p>To be successful the project will at least:</p><ul>
<li title="*">add value (in other words, would
      not take place or would be less effective without ESF support)</li>
<li title="*">give good value for money</li>
<li title="*">contribute to meeting the ESF
      Objectives or Community Initiative (and therefore, the National Action
      Plan for Employment)</li>
<li title="*">meet the more specific targets
      and requirements of the appropriate Regional Development Plan</li>
</ul><p>ESF support is available between 2000 and 2006
under the current EU regulations. This is known as a &quot;programme
period&quot;. Organisations can apply for more than one project during
this
period. Individual projects are not usually supported for longer than 24
months at a time, although additional funds may be applied for later.</p><h2>

			European Agricultural Guidance and Guarantee Fund (EAGGF)</h2><p>EAGGF is available in rural Objective 1 areas
    to
encourage the restructuring and diversification of rural areas, to promote
economic prosperity and social inclusion, whilst protecting and maintaining the
environment and our rural heritage. In areas outside Objective 1, the
EAGGF (Guarantee section) provides funding within the England Rural Development.</p><h2>

			The Financial Instrument for Fisheries Guidance (FIFG)</h2><p>The FIFG funds projects to modernise the
structure of the fisheries sector and related industries and to encourage
diversification of the workforce and fisheries industry into other
sectors. It also aims to ensure the future of the industry through
achieving a balance between resources and their exploitation.</p><p>
<strong>Further Information</strong>
</p><p>More detailed guidance on funding from the European
    Union is available at: </p><p>
<strong>

		<a href="http://www.cec.org.uk/">www.cec.org.uk</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=824"> Providing Information
		(824)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
