<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=330}]"><cms:name>batch-11-330</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Cremations and funerals - cremation without a funeral director</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=330}]"><cms:name>batch-11-330-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>cremation, without, funeral, director</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=330}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>It is often assumed, quite wrongly, that cremations can be competed only with the use of a funeral director.</i></p><hr/><p>Although a funeral director will be invited to organise the majority of cremations, some people prefer to organise cremations themselves. The details in the individual sections of the Charter for the Bereaved gives sufficient information to achieve this. More detailed leaflets giving you local information on arranging a burial or cremation are available from the Council.</p><p>The funeral director typically organising the cremation by collecting and moving the body, arranging embalming and viewing of the deceased, providing a coffin, hearse and other elements. Carrying out these services relieves the bereaved from doing what they may feel are unpleasant and difficult tasks. Ultimately, the funeral director must operate commercially and in charging for his or her   services, cremations can be expensive. In addition, the funeral director imposes him/herself on the arrangements to a greater or lesser degree.</p><p>Some people do not wish to use a funeral director. This can be for a wide variety of reasons. They may feel that passing the body of a loved one over to strangers is wrong. Some feel that personally organising a cremation is their final tribute   to the deceased person. Others may simply wish to save money by doing everything themselves or may have used a funeral director on a previous occasion and found the experience unsatisfactory. Some may feel that cremations arranged with a funeral director are routine and processed, and some may desire an innovative and different approach. It is, of course, your right to make this decision without giving a reason.</p><p>The entire cremation can be handled by the bereaved family and charter members are able to assist in facilitating this. Such a cremation is referred to as 'Personalised' or 'Independent', rather than the possibly offensive term 'DIY' cremation. These cremations will be different because traditional cremation elements may be unobtainable. Currently, many funeral directors will not sell coffins separately, neither will they offer a hearse for use, unless the entire cremation package is purchased 'Information   on using a Funeral Director'.</p><p>Consequently, personalised cremation arrangers use their own vehicles or hire vans in lieu of a hearse. They may also make their own coffin or use a biodegradable type.</p><p>These actions often attract comments that such cremations lack 'dignity'. It is important to refute this comment. Firstly, dignity is defined by the Concise Oxford Dictionary as 'true worth' and where a personalised cremation accords with the wishes of the deceased or the bereaved, it obviously possess this quality. Secondly, dignity is too often ascribed to standard set by commercial organisations. Consequently, using this argument, the more you spend, the more dignity you can obtain. This is evident in cremations, where the use of a Rolls Royce hearse is perceived to possess a higher level of dignity than, say, a Ford hearse. It is important not to allow such sentiments to deny any individual the right to arrange a cremation without commercial involvement. cremations arranged by the bereaved contain a far higher personal input, which evokes more emotion and often celebrates the life of the deceased in a more moving and individual way.</p><p>It is possible that the dominant and traditional role of funeral directors is diminishing, as new approaches are sought. A new type of 'green' funeral director is emerging, promoting bio-degradable coffins and a more personal approach. cremation facilitators are also appearing. They are people who will assist the bereaved in organising a cremation for a fee. They may offer a vehicle to carry the coffin and assist in handling the body. Other people, such as nurses, may offer laying-out or body preparation services, to avoid people having to do this themselves. this may be particularly relevant when a person dies at home within a 'hospice at home' scheme. These changes are evidence of a return to past times, when various members of the community helped in the completion of a cremation. </p><p> Please see our 
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=331">
<strong>funeral expenses</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 331</span>
</p><p>
<strong>Charter Rights</strong>
</p><p>It is your right to organise a cremation without the use of a funeral director.</p><p>It is your right, as executor (or next of kin) to be given the body by a mortuary, hospital, etc., in order to carry out a cremation without a funeral director.</p><p>It is your right to obtain a coffin (minimum biodegradable type) via your Charter member.</p><p>It is your right to obtain a Personalised or Independent cremation leaflet form your Charter member describing how to arrange a cremation without a funeral director.</p><p>
<strong>Charter Targets</strong>
</p><p>Charter members should ensure that the bereaved are aware of these rights, and that Personalised or Independent cremations offer social as well as financial benefits to the community.</p><p>Charter members should increase coffin choice wherever possible. the availability of a standard chipboard coffin is recommended, as well as a bio-degradable option. Coffins need not be stocked, provided a reliable source is identified. Where   green burial options are offered, a bio-degradable coffin should be available.</p><p>Charter members may need to consider introducing a fee for Personalised or Independent cremations, to reflect any additional work arising over the absence of a funeral director.</p><p>Charter members should consider whether new cremation options can be offered to the bereaved, which reduces the monopoly control of funeral directors. The following services have been suggested for further consideration taking into account the limitations (ultra vires) imposed on local authorities.</p><p>A body collection service without a traditional hearse, followed by cremation and the return or placement of the cremated remains.</p><p>Having a hearse (or equivalent estate car) available for hire, to enable people to carry out cremations.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=330"> Providing Information
		(330)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
