<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=333}]"><cms:name>-333</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Buying a grave</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=333}]"><cms:name>-333-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience></cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>buying, purchasing, grave, graves</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=333}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We appreciate that during this difficult time you will have to make important decisions about the cemetery and grave you want for the funeral.</i></p><hr/><p>The following information will help you make your choice.</p><h3>How do I buy a grave?</h3><p>Normally, your funeral director will help to make the necessary arrangements for buying a grave. Some people may want to make their own arrangements at the time of the funeral. You can organise this by directly contacting us. We will be happy to advise you. If you would like to view the section of the cemetery where the burial is to take place before the funeral, we will arrange for a member of staff to meet with you on the site.</p><h3>How long can I buy a grave for?</h3><p>In the cemeteries we manage, we offer several types of grave. The exclusive right of burial is sold for 50 years. These are known as 'purchased graves'.</p><h3>Who can buy a grave?</h3><p>Only people who live in the <span class="gen">enter location</span> can buy a grave space in the borough's cemeteries.</p><h3>When can burials take place?</h3><p>Burials can take place on any weekday, except on bank holidays. Please talk to your funeral director or contact us to discuss any specific needs.</p><h3>What types of graves are available?</h3><p>
<strong>Traditional grave spaces</strong>
</p><p>These allows the owner of the grave to put a full headstone and surround on the grave after burial.</p><p>All memorials of this type must be built on a concrete base or 'landing'.</p><p>
<strong>Lawn-type graves</strong>
</p><p>We will maintain these special areas, at no expense to the grave owner.</p><p>After the burial, the grave is made level and grassed over. The headstone can have a marble or granite vase plate on which flowers or wreaths can be placed.</p><p>So that we can maintain these areas, nothing else is allowed to be placed or grown on or around the grave and the area in front of the headstone is grassed over.</p><h3>Can I bury cremated remains in the cemeteries?</h3><p>Yes, there are memorial gardens for cremated remains at each of our cemeteries. Cremated remains can also be placed in purchased graves.</p><h3>Are all the graves on consecrated ground?</h3><p>Most of our cemeteries have consecrated (blessed as sacred) and unconsecrated areas where you can buy graves. The consecrated ground is consecrated by the Church of England.</p><h3>What is the difference between unpurchased and purchased graves?</h3><p>
<strong>Unpurchased grave</strong>
</p><p>An unpurchased grave, sometimes known as a public or common grave, is where the right to burial cannot be bought and the council has total control of the grave.</p><p>These graves can be bought within three years of the last burial. The council will decide who will be buried in the grave and this might not be members of the same family.</p><p>No memorial rights exist on public graves so no headstone or other memorial can be put up.</p><p>
<strong>Purchased grave</strong>
</p><p>A purchased grave is where the right of burial can be bought for a period of 50 years, with an option of another 25 years.</p><p>The owner of the right of burial can decide who will be buried in the grave and memorials are allowed in line with our cemetery regulations.</p><h3>How much will it cost?</h3><p>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=331">
<strong>Cemetery Charges</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 331</span>
</p><h3>Memorials</h3><p>We know how important memorials are as a lasting symbol of remembrance.</p><p>We offer technical advice and help to make sure that all memorials meet cemetery regulations.</p><p>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=334">
<strong>Information about memorials</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 334</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=333"> Providing Information
		(333)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
