<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=368}]"><cms:name>cctv-procedure-for-the-release-of-evidence-368</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>CCTV Procedure for the Release of Evidence</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=368}]"><cms:name>cctv-procedure-for-the-release-of-evidence-368-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>cctv, procedure, release, evidence</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=368}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Arguably, Closed Circuit Television (CCTV) is one of the most powerful tools to be developed during recent years to assist with efforts to combat crime and disorder whilst enhancing community safety. </i></p><hr/><p>Equally, it may be regarded by some as the most potent infringement
    of
    people's liberty. If users, owners and managers of such systems are to command
    the respect and support of the general public, the systems must not only
    be used with the utmost probity at all times, they must be used in a manner
    which
    stands
  up to scrutiny and is accountable to the very people they are aiming to protect.</p><p>The
      Council is committed to the belief that everyone
        has the right to respect for his or her private and family life. Although
      the use of CCTV cameras has become widely accepted in the UK as an effective
      security
        tool, those people who do express concern tend to do so over the handling
  of the information (data) which the system gathers. </p><p>After considerable
      research and consultation, a nationally recommended standard
          has been adopted by the system owners.</p><h2>General Policy</h2><p>All requests for the release of data shall be
        channelled
      through the data
              controller or his nominated representative.</p><h2>Primary Request
        To View Data</h2><p>Primary requests to view data generated by a CCTV system
      are likely
              to be made by third parties for any one or more of the following
      purposes: </p><ul>
      <li title="*">Providing evidence
    in criminal proceedings </li>
<li title="*">Providing evidence
    in civil proceedings or tribunals </li>
<li title="*">The prevention of
    crime</li>
<li title="*">The investigation
    and detection of crime (may include identification of offenders)</li>
<li title="*">Identification of
    witnesses</li>
      </ul><p>  Third parties, which are required to show adequate grounds
                  for disclosure of data within the above criteria, may include,
                  but
                  are not limited
                  to: </p><ul>
<li title="*">Police</li>
<li title="*">Statutory authorities
            with powers to prosecute, (eg. Customs and Excise; Trading Standards,
    etc) </li>
<li title="*">Solicitors</li>
<li title="*">Claimants in civil
    proceedings</li>
<li title="*">&gt;Accused persons
    or defendants in criminal proceedings</li>
<li title="*">Other agencies,
            (as agreed by the Data Controller and notified to the Information
    Commissioner) according to purpose and legal status</li>
</ul><p>  Upon
                        receipt from a
                    third party of a bona fide request for the release of data,
                    the data controller shall: </p><ul>
                    <li title="*">Not
            unduly obstruct a third party investigation to verify the existence
    of relevant data. </li>
<li title="*">Ensure the retention
            of data which may be relevant to a request, but which may be pending
    application for, or the issue of, a court order or subpoena. A
    time limit shall be imposed on such retention, which will be notified at
    the time of the request.</li>
</ul><p>  Where requests
                        fall
                        outside
                        the terms
                        of disclosure and Subject Access legislation, the data
                        controller, or
                        nominated representative,
                        shall: </p><ul>
<li title="*">Be
              satisfied that there is no connection with any existing data held
    by the police in connection with the same investigation.</li>
<li title="*">Treat all such enquiries
    with strict confidentiality.</li>
</ul><h2>  Secondary Request To View Data</h2><p>A 'secondary' request
                            for
                            access to data
                            may be defined as
                            any request being made which does not fall into the
                            category of a primary request.
</p><p> Before complying
                              with a secondary request, the data controller shall
                              ensure that: </p><ul>
                              <li title="*">The
            request does not contravene, and that compliance with the request
            would not breach, current relevant legislation, (eg. Data Protection
            Act 1998, Human Rights Act 1998, section 163 Criminal Justice and
    Public Order Act 1994, etc); </li>
<li title="*">Any legislative
            requirements have been complied with, (e.g. the requirements of the
    Data Protection Act 1998);</li>
<li title="*">Due regard has been
            taken of any known case law (current or past) which may be relevant,
    (eg. R v Brentwood BC ex p. Peck); and </li>
<li title="*">The request would
    pass a test of 'disclosure in the public interest'.</li>
</ul><p>   If, in compliance with
                              a secondary
                              request
                              to view data,
                              a decision is
                              taken to release material to a third party, the
                              following safeguards shall be put
                              in place before surrendering the material: </p><ul>
<li title="*">In respect
            of material to be released under the auspices of 'crime prevention',
            written agreement to the release of the material should be obtained
            from a police officer, not below the rank of Inspector. The officer
            should have personal knowledge of the circumstances of the crime/s
    to be prevented and an understanding of the CCTV System Code of Practice.</li>
<li title="*">If the material
            is to be released under the auspices of 'public well being, health
            or safety', written agreement to the release of material should be
            obtained from a senior officer within the Local Authority. The officer
            should have personal knowledge of the potential benefit to be derived
            from releasing the material and an understanding of the CCTV System
    Code of Practice. </li>
</ul><p>  Recorded material
                                may be used for bona fide training purposes such
                                as police or staff training. Under no circumstances
                                will
                                recorded
                                material be released
                                for commercial sale of material for training
                                or entertainment purposes. </p><h2>  Individual Subject Access under
    Data Protection Legislation</h2><p>Under the terms of Data Protection
                                    legislation, individual access
                                    to personal data,
                                    of which that individual is the data subject,
                                    must be permitted providing: </p><ul>
<li title="*">The
    request is made in writing;</li>
<li title="*">A specified fee
    is paid for each individual search;</li>
<li title="*">The data controller
            is supplied with sufficient information to satisfy him or her self
    as to the identity of the person making the request;</li>
<li title="*">The person making the request provides sufficient and accurate information about
        the time, date and place to enable the data controller to locate the
        information which that person seeks, (it is recognised that a person
        making a request is unlikely to know the precise time. Under those circumstances
        it is suggested that within one hour of accuracy would be a reasonable
    requirement);</li>
<li title="*">The person making
            the request is only shown information relevant to that particular
            search and which contains personal data of her or him self only,
            unless all other individuals who may be identified from the same
    information have consented to the disclosure.</li>
</ul><p>  In the event of the data controller complying
                                      with a request to supply a copy of the
                                      data to the subject,
                                      only data
                                      pertaining to the individual
                                      should
                                        be copied, (all other personal data which
                                      may facilitate the identification of any
                                      other person
                                      should be
                                      concealed or erased).
                                      Under these
                                      circumstances an additional fee may be
                                      payable. </p><p>The data
                                        controller is entitled
                                        to refuse an individual request to view
                                        data under these provisions if insufficient
                                        or
                                        inaccurate information is provided, however
                                        every effort
                                        should be made to comply
                                        with subject access procedures
                                        and each request should be treated on
    its own merit. </p><p>In addition to
                                          the principles contained within the
    Data Protection legislation, the data
                                          controller should
                                          be satisfied that the data is:  </p><ul>
<li title="*">Not
            currently and, as far as can be reasonably ascertained, not likely
    to become, part of a 'live' criminal investigation;</li>
<li title="*">Not currently and,
            as far as can be reasonably ascertained, not likely to become, relevant
    to civil proceedings;</li>
<li title="*">Not the subject
    of a complaint or dispute which has not been actioned; </li>
<li title="*">The original data
            and that
the audit trail has been maintained;</li>
<li title="*">Not removed or copied
    without proper authority;</li>
<li title="*">For individual disclosure
    only (i.e. to be disclosed to a named subject).</li>
</ul><h2>  Process of Disclosure</h2><p>Verify the
                                              accuracy of the request. </p><p> Replay the data to the requestee
                                                only, (or responsible person
    acting on behalf
                                                of the
                                                person making
                                                the request). </p><p>  The viewing should take place
                                                  in a separate room and not
          in the
                                                  control
                                                  or monitoring
                                                  area. Only
                                                  data which
                                                  is specific
                                                  to the
                                                  search request
                                                    shall be
                                                  shown. </p><p>  It must not be possible to
                                                    identify any other individual
                                                    from the
                                                    information being shown,
                                                    (any such information
                                                    will be
                                                    blanked-out, either by means
                                                    of electronic screening or
                                                    manual editing on the monitor
                                                    screen). </p><p>  If a copy of the material
                                                      is requested and there
          is no on-site
                                                      means of
                                                      editing out
                                                      other personal
                                                      data,
                                                      then
                                                      the material
                                                      shall be sent
                                                      to an
                                                      editing house
                                                      for processing prior to
          being sent to the requestee. </p><h2>Media Disclosure</h2><p>In
                                                          the event of a request
                                                          from the
                                                          media for
                                                          access to
                                                          recorded
                                                          material,
                                                          the procedures
                                                          outlined
                                                          under
                                                          'secondary
                                                          request
                                                          to view data' shall
    be followed. If material
            is to be released
                                                          the following procedures
                                                          shall be adopted:
    </p><ul>
<li title="*">The
            release of the material must be accompanied by a signed release document
            that clearly states what the data will be used for and sets out the
            limits on its use, and indemnifies the partnership against any breaches
    of the legislation.</li>
<li title="*">The release form
            shall state that the receiver must process the data in a manner prescribed
            by the data controller, e.g. specific identities/data that must not
    be revealed.</li>
<li title="*">It shall require
            that proof of any editing must be passed back to the data controller,
            either for approval or final consent, prior to its intended use by
            the media (protecting the position of the data controller who would
            be responsible for any infringement of Data Protection legislation
    and the System's Code of Practice). </li>
<li title="*">The release form shall be considered a contract and signed
          by both parties.</li>
</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=368"> Providing Information
		(368)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
