<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=676}]"><cms:name>legal-advice-676</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Legal Advice</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=676}]"><cms:name>legal-advice-676-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>legal, advice</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=676}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The idea behind the Community Legal Service (CLS) was for people to find help easily and feel confident in the quality of service they get from legal service and advice providers. The CLS aims to ensure that people can get help and information about their legal rights and understand how to enforce them in the right place and at the right time.</i></p><hr/><p> To
      make it easier for the public to get advice and legal help, the CLS brings
      together organisations offering advice and legal services into local networks.
      These networks include solicitors, Citizens' Advice Bureau, Law Centres,
      local authority services (including libraries), community centres, and
      a host of other organisations. The networks are organised and supported
      by Community Legal Service Partnerships, which are made up of representatives
      of the Legal Services Commission, local authorities, funders and providers
      of advice. </p><p> The
      job of Partnerships is to assess the need for legal and advice services
      in their area. They must also work together to ensure that the right kinds
      of services are available to meet priority needs.</p><p> Details
      of the CLS Partnerships are available on the  
		<a href="http://www.justask.org.uk/">
				<strong>Community
  Legal Service</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> website.</p><h2>Consumer
      Support Network</h2><p>Consumer
          advice agencies are working together as a group to develop a network plan
          to ensure that good quality consumer advice is accessible by the whole community.
          The Consumer Support Networks (CSNs) initiative, encourages consumer advice
          providers to join-up their services and provide consumers, wherever they
        live, with reliable, timely and quality assured advice. </p><p> Consumer
      advice needs to reflect today's complex and fast-changing marketplace.
      It must take account of developments such as the growth of internet shopping
      and the often complicated ways that goods and services are sold. We would
    expect advice available to cover:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">what to look out for when buying goods and services</li>
			<li title="*">consumers' rights and obligations
      when buying goods and services</li>
			<li title="*">how to obtain redress when things
      go wrong</li>
		</ul><p>     Consumer
      Support Networks and the Community Legal Service are complementary initiatives.
      </p><p> For
      more general information see the  
		<a href="http://www.csnconnect.org.uk/">
				<strong>Consumer
  Support Networks</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> website. </p><h2>Community
      Legal Service Quality Mark</h2><p>An
        important principle of the Community Legal Service is that of simple referral
        to the right part of the network. If the first organisation you contact
        cannot help, they should be able to refer to another organisation that
        can. Community Legal Service Partnerships will ensure that advice providers
        in their area take part in a referral network and strongly encourage providers
        to apply for the Quality Mark.</p><p> One
      of the ways to improve access to, and delivery of legal and advice services
      in the community is by setting up and running referral networks. Effective
      referral is also one of the requirements of the CLS Quality Mark. We want
      people to recognise a certain standard of legal information and help. </p><p> When
      you see an organisation that displays the CLS logo, you know that organisation
      meets certain quality standards. If a Community Legal Service provider
      is unable to deal with all aspects of your problem, it can refer clients
      to another Quality Marked organisation.</p><p> For
      more information on the Community Legal Service Quality Mark see the  
		<a href="http://www.legalservices.gov.uk/">
				<strong>Legal
  Services Commission</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> website.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=676"> Providing Information
		(676)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
