<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=688}]"><cms:name>witness-support-688</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Witness Support</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=688}]"><cms:name>witness-support-688-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>witness, support</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=688}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If you report a crime to the police you can expect:</i></p><hr/><ul>
		<li title="*">the police to investigate
    the crime; </li>
<li title="*">in most cases, to be
          contacted by Victim Support - unless you ask the police not to pass
    on your details;<strong>*</strong>
</li>
<li title="*">to be told by the police
    if someone is charged with, or cautioned for, the offence; </li>
<li title="*">to be told (if you
          ask to be) by the police or the Crown Prosecution Service if the charge
    is later dropped or downgraded; </li>
<li title="*">if you are needed as
          a witness, to be given a 'Witness in Court' leaflet, and told the date
    of the trial; </li>
<li title="*">if the case goes to
          court, consideration to be given to making a compensation order in
    your favour;</li>
<li title="*">to be told (if you
          ask to be) the result of the court case; in more serious cases, to
          be told (if you ask to be) the result of any appeal against conviction
    or sentence;</li>
<li title="*">to be given advice
          about applying for compensation for personal injury from the criminal
    Injuries Compensation Authority; and </li>
    <li title="*">to be given crime prevention
    advice if you ask for it.</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>* Not
all categories of crime are routinely referred to Victim Support by the
police</strong>
</p><p>To
help make this possible, you should:</p><ul>
<li title="*">report
    the crime to the police promptly;</li>
<li title="*">give the police full
    details of your injury or loss;</li>
<li title="*">tell the police if
    you want compensation;</li>
<li title="*">tell the police if
    you fear for your (or your family's) safety;</li>
<li title="*">tell the police if
    you do not want them to tell Victim Support or the press;</li>
<li title="*">tell the police of
          any changes of address while the case remains unresolved; and contact
    Victim Support directs if you want to.</li>
</ul><h2>What Happens Next?</h2><p>The
police will try to catch the criminal but they may not always succeed.
If they do have a suspect, there may not be enough evidence to charge the
person or, if the person is young or mentally disordered, and the offence
is not too serious, the police may decide to caution him or her instead.
In some cases the suspect may be facing more serious charges for other
offences and may be prosecuted for those offences instead.

</p><p>If
the police decide to charge someone the case is taken over by the Crown
Prosecution Service (CPS), an independent authority, which prosecutes in
the name of the Queen. They decide whether there is enough evidence to
provide a realistic prospect of conviction and whether prosecution would
be in the public interest. The CPS does not act directly on behalf of individual
victims or represent them in criminal proceedings, but it does carefully
consider the interests of victims when deciding where the public interest
lies.

</p><h2>The Press</h2><p>The
press can play an important role in tackling crime. For the purposes of
investigating an offence, catching criminals or for crime prevention, the
police may release details of a case to the press. If you are concerned
about this happening, tell the police officer dealing with the case.

</p><h2>Going to Court</h2><p>For
the reasons mentioned above, many cases never reach court. Of those that
do the great majority are dealt with by magistrates' courts. The most serious
cases have to be sent to the Crown Court for trial by jury.

</p><p>If
your case goes to court and you are needed as a witness:

</p><ul>
<li title="*">You will
          be sent a copy of the leaflet 'Witness in Court' which will explain
    what is likely to happen.</li>
<li title="*">You should let the
          police know if there are any days you could not manage to attend court
          - for instance, because of important job or professional commitments,
          or because you have a holiday booked. If possible, these dates will
          then be avoided although there may be times when the case has to go
    ahead even though this may not be convenient for individual witnesses. </li>
<li title="*">The aim is that prosecution
          witnesses do not have to wait more than two hours before being called
    to give evidence.</li>
<li title="*">Arrangements will be
          made to provide an interpreter if you are called to give evidence and
    are unable to give it in English. </li>
<li title="*">If you are not needed
          as a witness the police will try to keep you informed about hearing
          dates ( there could be several such dates if, for example, cases are
          delayed or postponed). They will also try to keep you informed of the
    results of the cases. </li>
</ul><h2>Victim Support</h2><p>Victim
Support offer a free, confidential service to vistims of crime. Trained
volunteers based in local schemes contact
people following a crime to offer
free, confidential support and information.

</p><p>Victim Support is an independent national charity.

</p><p>People
are referred to Victim Support by the police and other organisations, or
make direct contact themselves to ask for help.


</p><p>Visit the <strong>

		<a href="http://natiasso03.uuhost.uk.uu.net/site_home.html">Victim
        Support</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to external website</span> website
        for more information.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=688"> Providing Information
		(688)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
