<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=618}]"><cms:name>batch-4-618</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Archaeological consultancy</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=618}]"><cms:name>batch-4-618-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>archaeological, consultancy</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=618}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Importance Of Archaeology</i></p><hr/><p>Archaeological remains are irreplaceable. They are evidence - for prehistoric periods, 
  the only evidence - of the past development of our civilization.</p><p>Today's archaeological landscape is the product of human activity over thousands 
  of years. It ranges through settlements and remains of every period, from the camps 
  of the early hunter gatherers 400,000 years ago to remains of early 20th century 
  activities. It includes places of worship, defence installations, burial grounds, 
  farms and fields, and sites of manufacture.</p><p>These remains vary enormously in their state of preservation and in the extent 
  of their appeal to the public. &quot;Upstanding&quot; remains are familiar enough 
  - the great stone circles, the castle and abbey ruins of the Middle Ages or abandoned 
  coastal defence systems. But less obvious archaeological remains, such as ancient 
  settlements and field systems, are also to be found across large parts of the country. 
  Some prehistoric sites in wetland areas contain important wood and organic remains. 
  Many buildings in older towns lie on top of Roman, Anglo-Saxon or medieval structures.</p><p> Archaeological remains should be seen as a finite and non-renewable resource, 
  in many cases highly fragile and vulnerable to damage and destruction. Appropriate 
  management is therefore essential to ensure that they survive in good condition. 
  In particular, care must be taken to ensure that archaeological remains are not 
  needlessly or thoughtlessly destroyed. They can contain irreplaceable information 
  about our past and the potential for an increase in future knowledge. They are part 
  of our sense of national identity and are valuable both for their own sake and for 
  their role in education, leisure and tourism.</p><p>The present century has been a period of striking environmental change. Some changes, 
  like the erosion of coastal areas, have occurred naturally. But much archaeological 
  heritage has been destroyed by human activity - for example, by modern construction 
  methods in urban development and expansion of the road network, by modern agricultural 
  techniques (in particular deep ploughing or drainage of wetlands), and by mineral 
  extraction.</p><p>With the many demands of modern society, it is not always feasible to save all 
  archaeological remains. The key question is where and how to strike the right balance. 
  Where nationally important archaeological remains, whether scheduled or not, and 
  their settings, are affected by proposed development there should be a presumption 
  in favour of their physical preservation. Cases involving archaeological remains 
  of lesser importance will not always be so clear cut and planning authorities will 
  need to weigh the relative importance of archaeology against other factors including 
  the need for the proposed development. Regardless of the circumstances, taking decisions 
  is much easier if any archaeological aspects of a development site can be considered 
  early on in the planning and development control process. This is discussed in Section 
  B.</p><p>Archaeological records for England currently contain around 600,000 sites and monuments. 
  Some 13,000 nationally important cases enjoy special protection as &quot;scheduled 
  monuments&quot;, under the Ancient Monuments and Archaeological Areas Act 1979. 
  English Heritage have embarked on a survey programme which is expected to result 
  in significant additional numbers being given this statutory protection (see Annex 
  3).</p><p>Scheduling archaeological remains ensures that the case for preservation is fully 
  considered given any proposals for development or other work which might damage 
  the monument. The planning system is equally in a position to consider the desirability 
  of preserving archaeological remains. Much can be achieved within the wider planning 
  process when developers are prepared to enter into discussions with archaeologists 
  and consider fully the needs of archaeology. This voluntary approach to considering 
  the needs of archaeology is a well-established and growing practice and has been 
  formalized in Codes of Practice by the British Archaeologists' and Developers' Liaison 
  Group (BADLG), and the 
		<a href="http://www.cbi.org.uk/home.html">
				<strong>Confederation 
  of British Industry (CBI)</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> Code for Mineral Operators.</p><p>Archaeological issues are often important in minerals planning, particularly in 
  the extraction of sand and gravel. River valleys have provided an attractive place 
  for man to settle but at the same time these areas often contain valuable sand and 
  gravel resources. Minerals can clearly only be worked where they are found so they 
  often differ from other forms of development in that there is not the same flexibility 
  of choice of location. The CBI's revised Code of Practice for Mineral Operators 
  on archaeological investigations provides advice on how minerals operators should 
  consult archaeological interests in formulating planning applications, to ensure 
  that archaeological factors are fully taken into account in the planning decision 
  process.</p><p>The key to informed and reasonable planning decisions, as emphasised in paragraphs 
  19 and 20, is for consideration to be given early, before formal planning applications 
  are made, to the question whether archaeological remains exist on a site where development 
  is planned and the implications for the development proposal. When important remains 
  are known to exist or when archaeologists have good reason to believe that important 
  remains exist, developers will be able to help by preparing sympathetic designs 
  using, for example, foundations which avoid disturbing the remains altogether or 
  minimise damage by raising ground levels under a proposed new structure, or by the 
  careful siting of landscaped or open areas. There are techniques available for sealing 
  archaeological remains underneath buildings or landscaping, thus securing their 
  preservation for the future even though they remain inaccessible for the time being.</p><p>If physical preservation in situ is not feasible, an <strong>
				
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=619">archaeological 
  excavation</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to pid 619</span> for the purposes of 'preservation by record', may be an acceptable 
  alternative. From the archaeological point of view this should be regarded as a 
  second best option. The science of archaeology is developing rapidly. Excavation 
  means the total destruction of evidence (apart from removable artefacts) from which 
  future techniques could almost certainly extract more information than is currently 
  possible. Excavation is also expensive and time-consuming, and discoveries may have 
  to be evaluated in a hurry against an inadequate research framework. The preservation 
  in situ of important archaeological remains is therefore nearly always to be preferred.</p><p>Positive planning and management can help to bring about sensible solutions to 
  the treatment of sites with archaeological remains and reduce the areas of potential 
  conflict between development and preservation. Both central government and English 
  Heritage have important roles to play. But the key to the future of the great majority 
  of archaeological sites and historic landscapes lies with local authorities, acting 
  within the framework set by central government, in their various capacities as planning, 
  education and recreational authorities, as well as with the owners of sites themselves. 
  Appropriate planning policies in development plans and their implementation through 
  development control will be especially important.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=618"> Providing Information
		(618)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
