<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=619}]"><cms:name>batch-4-619</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Archaeological excavations and surveys</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=619}]"><cms:name>batch-4-619-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Tourist</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>archaeological, excavations, surveys</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=619}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If you are planning a development, it pays to seek archaeological advice from the Council as early as possible before submitting a planning application. This can save time and money and avoid problems later.</i></p><hr/><p>An initial consultation will show whether there are any known, or likely, archaeological remains within   or adjacent to a proposed development.</p><p>On the basis of this preliminary appraisal, it may be necessary   to commission a fuller archaeological assessment or evaluation by a professionally   qualified archaeological contractor. The report on this work should accompany the   planning application, and include an assessment of the archaeological effects of   the development and any measures proposed to reduce it's impact. The Local Planning   Authority may defer a planning decision until this information is available.</p><p>The first priority is the preservation of significant archaeological   remains in situ. To achieve this, the archaeological impact of the development should   be minimised by, for example, sympathetic foundation design or amendments to the   layout. If this is not feasible, then detailed excavation, recording and publication   is the second best option.</p><p>Archaeological implications will be a material consideration   for the Local Planning Authority when making a planning decision. If further archaeological   work is necessary this can be secured, either by the use of a planning condition,   or by a legal agreement under section 106 of the Town and Country Planning Act 1990.</p><p>In other cases, particularly small-scale development, recording   of archaeological remains during development may be advised; this is known as a   watching brief and will normally be secured by a planning condition.</p><h4>Archaeology in Practice</h4><p>Archaeological work, before and during development, can take   a number of forms :</p><ul>				<li title="*">					<strong>desk-based assessment:</strong> a detailed appraisal of available information     about a site before a planning application is submitted or approved.</li>				<li title="*">					<strong>field evaluation:</strong> a survey or trial excavation designed to assess the     nature of archaeological remains within a proposed development area before a planning     application is submitted or approved. Techniques may include fieldwalking, geophysical     survey and trial trenching.</li>				<li title="*">					<strong>excavation and recording:</strong> a controlled programme of fieldwork to provide     a lasting record of archaeological evidence unavoidably destroyed by development</li>				<li title="*">					<strong>watching brief:</strong> the recording of archaeological evidence coming to light     during the course of development</li>			</ul><p>It is national and local practice that the costs of archaeological   work made necessary by development should, in most circumstances, be borne by the   developer.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=619"> Providing Information
		(619)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
