<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=364}]"><cms:name>elections--electoral-register-364</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Elections - Electoral Register</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=364}]"><cms:name>elections--electoral-register-364-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>election, electoral, register</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=364}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A recent change to the law now means that you can add your name to the register of electors at any time throughout the year. </i></p><hr/><p>If you do not register then you cannot exercise
      your democratic right to vote in any election.  It is also much harder
  to obtain credit if you are not on the Register. </p><p>The council is contemplating taking legal
      proceedings against householders who fail to return their registration
  form.</p><p>  You can check the Electoral Register at your
      local Customer Service Centre. Libraries
      also have local sections of the register. </p><p>Complete back files are held at <span class="gen">enter location</span>. Alternatively you can contact the Electoral Registration
    Office on  <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span> who will check
    the register for you. </p><p>  The edited register leaves out the names and addresses of people who have asked
      for them to be excluded from that version of the register. The edited register
      can be bought by anyone who asks for a copy, and they may use it for any
    purpose. </p><p>If you are not on the published register, all
    you need to do is complete the  <strong>
				
			
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to online form</span>.
  You need to sign your own form - someone else cannot do it for you. </p><p>When you send us your completed, signed form we will add you to our list of
    new applications. Any elector can then object to your name being added to the
  register. If this happens we will write to you. </p><p>If your application is not objected to, we will change your details within
  <span class="gen">enter amount</span> weeks of receiving your form. We will write to tell you when your application
  is allowed. </p><p>We will also tell the Electoral Registration Officer for your old address
  that you have moved, so that your name can be removed from that register. People
  who live at two homes (including students) are allowed to register at both.
  If you do not want to be removed from your other address please explain why
on your form. </p><p>There are special rules about names being added to the voters list during
  an election period. Because of these you may not be able to vote at that election
  if you are added during this time. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=364"> Applications for services
		(364)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset><cms:links oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contentassets.RelatedLink:{id=364}]"><cms:targetType>internalLink</cms:targetType><cms:linkOrder>1</cms:linkOrder><cms:linkTitle>PDF Form</cms:linkTitle><cms:targetItem oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.FileStorageItem:{id=364}]"/></cms:links></cms:item>
