<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=162}]"><cms:name>advocacy-for-carers-162</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Advocacy for Carers</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=162}]"><cms:name>advocacy-for-carers-162-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>advocacy, carers</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=162}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A carer is someone of any age whose life is restricted because they are looking after a friend, relative, partner or person who cannot manage without help, because of illness, age or a disability of any kind.</i></p><hr/><p> Someone who is paid to 
  undertake their caring role is therefore not a carer, although some carers may 
  be in receipt of Invalid Care Allowance or in full time employment.</p><p>Carers fall broadly into 
  3 categories:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Adult carers -  
      an adult caring for another adult such as a spouse, partner, friend or relative.</li>
  <li title="*">Parent carers -  
      an adult who cares for an ill or disabled child.</li>
  <li title="*">Young carers -  
      a child or young person who is carrying out significant caring tasks and 
      assuming a level of responsibility for another person which would usually 
      be taken by an adult. This may be a sibling or a parent.</li>
  </ul><p>Carers are a valuable resource 
  and their contribution to community care far exceeds the combined efforts of 
  statutory and voluntary agencies. The continued health and well being of carers 
  is vital to the success of community care.</p><p>The impact of caring responsibilities 
  on people's working lives and on their income cannot be ignored. Many 
  carers give up work or reduce their hours of work to care. Many carers in paid 
  work report an impact of their own physical and emotional health as a result 
  of juggling a paid job with caring. Those carers who give up work to care, face 
  the prospect of lost earnings, and the subsequent impact on savings and pensions, 
  as well as the loss of skills in practice, and the disadvantage they might face 
  in trying to return to work when caring ends.</p><p>Carers are also a source 
  of important information as they are close to day to day problems and experience 
  first hand services provided. They are therefore ideally placed to feedback 
  vital information regarding the effectiveness and quality of existing services, 
  and suggest ways of improvement.</p><p>Carers can also challenge 
  assumptions and raise awareness of issues facing people living and caring at 
  home - they are therefore well placed to influence planning and policies.</p><p>Working with and listening 
  to carers will therefore enable all agencies to make more effective use of resources. 
  If the services required are not provided, there may be short term savings, 
  but there will most definitely be additional expenditure in the long term.</p><h2>Legislation</h2><p>The 
  Children Act 1989 gives local authorities the duty to safeguard and promote 
  the welfare of children and is therefore relevant both to young carers and parent 
  carers of children with disabilities and special needs.</p><p>The Carers (Recognition 
  and Services) Act 1995 built on previous legislation and gives carers the right 
  to ask for their own assessment. Assessment is the key both to individual choice 
  and provision of appropriate support and is also integral to the development 
  of a systematic collation of carers' needs to support service planning. 
  It is therefore vital to ensure that carers' needs are considered and 
  recorded as part of any assessment. However, the right to assessment was qualified 
  by two main factors:</p><ul>
				<li title="*">  The carer must be providing 
    &quot;substantial care on a regular basis&quot;.</li>
				<li title="*">  
    The person care for must also have an assessment for community care.</li>
			</ul><p>The Carers and Disabled 
  Children Act 2000 now gives carers the right to an assessment even when the 
  disabled person refuses an assessment. It also gives parents of children with 
  disabilities the right to request an assessment and empowers local authorities 
  to provide services.</p><p>Having listened to the carers 
  view, the Local Authority must take into account the result of the carers assessment 
  when deciding what services to provide to the person who is being care for.</p><p>It is clear that many carers 
  are still not aware of their right to a separate assessment. However, Department 
  of Health guidance clearly states that local authorities should offer carers 
  the right to a separate, confidential interview i.e. it is not incumbent on 
  the carer to ask.</p><h2>Objectives </h2><p>The objectives of this Council 
  are:</p><ul>
    <li title="*">To raise 
      awareness of carers issues, and help to keep them on the agenda of all relevant 
      agencies.</li>
  <li title="*">To set out key values 
      and principles for services to carers in the form of a local Carers Charter.</li>
  <li title="*">To improve the quality 
      and increase the availability of information to carers.</li>
  <li title="*">To promote and support 
        the appropriate involvement of carers in:<br/>
        - Discussions and 
          decisions around the individual care and treatment plans of the people 
          they care for. <br/>
        - Monitoring the 
          quality and standards of care and treatment. <br/>
         - The development 
          of strategies and services.</li>
  <li title="*">To identify and 
        promote good practice across all purchasers and providers of:<br/>
        - Community Care 
          and Children's Services<br/>
          - Health Services<br/>
          - Housing Services</li>
</ul><h2>Key Principles</h2><p>
				<strong>Carers should have 
  recognition:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">Of the 
      value of their contribution to health and social care for people in need.</li>
  <li title="*">Of their differing 
      needs as individuals.</li>
  <li title="*">Of their needs for 
      a range of practical and emotional support.</li>
  <li title="*">Of their expertise 
      and skills.</li>
  <li title="*">Of the need to involve 
      carers in monitoring services and the importance of taking into account 
      their experiences in the evaluation of services.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>Carers should have 
  choice:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">Subject 
      to their own cultural beliefs.</li>
  <li title="*">On whether or not to 
      take on or continue their caring role.</li>
  <li title="*">On whether or not to 
      become involved in the assessment of the person they care for.</li>
  <li title="*">To have an assessment 
      of their own needs.</li>
  <li title="*">To be consulted on 
      and involved in planning services that they and the person they care for 
      receive.</li>
  <li title="*">To use advocacy and 
      mediation services.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>Carers should have 
  information:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">Which is 
      coordinated and easily accessible.</li>
  <li title="*">Which is available 
      at all stages, especially before, but also during and after caring.</li>
  <li title="*">Which is available 
      in a range of formats and languages.</li>
  <li title="*">About all relevant 
      services including housing advice.</li>
  <li title="*">About charges, entitlements 
      and welfare benefits.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>Carers should be 
  provided with appropriate practical help:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">Which promotes 
      their good health.</li>
  <li title="*">Through good assessment 
      procedures, tailoring services to individual needs.</li>
  <li title="*">Which includes a range 
      of good quality flexible services planned with carers and including practical 
      help such as laundry, shopping, housework and sitting services.</li>
  <li title="*">Which includes opportunities 
      for short and longer breaks.</li>
  <li title="*">Which includes the 
      development of greater range of innovative and flexible respite services.</li>
  <li title="*">Which includes counselling 
      and support to deal with all aspects of caring including the end of caring 
      responsibilities.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>The financial cost of caring  
should be minimised:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">By ensuring 
      information and advice on benefits and entitlements throughout caring is 
      available.</li>
  <li title="*">By keeping charges 
      to a minimum, but without reducing quality and quantity through carer sensitive 
      practices by all employers which allow carers to continue in paid employment.</li>
  <li title="*">By providing advice 
      about employment opportunities during and after caring.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>Services and information 
  should be co-ordinated within and across agencies in order to best meet the needs 
  of carers:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">Carer sensitive 
      policy and practice should be encouraged.</li>
  <li title="*">Carer sensitive admission 
      and discharge policies should be developed in all hospitals.</li>
  <li title="*">Wherever possible and 
      subject to confidentiality and choice, relevant information should be shared 
      between agencies.</li>
</ul><p>
				<strong>Carers should be 
  involved in planning and monitoring the services they receive:</strong>
			</p><ul>
			  <li title="*">In order 
      to properly reflect the differing needs of carers and to take into account 
      their culture, race, religion, gender, age, disability or illness.</li>
  <li title="*">Organisations should 
      continue to explore creative ways to involve carers in the planning process.</li>
  <li title="*">Carers should be encouraged 
      to express their views about services they and person cared for receive.</li>
  <li title="*">Carers views should 
      be listened to and recorded.</li>
  <li title="*">Carers should always 
      receive feedback on their contribution and what has happened as a result.</li>
</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=162"> Providing Information
		(162)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
