<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=449}]"><cms:name>arts-and-leisure-449</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Children's library service</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=449}]"><cms:name>arts-and-leisure-449-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Child</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>children, library, service</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=449}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Arts and Leisure</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Libraries are for everyone! - You're never too young to join and it's free!</i></p><hr/><p>
				You can download an application form here - your parent or guardian 
  will need to sign it, or alternatively you can call into the library and ask for 
  a membership form. Take the signed completed form along to your local library and 
  you will be given your library key card.
			</p><p>
				There are all sorts of books in the library
			</p><ul>
				<li title="*">books for babies</li>
				<li title="*">adventure stories</li>
				<li title="*">funny stories</li>
				<li title="*">information books</li>
				<li title="*">books for mums and dads</li>
				<li title="*">...and lots more.</li>
			</ul><p>
				You can borrow up to eight books, and keep them for up to four 
  weeks. Bring them back on or before the date stamped in the book. You can have your 
  books stamped again if nobody else wants them. You won't have to pay fines if the 
  books are returned to the library late - but don't forget other people may want 
  to read them.
			</p><p>
				Cassettes and CD's are also available - you have to pay to borrow 
  these except story tapes for very young children which are free.
			</p><p>
				Some libraries have computers in their children's sections on 
  which you can book time in 30 minute slots. All libraries have computer learning 
  facilities that children can use. At most libraries there is a selection of CD ROMs 
  such as Encarta and The Way Things Work, to help with study and homework. Children 
  can also access the Internet subject to signed permission from a parent or guardian 
  and other safeguards. Computer sessions can be booked by asking at the library or 
  telephoning. You will need your Library card. Printouts cost <span class="gen">enter amount</span> per sheet.
			</p><p>
				Activities take place throughout the year - usually around school 
  holiday times. Look out for storytimes, crafts, arts workshops, quizzes, competitions, 
  etc.
			</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=449"> Providing Information
		(449)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
