<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=792}]"><cms:name>major-accident-hazards-792</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Major Accident Hazards</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=792}]"><cms:name>major-accident-hazards-792-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>major, accident, hazards</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=792}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The terrible events of September 11th 2001 in New York highlighted that the modern world is still an unsafe place. There are a multitude of potential risks and so emergencies will inevitably occur. </i></p><hr/><p>To illustrate this further, between 1988 and April 1989 the following disasters occurred: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">Piper Alpha oil platform fire</li>
			<li title="*">The Lockerbie Disaster</li>
			<li title="*">The Clapham rail crash</li>
			<li title="*">The Kegworth air accident; and</li>
			<li title="*">The Hillsborough football stadium tragedy </li>
		</ul><p>More recently there have been the terrorist incidents in Central London, Docklands and Manchester, the Dunblane massacre, the BSE crisis, the Southall and Paddington train crashes, severe floods, widespread foot and mouth disease and many other less publicised incidents.</p><p>The Council recognises that there is an need for effective planning for civil emergencies to ensure the efficient and speedy management of the response to these incidents between all the possible agencies; the Police, Fire Brigade, Ambulance Service, the Council, utilities providers and voluntary agencies. </p><p>The purpose of the Council's emergency planning is to provide staff with the plans, procedures and information they will require to enable them to ameliorate the effects of any major emergency occurring within <span class="gen">enter council name</span>, whilst allowing Council services to continue to provide as far as possible their usual day to day services. </p><p>The Council's emergency plans set out the information, procedures and details required to ensure an effective, flexible and timely response to an emergency thus reducing to a minimum the distress and disruption caused by such an incident. </p><p>If you require any further information on the Council's emergency planning, please use the contact details above.</p><h2>Major Emergency Arrangements </h2><p>The one thing you can be sure of in an emergency situation is that it will probably be the last thing that you expected. Floods, severe weather, transport accidents (air, sea, road, rail) or incidents involving dangerous chemicals usually strike without warning.</p><p>This guide explains simple steps everyone should take to be ready when an emergency strikes. It explains easy safety measures, how to reduce damage to property and what to do if you have to shelter in your home or move out of your home until danger has passed. Remember your own preparations and self-help are essential and critical factors in dealing with any emergency. </p><p>This simple guide aims to help people cope with the unexpected and assist the emergency services in dealing quickly and efficiently with major emergencies.</p><h2>Dealing with an emergency</h2><p>Whatever the situation, it is important to be ready to follow the instructions from the Police and other emergency services. Planning for an emergency is never easy because no-one can predict what might happen - a major road, train, air or river accident; a serious fire; violent storms; flooding or another dangerous incident. Whatever happens, it will almost certainly mean police, fire and ambulance services in the front line of a tough situation. </p><p>Although every incident is different, they will operate in accordance with procedures set out in the  Emergency Services Major Incident Procedure Manual.</p><p>These procedures are constantly being updated, and the Council has its own plans for mobilising social services, housing, highways and environmental health. Public utilities, voluntary organisations and many businesses also have their own emergency plans.</p><p>An emergency incident might mean evacuating an area  and providing temporary accommodation. Rest centres may need to be set up, food and blankets provided and information given to anxious relatives. Someone has to be ready to reunite families who may be parted by an emergency situation, perhaps because the children were at school or some people at work.</p><p>Arranging all this is the job of the emergency services supported by the Council and many other public, private and voluntary organisations.</p><h2>Radio and TV - warning the public</h2><p>In major emergency situations, it may be necessary to issue warnings and advice to the public. Such messages would normally be broadcast on relevant radio and TV channels.</p><p>Remember to cater for power cuts - you should have a battery-operated radio and know how to tune in to your local stations.</p><h3>Local Radio Stations</h3><p>These are as follows:</p><p>
<span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><h2>Major Hazard Sites </h2><p>Some industries, because of the nature and quantity of chemicals or substances stored or processed, are required by law to distribute information to people living in the immediate vicinity of the hazardous sites.</p><p>This requirement applies to the following sites in <span class="gen">enter council name</span>:</p><p>
<span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><p>If you live in the immediate vicinity of the above sites you should have received an information card from the company. Make sure that you and all occupants understand the information and advice so that they can take the appropriate action in the event of an accident.</p><p>If you have not received the information card, you should contact the company.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=792"> Providing Information
		(792)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
