<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=793}]"><cms:name>flooding-793</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Flooding</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=793}]"><cms:name>flooding-793-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>flooding</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=793}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Environment Agency operates a flood warning system, giving information to the public, media, emergency services and local Authorities.&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;</i></p><hr/><p>
				Using the latest
    available technology,&#xA0;staff monitor rainfall, river levels and sea conditions
    24 hours a day and use this information to forecast the possibility of flooding.
    If flooding is forecast, warnings are issued using a set of four easily recognisable
    codes. The following codes are used:
			</p><p>
			<strong>
				
Flood
    Watch </strong>- Flooding possible. Be aware! Be prepared! Watch out!

			</p><p>
			<strong>
				
					Flood
    Warning </strong>- Flooding expected affecting homes, businesses and main roads.
    Act now!	</p><p>
			<strong>Severe
    Flood Warning</strong> - Severe flooding expected. Imminent danger to life and
    property. 
			</p><p>
			<strong>
All
    Clear </strong>- An all clear will be issued when flood watches or warnings are
    no longer in force.
			</p><p>
				  For more information on the current flooding situation, visit the 
		<a href="http://www.environment-agency.gov.uk/subjects/flood/floodwarning/">
				<strong>Environment Agency</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> website.
			</p><p>
				 When there is a risk of flooding the Agency issues warnings through
  the media; they are broadcast on TV weather bulletins and on radio weather
  and travel reports. Make sure you know which is your local radio station. </p><p>Flood
  warnings are also displayed on ITV Teletext regional weather pages (page 154)
  and on BBC Ceefax (page 419).
			</p><p>
				The Environment Agency
      provides the <strong>Floodline Service - Telephone Number 0845
      988 1188 </strong>.
    You can listen to recorded flood warning information or speak to an operator
    for general information and advice 24 hours a day.
			</p><h2>
				What this Council Will
    Do
			</h2><p>
				The Council's
      approach to providing emergency assistance during times of flooding is as
      follows:
			</p><ul>
			<li title="*">The Council has no
        legal responsibility to provide assistance to residents during times
        of flood, however the Council has provided emergency assistance on an
        ad hoc basis dependent upon local knowledge and experience of the
    situation.</li>
			<li title="*">The Council will provide
        sandbags or other such equipment as it feels appropriate, if they are
        available, to assist with the defence from flooding to persons or property
    within the area.</li>
			<li title="*">The Council will keep
        a stock of filled sandbags during times of potential flooding to aid
        the speed of response. The Council will deliver the sandbags or other
        equipment where the owner/occupier is unable to collect them from Council's
        depot. It will be the responsibility of the property
        owner/occupier to dispose of the sandbags once they are satisfied the
    risk of flooding has subsided.</li>
			<li title="*">The Council will provide
        engineering advice on ways residents can alleviate the risk of flooding
        to their properties if requested and issue general guidance to all properties
        in the area of their roles and responsibilities under the Land Drainage
        Act 1991. The Council will provide, if possible, during times of severe
        flooding, engineering advice on site to assist with the use of resources
    and control the situation where appropriate.</li>
			<li title="*">The Council will assist
        with the dissemination of Environment Agency flood warnings where appropriate.
        The Council will keep the necessary equipment at their depot to carry
        out the above functions, or have facilities to get access to the appropriate
    equipment rapidly.</li>
			<li title="*">Very serious flooding
        resulting in the need for evacuation of houses, provision of temporary
        accommodation and the like is covered by the Council's Emergency
    Plan.</li>
		</ul><p>
					    If you live near the coast, there is always a possibility that a combination
    of high tides and bad weather will threaten your property with flooding, even
    though engineers will have done as much as possible to reduce the risk of this
    happening.</p><p>    However, even if you live inland, events over the past few winters have demonstrated
    that exceptional storms can cause flooding even on hill slopes, when the
    drainage system is simply overwhelmed by the amount of water it is expected
    to carry.</p><p> In addition, when the ground is saturated even small additional amounts of
    rainfall will find it difficult to drain away from gardens and enclosed spaces.</p><p>The  Council, at times of
    emergency, will be endeavouring to protect the public at large
    and will not be able to assist a large number of individual homeowners who
    may
    find their properties threatened.
				</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=793"> Providing Information
		(793)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
