<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=794}]"><cms:name>pipelines-794</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Pipelines</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=794}]"><cms:name>pipelines-794-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>pipelines</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=794}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Pipeline Safety Regulations 1996 task local authorities with the production of emergency plans or the modification of existing plans, to cover certain major accident hazard pipelines (MAHP) within their area. The Health and Safety Executive notify the Council of those pipelines that require plans in the region. </i></p><hr/><p>The following gives
    an overview of the emergency response to a pipeline incident, showing how
    the existing procedures of various organisations
  would be applied and co-ordinated. </p><p>It follows the recommended national format for Pipeline Safety Plans.</p><h2>Pipeline System</h2><p>The operator for the
      notified Major Accident Hazard Pipelines in this area is Transco (formerly
      British Gas). The product carried is natural
  gas.</p><p>Transco supply maps showing
      pipeline routes and data to the Emergency Planning Team. This information
    is shared with the Fire Service.
    The details recorded include data on bore diameter, operating pressure and
  above ground equipment such as valves and pumping stations. </p><p>  For security reasons this information is not available to the public. Local
      Authority Planning and Emergency Planning sections can request the Pipeline
      Major Accident Prevention Document containing the above information from
    Transco. </p><h2>Hazard and Effect</h2><p>An
        incident involving a high pressure gas pipeline is readily identified by
    the following features:</p><p>
				<strong>Release of gas </strong>-
      Significant damage to a Major Accident Hazard Pipeline that results in
      a pipeline puncture
      or rupture will lead to a pressurised release
    of natural gas. All pipelines operating under 75 bar (which is used for the
  National Transmission System) contain odorised gas. </p><p>If ignited this may give rise to a thermal radiation hazard to individuals
    in the vicinity. Ignition can be immediate, delayed local ignition, delayed
    remote ignition, or no ignition at all. Each may have different consequences,
    hazard ranges and duration and for this reason time scale and sequence of any
  incident will vary.</p><p>
				<strong>Duration of pipeline</strong>
				<strong>leaks</strong>  - When a high-pressure pipeline fails, immediate and rapid de-pressurisation
      occurs over a matter of seconds, and is followed
    by relatively stable flow as the pipeline unpacks due to the leak and continued
    pumping of gas into the pipeline. Flow may last for several hours dependant
    on the location and topography of the pipeline and the time for Transco personnel
    to arrive on site to shut down valves not shut remotely from the Transco
  Control Centre.</p><p>
				<strong>Blast Effects
        and Projectiles</strong>  - The pressure blast at the time of failure
        can be significant in close proximity to the pipeline, cover material
        over
    the pipeline may be thrown into the air at high velocity, but the serious
      effects will diminish with distance. Delayed ignition in the vicinity of
      buildings
  may result in loss of window glass as a result of blast over pressure. </p><p>
				<strong>Fire and Explosion</strong> -
      The ignition of any release of gas will cause a flare, which may have serious
      effects due to thermal radiation. People can be shielded
    indoors but radiation levels may be sufficient for the buildings to catch
      fire. Techniques are available for estimating the thermal radiation from
      an estimated
    quantity of gas released over time. Any failure of pipelines carries the
      risk of ignition, but experience has shown that in the majority of cases
      ignition
  does not occur.</p><p>If a release of gas does not ignite immediately, it will form a cloud, which
    will disperse over large distances. If a cloud of gas ignites it may burn back
    as a flash fire to the point of origin. As it disperses it will be diluted
    with air, the concentration falling below the lower explosive level (LEL) when
    it will no longer present a fire hazard. The distance over which such a release
    may disperse depends on the type of release and the prevailing weather conditions.
  Concentrations and duration may be estimated using plume modelling.</p><p>It is important that ignited gas is not extinguished unless specifically requested
  by the Transco on site controller.</p><p>
				<strong>Noise</strong> - The release of
      high-pressure gas creates a great deal of noise, which can be very intense
      leading to temporary hearing damage. High noise levels
  can also be disorientating and may cause unexpected behaviour in people effected.</p><p>
				<strong>Hazard Range
        and Emergency Planning Distances</strong> - Transco have calculated hazard information related
      to thermal radiation. This is supplied to the Fire
  Service and is also available to planning departments in local authorities.</p><h2>Plan Activation</h2><p>In
        view of the extreme nature of a high-pressure pipeline failure it is likely
      that initial notification will be by a member of the public either by 999
        call or to the gas emergency number.</p><p>The Emergency Services
      and Transco will follow their standard procedures to investigate reports.
      If at any stage they identify a requirement for additional
    resources, a mutual decision is taken to notify other organisations and undertake
    wider co-ordination. This process is the same as that employed in response
  to other major incidents.</p><p>There
    is a single national gas emergency number for all notifications:  0800
    111 999.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=794"> Providing Information
		(794)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
