<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=52}]"><cms:name>education-1-52</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Paid work or work experience and school aged pupils</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=52}]"><cms:name>education-1-52-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>paid, work, experience, school, aged, pupils</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=52}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Work Experience is an important part of Education for Employability which allows students to learn about the world of work in a &quot;real life&quot; working situation.&#xA0;</i></p><hr/><p>It is intended to give a student an experience of working life and the Key Skills needed in the workplace rather than an chance to try out an occupation they may want to follow. Within the limits of what is available, and the demands for very popular areas of work, the choice is made to benefit a student's education, rather than for job sampling or recruitment purposes. Normally, companies where a student already has experience through a parent or a part-time job are not used. This makes sure that they are having a real extension of their experience. The preparation programme for students will ask them to look at equal opportunities and stereotyping prior to making choices. All students, from those taking the fewest examinations to those who will take degrees, need real knowledge of the world of work.</p><h3>Students eligible to take part in Work Experience </h3><p>Students in the last 2 years of compulsory schooling can take part in Work Experience (from the start of Y10)</p><h3>What students should do whilst on Work Experience </h3><p>As far as possible students should undertake real tasks to give them an idea of the work carried out by the employer. They should learn how the company is organised. Some students may observe the more complicated parts of running a company and should gain an understanding of how enterprise, creativity and innovation help business growth. A programme should be organised for the student, and employers should monitor what the student has achieved. Every student should have a Work Experience Logbook in which they can record progress. The employer could help by making sure the students completes it and by completing the Employer Assessment section for the student.</p><h3>Role of the Parents/Guardians</h3><p>Parents/guardians can offer valuable support in finding placements. Their written consent is needed before a placement can begin. They will have information about the arrangements, and will know how to contact the school if their son or daughter reports a problem to them about their placement. They will be asked to provide medical information which could affect the health, safety and welfare of their son or daughter whilst on a work placement.</p><h3>Limits on the jobs student can do</h3><p>The Education Act 1996 and local bye-laws place limitations on the type of work which students can experience. The School's Work Experience Co-ordinator can give advice on this.</p><h3>How arrangement are made by the school</h3><p>The Work Experience Co-ordinator or Teacher Responsible plans a Scheme of Work for the Health and Safety Preparation, Briefing and Debriefing of students prior to Work Experience. When a company is known to be willing to take a student the teachers responsible for the student will send the company contact details of their Work Experience Programme. Parents, Employers and Students are asked to complete the Approval and Consent Form which indicates that all parties agree with the arrangements.</p><h3>Placement Suitability Visit</h3><p>Work Experience Organisers  have a duty to assess the ability of a work experience placement provider to provide for a student's health, safety and welfare whilst on Work Experience.</p><h3>Specific Risk Assessment for Young Workers</h3><p>Employers need to inform students of their main duties and tasks, the type of work, any associated specific risks and their control measures and remind the students of their responsibilities whilst on placement. Parents/guardians will also have to be told of these risks. There is a section on the Employers Section of the Approval and Consent Form to do this. If parents/guardians or employers have any queries or difficulties they can contact the Work Experience Co-ordinator.</p><h3>Health and Safety at Work</h3><li title="*">During preparation in school, students will have the importance of health and safety responsibilities at work outlined to them. They will be introduced to the ideas of their own responsibility for health and safety, safe working practices, signage and significant specific risks and general control measures.The employer will need to reinforce these Health and Safety responsibilities at the start of their placement through their Induction Process.</li><li title="*">The Health and Safety Training for Employment Regulations 1990 give all school students receiving training the same protection and duties as employees under the Health and Safety at Work Act and other relevant statutory provisions.</li><li title="*">The requirement for employers to inform parents/guardians of the outcome of their Risk Assessment is under the Management of Health and Safety at Work Regulations 1999. The Approval and Consent Form will enable employers to do this if they wish.</li><li title="*">The general duty of care which teachers owe to their students will extend to the arranging of any Work Experience placement.</li><li title="*">The main responsibility for the Health and Safety of the student whilst on Work Experience lies with the employer.</li><li title="*">Fire, First Aid and Accident Reporting procedures must be explained to the student by the employer.</li><li title="*">Similarly, any particular hazards associated with the work area and the work to be done must be explained and the importance of following safe working practices emphasised.</li><li title="*">Appropriate safety equipment and protective clothing must be available where appropriate.</li><li title="*">It is in everyone's interest that the employer ensures adequate supervision throughout the placement. Supervisors should be aware of the purpose of work experience, have a good knowledge of Health and Safety and know something about the young person working with them.</li><h3>Medical Information on Students</h3><p>Each student's health should be considered before a placement is chosen; for example, someone with asthma would avoid dusty places. If a student is on medication the employer must be informed. The parents will be asked to provide medical information which may affect the safety and welfare of their son or daughter whilst on a placement.</p><h3>Reporting Of Accidents, Incidents and Dangerous Occurrences</h3><p>It is the responsibility of the employer to report any accidents, incidents or dangerous occurrences that occur on site following their normal procedures for such reporting covered by the RIDDOR 1995 Regulations. The employer must report any such accidents or occurrences to the Headteacher or Work Experience Co-ordinator of the school and the student's home if a telephone number is provided.</p><h3>Child Protection Issues</h3><p>Schools should have given consideration to preparing students to deal with and report incidents that they feel uncomfortable with during their work placement. Employers should take account of child protection issues under the Criminal Justice and Court Services Act 2000.</p><h3>Insurance Arrangements</h3><p>The Employers Insurance Company must be informed of the employer's intention to take on a Work Experience student. Where a student will be travelling in a vehicle for the purposes of work the vehicle insurance must cover them.</p><p>There are 6 principal areas of risk that may arise in the course of Work Experience:-</p><li title="*">Injury to students themselves</li><li title="*">Injury to others on the premises</li><li title="*">Injury to others not on the premises</li><li title="*">Damage to or loss of employers' property</li><li title="*">Damage to or loss of other property</li><li title="*">Damage to or loss of employee's property</li><p>Where a &quot;liability&quot; can be demonstrated then:-</p><li title="*">Injuries caused to others on the premises, others not on the premises, damage to others property and damage to employee's property should normally be covered by the employer's Public Liability Insurance policy.</li><li title="*">Damage to the employer's own property should normally be covered by the employer's Material Damage policy.</li><li title="*">Injuries to the student whilst on work experience will be covered by the employer's Employers Liability Insurance policy.</li><p>Students must be briefed that if they cause injury or damage through a deliberate act they will not be indemnified by insurance and may be required to meet the cost of any compensation the Courts may award.</p><h3>Teacher Visits to Placement Providers</h3><p>The  LEA Work Experience Scheme requires the school staff to make a Teacher Visit to the employer during the placement in order to monitor and review the progress of the student. Where a visit is deemed not to be &quot;reasonably practicable&quot; e.g. out of the area, the school will contact the employer.</p><h3>Hours of Work</h3><p>The Working Time Regulations 1998 apply to students on work experience however, the number and pattern of hours worked is normally agreed by the provider, school and student. If possible, normal hours should be worked, but students are not allowed to work outside any hours specified by legislation. If a company's hours are 8 am to 5 pm, it is not expected that students arrive at 9 am and leave at 4 pm.</p><h3>Pay, Tax and National Insurance</h3><p>Students on work experience must not be paid and will not pay tax or N.I. contributions. Employers can assist with travelling or lunch costs if they wish.</p><h3>Length of Work Experience</h3><p>There are no fixed requirements. Five to ten days on a &quot;Block&quot; is currently seen as the normal length of stay if Work Experience is to offer enough depth to be of use. Students on an &quot;Extended&quot; Work Experience need to work at least one day per week if the experience is to be of real value.</p><h3>Lunch and Break Periods</h3><p>Parents should discuss the arrangements for lunch and break periods with their son/daughter and make sure they are suitable. If a student leaves the employer's premises during lunch or break periods, no liability can be accepted by the employer or the school for any incident that may occur.</p><h3>Out of the Area Work Placements</h3><p>If a student wishes to undertake Work Experience out of the area then parents/guardians are responsible for making the appropriate arrangements for travel and accommodation. There could be problems with obtaining a Placement Suitability Visit in these cases and the Work Experience Co-ordinator should be the first point of contact if information on this is required.</p><h3>Who to contact at the School if there is a problem</h3><p>Each School has a Work Experience Co-ordinator who can be contacted at any time during the work placement. Parents/Guardians and Employers should be given the name of the Work Experience Co-ordinator and their contact telephone number prior to the work placement taking place.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=52"> Providing Information
		(52)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
