<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=631}]"><cms:name>education-1-631</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Chaperone Service</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=631}]"><cms:name>education-1-631-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Child</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>chaperone, service</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=631}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A child taking part in a performance, which can include TV or filming, theatre, sporting activities or modeling, will require chaperoning.</i></p><hr/><p>&quot;Chaperones act in 'loco parentis' and should exercise the care which a good parent might be reasonably expected to give that child&quot;.</p><p>Application for a Chaperone Licence must be made to the Local Education Authority in whose area the prospective chaperone lives. Due to various checks which have to be made, the time between the LEA receiving an application and the issuing of a Chaperone Licence can take a while - please allow for this.</p><h3>Responsibilities of a Chaperone</h3><ul>
			<li title="*">A Chaperone's first priority is always to the child.</li>
			<li title="*">A Chaperone is the key person to whom the child looks to for guidance, protection, clarification and support.</li>
			<li title="*">One of a Chaperone's greatest strengths is their ability to negotiate with the production company 'on site' and be able to say no when what is being requested of the child is contrary or detrimental to either the child's health, well being and/or education. For example, requesting a child to stay at a place of performance over and above the hours/times laid down in either the child's licence or the regulations, lack of education time, and so forth (contact the Local Education Authority  if you experience difficulties here).</li>
			<li title="*">At no time should a child perform if unwell.</li>
			<li title="*">Chaperones should keep a note of important contacts, for example, their Licensing Authority, the child's Licensing Authority, the Local Authority in whose area the child is performing, the child's Agent and the child's Parent/Legal Guardian.</li>
			<li title="*">The maximum number of children chaperones are allowed to have in their care at any one time is 12. But, in a lot of instances this will be too many (diverse mixture of ages requiring more concentrated supervision and so forth). We recommend 8 children to be the maximum in many cases.</li>
			<li title="*">The child should not perform if a licence has not been granted, unless they fall within the exemption period.</li>
			<li title="*">Chaperone's should not presume that a child is licensed. Always ask to see a child's Licence upon arrival at a place of performance.</li>
			<li title="*">If the production company cannot prove that a child is licensed, Chaperone's should contact the child's LEA urgently, otherwise a contravention may have occurred.</li>
			<li title="*">Production companies are required to log certain activities during a performance i.e. arrival and departure times at the place of the performance etc.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=631"> Providing Information
		(631)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
