<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=599}]"><cms:name>planning-599</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Statutory development plans</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=599}]"><cms:name>planning-599-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Businesses</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>statutory, development, plans</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=599}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Development planning is a continuous process of looking forward and deciding on a course of action to improve people's quality of life and the appearance of our environment in a sustainable way. It involves protecting the best, improving the worst, and aiming positively to ensure a better quality of life for everyone, now and for future generations. </i></p><hr/><p>Development plans focus on land use development and protection set within the context of wider social, economic and environmental trends and considerations. Reflecting national and regional planning policies, development plans make strategic provision for the long-term use of land and buildings, providing a framework for local decision making and the reconciliation of competing development and conservation interests. </p><p>They aim to ensure that land use changes proceed coherently, efficiently, and with maximum community benefit. Development Plans indicate clearly how local residents, landowners, and other interested parties might be affected by land use change. They are subject to regular periods of intensive public consultation, involvement and negotiation. </p><p>Decisions on planning applications are made in accordance with the adopted Development Plan unless other material considerations, relating to land use development, indicate otherwise. </p><p>Once   Development Plans are adopted, they are eventually superceded by a single document, the <strong>Unitary Development Plan</strong>. <span class="gen">enter hyperlink</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=599"> Providing Information
		(599)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
