<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=272}]"><cms:name>batch-23-272</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Community transport</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=272}]"><cms:name>batch-23-272-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>community, transport</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=272}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Community Transport is the provision of non-profit making transport for members of the community who do not have suitable conventional public transport services available for their travel needs.</i></p><hr/><h2>Ring and Ride</h2><p>Ring and Ride Schemes operate within a number of towns. They are the main initiative in the provision of public transport for disabled and frail elderly people and provide a local service into local towns to allow potentially housebound people the opportunity to shop and use local amenities. The difference between a Ring and Ride and a conventional service lies in the flexible routing and the fact that the minibus is specially adapted with a wheelchair lift and removable seats to accommodate wheelchairs. </p><p>Passengers book a journey in advance simply by phoning their local scheme Co-ordinator the day before they wish to travel and are picked up at their door with assistance from the driver if necessary. </p><p>Ring and Ride Schemes have proved to be a great success and extremely popular with those that use them. Without the service many disabled and frail elderly people would not be able to get out and about and visit the town centres to do their shopping or make essential trips to the post office, bank etc. </p><p>For more information on the Ring and Ride Scheme, contact <span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><h2>Shopmobility</h2><p>Shopmobility provides manual and powered wheelchairs and scooters to help people with limited mobility to shop and use the city centre facilities. It can be used by young or old no matter whether their disability is temporary or permanent. Shopmobility is available both to residents and visitors alike. First time visitors need to register and training in the use of the vehicle will be provided. </p><p>Shopmobility Schemes are located next to car parking facilities so that when passengers arrive, they are able to park and transfer directly to their chosen vehicle. The user pays a deposit on the vehicle, which is refunded when the vehicle is returned. </p><p>In some locations, leisure mobility schemes are being developed to take the concept of Shopmobility and apply it to other destinations such as seaside, the countryside and special events widening access for all in the area. </p><p>For further information on Shopmobility, please contact  <span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><h2>Community Bus Scheme</h2><p>A Community Bus Scheme involves the operation of a small bus by a community-based organisation utilising volunteer drivers to provide regular, scheduled local bus services planned in response to local needs on a non-profit making basis. They play an important part in the community transport programme and have proved to be an invaluable asset to the more remote and isolated communities where conventional Public Transport cannot meet the identified need in a cost effective manner. </p><p>For further information on Community Bus Schemes, please contact <span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><h2>Community Car Schemes </h2><p>Community Car Schemes are one of the most flexible forms of Community Transport and make a significant contribution to the movement of disabled and frail elderly people. </p><p>Community car drivers use their own vehicles to carry those unable to use conventional transport to pre-booked destinations, most frequently medical appointments, in exchange for a specified mileage charge. An escort may travel with a passenger for a charge. </p><p>Passengers book a journey in advance with the scheme Co-ordinator who matches up the travel requirement with the drivers available. </p><p>The volunteer driver picks up the client from their home, takes them to their appointment and brings them back home. </p><p>For more information on Community Car Schemes, please contact <span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=272"> Providing Information
		(272)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
