<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=274}]"><cms:name>batch-23-274</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Parking bay</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=274}]"><cms:name>batch-23-274-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>parking, bay</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=274}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Any Blue Badge holder may apply for a blue badge holders parking place. The Council will consider the application. There are two different schemes available: </i></p><hr/><ul>
  <li title="*">A disabled parking bay that is available for use by any holder of a Blue Badge near a hospital, clinic, doctor's surgery, chemist or other public building; or </li>
  <li title="*">A dedicated disabled parking bay close to the applicants address that can only be used by the holder of the corresponding numbered permit. </li>
</ul><p>In each case, the parking place will be sited as near as possible to the relevant building but we have to take the following into consideration: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Traffic flow </li>
  <li title="*">The interests of the owners and occupiers of adjoining properties </li>
  <li title="*">Access to premises </li>
  <li title="*">And road safety </li>
</ul><p>  Any Blue Badge holder is able to park in a disabled parking bay. As a Blue Badge holder, to obtain a new disabled parking bay (for use by any Blue Badge holder) a successful application must be made which demonstrates certain qualification criteria. To qualify for a disabled parking bay, you must first hold a valid Blue Badge and: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Demonstrate a genuine need for the bay requested </li>
  <li title="*">And not have access to private parking within or near the premises</li>
</ul><p>You can obtain an application form using the details above. The Council will make every effort to deal with applications as quickly as possible. However, putting in parking places involves consultation with local people and statutory bodies as well as the production and publication of Traffic Management Orders. An application will take a minimum of 3 months to process. </p><h2>Applying for a Dedicated Disabled Parking Bay </h2><p>A dedicated disabled parking bay is reserved for one specific badge holder. To obtain a dedicated badge holder's parking bay, a successful applicant must satisfy certain qualification criteria. To qualify for a dedicated badge holder's parking bay, you must hold a valid blue badge and: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Receive the higher rate mobility component of the disability living allowance </li>
  <li title="*">Drive your own car or nominate a carer who drives you and resides at your address </li>
  <li title="*">Have no access to private parking </li>
  <li title="*">And provide copies of your driving licence and vehicle registration documents showing your name and  address (showing you are a local resident) </li>
</ul><p>If you do not receive a qualifying allowance because you are of retirement age, your mobility impairment will need to be assessed by an occupational therapist appointed by the Council. </p><p>You can obtain an application form by contacting us. The contact details are given above. The Council will make every effort to deal with applications as quickly as possible. However, putting in parking places involves consultation with local people and statutory bodies as well as the production and publication of Traffic Management Orders. An application will take a minimum of 3 months to process. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=274"> Providing Information
		(274)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
