<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=276}]"><cms:name>batch-23-276</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Personal transport</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=276}]"><cms:name>batch-23-276-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>personal, transport</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=276}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Motability Scheme was established to provide disabled people with safe, reliable and affordable cars. Cars account for 99% of the Scheme's activities, with powered wheelchairs and scooters making up the balance. </i></p><hr/><p>The Scheme works only because it brings together a number of essential elements: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">The Government (Department for Work and Pensions) </li>
			<li title="*">Motability (the registered charity empowered by its Royal Charter) </li>
			<li title="*">Motability Operations (owned by the UK's largest banks), operating the car Schemes on a not-for-profit basis </li>
			<li title="*">route2mobility Ltd (&quot;r2m&quot;), a privately owned company which operates the powered wheelchair and scooter scheme </li>
			<li title="*">Manufacturers of cars, powered wheelchairs and scooters </li>
			<li title="*">Car dealers and dealers in powered wheelchairs and scooters </li>
			<li title="*">Specialist vehicle adaptation companies </li>
			<li title="*">Insurance and roadside assistance providers </li>
		</ul><p>Over 1.5 million disabled people in the UK qualify for the Higher Rate Mobility Component of Disability Living Allowance from the Government. What a disabled person chooses to do with that money is entirely up to them. Currently, 400,000 disabled people have chosen to have their allowances paid to the Scheme to meet the cost of having a car, powered wheelchair or scooter through a contract hire or hire purchase arrangement. </p><p>Cars are supplied new from Motability accredited dealerships and customers can choose from over 20 car brands. There are more than 3,500 Motability accredited car dealerships across the UK and a national network of accredited retailers of powered wheelchairs and scooters. The Motability Scheme also provides a small number of used cars through hire purchase. </p><p>For more information on the Motability Scheme, visit the  website at 
		<a href="http://www.motability.co.uk">www.motability.co.uk</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=276"> Providing Information
		(276)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
