<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=764}]"><cms:name>batch-13-764</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Pilotage</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=764}]"><cms:name>batch-13-764-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>pilotage</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=764}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Pilots with local knowledge have been employed on board ships for centuries to guide vessels into or out of port safely - or wherever navigation may be considered hazardous, particularly when a shipmaster is unfamiliar with the area. </i></p><hr/><p>In addition to local knowledge and expertise, pilots are able to provide effective communication with the shore and with tugs, often in the local language.</p><p>Qualified pilots are usually employed by the local port or maritime administration and provide their services to ships for a fee, calculated in relation to the ship's tonnage, draught or other criteria.</p><p>The importance of employing qualified pilots in approaches to ports and other areas where specialized local knowledge is required was formally recognized by the International Maritime Organization (IMO) in 1968, when the Organization adopted Assembly resolution A.159(ES.IV) Recommendation on Pilotage. </p><p>The resolution recommends Governments organise pilotage services where they would be likely to prove more effective than other measures and to define the ships and classes of ships for which employment of a pilot would be mandatory. </p><p>More information on pilotage can be found on the 
		<a href="http://www.imo.org/home.asp?flash=false">
				<strong>International Maritime Organization</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> website.  The IMO is the United Nation's specialised agency responsible for improving maritime safety and preventing pollution from ships.</p><h2>Pilotage in Our Ports/Harbours</h2><p>The following is a summary of the Pilotage Directions which apply to vessels bound to or from <span class="gen">enter details</span> navigating in the Competent Harbour Authority (CHA) pilotage area, as set out in the Pilotage Act 1987.</p><p>
<span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=764"> Providing Information
		(764)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
