<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=780}]"><cms:name>houseboats-780</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Houseboats</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=780}]"><cms:name>houseboats-780-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>houseboats</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=780}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The following guidance must be observed by people who own houseboats that are located in waters maintained by this Council:</i></p><hr/><p>&quot;<strong>houseboat</strong>&quot; 
  means any vessel used or intended to be used for human habitation but shall 
  not include any ship registered under the Merchant Shipping Act 1894 or any 
  boat or vessel bona fide used for navigation </p><p>&quot;<strong>master</strong>&quot; 
  when used in connection with a vessel or houseboat means any person whether 
  the owner or not having or taking the command charge or management of the vessel 
  or houseboat for the time being <br/>
  <br/>
  &quot;<strong>under way</strong>&quot; when used in relation to a vessel or 
  houseboat means when she is not at anchor or moored or made fast to the shore 
  or aground </p><p>&quot;<strong>Harbour Master</strong>&quot; 
  means the Harbour Master appointed by the Council or any other officer appointed 
  by the Council and includes any duly authorised assistant of the Harbour Master 
  and of any such officer</p><h2>Keeping of Houseboats </h2><p> The 
  master of a houseboat shall not keep his houseboat in the harbour without the 
  written consent of the Harbour Master and such consent must specify the date 
  upon which it shall cease to have effect. </p><h2>Anchoring </h2><p> The master of a vessel 
  or houseboat shall not except in an emergency anchor in the harbour in such 
  a manner as to obstruct navigation </p><h2>Making Fast </h2><p> The master of a vessel 
  or houseboat shall not make fast to any other vessel or houseboat or her moorings 
  without the previous permission of the master of such other vessel or houseboat 
  or the owner of her moorings unless ordered to do so by the Harbour Master </p><h2>Not to Lie Alongside Others </h2><p>The master of a vessel or 
  houseboat shall not permit her without the previous consent of the Harbour Master 
  to lie at any mooring of the Council when a vessel or houseboat is already thereat 
  or alongside any other vessel or houseboat </p><h2>Obstruction of Others </h2><p>The master of a vessel or 
  houseboat shall not permit her to be placed in any position that may interfere 
  with the access by any other vessel or houseboat to any pier jetty wharf landing 
  steps landing place hard or grid without the permission of the Harbour Master.</p><h2>Change of Anchorage </h2><p>The master of any vessel 
  or houseboat lying within the harbour shall take up the anchor or anchors of 
  such vessel or houseboat if so required by the Harbour Master. </p><h2>Indication of Anchors </h2><p>The master of a vessel or 
  houseboat in letting go an anchor on to the fundus in the fairway of the harbour 
  shall have a watch-buoy attached thereto in such manner as clearly to indicate 
  its position if so required by the Harbour Master <br/>
  <br/>
  The master of every vessel or houseboat which has slipped or parted from an 
  anchor shall forthwith give notice thereof and of the position of such anchor 
  to the Harbour Master </p><h2> Vessels 
  to have Names Marked on Them </h2><p> The owner of a vessel which 
  is not registered as a ship under the Merchant Shipping Act 1894 or as a fishing 
  vessel under the Merchant Shipping Act 1988 and marked accordingly shall ensure 
  that the vessel is marked conspicuously with its name or other means of identification 
  unless exempted by the Harbour Master </p><h2>Registration of Vessels </h2><p>The owner of a vessel normally 
  kept within the harbour shall register the same with the Harbour Master forthwith 
  and shall thereafter register the vessel at intervals of not more than once 
  a year and shall inform the Harbour Master of the place where the vessel is 
  kept. </p><h2>Change of Ownership of Vessels </h2><p>On any change in the ownership 
  of a vessel kept within the harbour the parties to the change shall ensure that 
  immediate written notification is given to the Harbour Master </p><h2>Accommodation of Others </h2><p>The master of any vessel 
  or houseboat having any rope chain or other connection fastened to the shore 
  or to any post or buoy or mooring in the harbour shall when necessary or directed 
  by the Harbour Master slacken or haul taut the same as the case may require 
  for the accommodation of other vessels or houseboats moving in the harbour.</p><h2>Mooring or Anchoring </h2><p>The master of any vessel 
  which has an overall length greater than 60 feet or registered gross tonnage 
  greater than 40 tons or any houseboat shall when directed by the Harbour Master 
  moor or anchor his vessel or houseboat fore and aft </p><h2>Maintenance and Painting of Vessels 
  </h2><p>The master of a vessel or 
  houseboat shall not intentionally list his vessel or houseboat in order to undertake 
  maintenance work nor shall he engage in the scraping, blasting or painting of 
  such vessel or houseboat on the foreshore or mudlands or other part of the harbour 
  without the previous consent of the Harbour Master and then only in accordance 
  with such directions as he may give and subject to such conditions as he may 
  impose. </p><h2>Lighting of Craft </h2><p>The master of any houseboat 
  in the harbour shall if such houseboat be moored or anchored next to the fairway 
  of the harbour or if ordered to do so by the Harbour Master provide and maintain 
  between sunset and sunrise lights in accordance with the Merchant Shipping (Distress 
  Signals and Prevention of Collisions) Regulations 1989 (Part C Lights and Shapes)</p><h2>Placing etc. of Moorings </h2><p>No person shall place lay 
  down maintain use and have private moorings on the fundus or foreshore of the 
  harbour without a licence granted by the Council. Any person requiring such 
  a licence shall make written application therefor to the Harbour Master such 
  application to specify such information as the Council shall from time to time 
  require. </p><h2>Lifting and Removal of Moorings 
  </h2><p> No person shall (unless 
  required by the Harbour Master so to do) lift a private mooring from the fundus 
  or foreshore without giving to the Harbour Master at least 24 hours previous 
  written notice of the date and time when such mooring is to be lifted. </p><h2>Re-location of Moorings</h2><p> The owner or other person 
  in charge of a private mooring shall on the instruction of the Harbour Master 
  remove it from the harbour or to a new position therein. </p><h2>Identification 
  of Mooring Buoys and Like Apparatus </h2><p>No person shall place, lay 
  down, maintain, use and have private moorings which are not identifiable by 
  a distinctive mark, colour or other device previously indicated to and approved 
  by the Harbour Master and registered in his records at the Harbour Office and 
  the Harbour Master may require an amendment or variation of an identification 
  to avoid confusion or for any other good reason. </p><h2>Inspection of Moorings </h2><p>The master of any vessel 
  or houseboat shall on receipt of seven days written notice lift the moorings 
  of such vessel or houseboat for inspection by the Harbour Master </p><h2>Petrol and Oil not to be Pumped 
  into the Harbour</h2><p> Notwithstanding any statutory 
  provision no person on board a vessel or houseboat shall cause petrol or oil 
  or water mixed with these liquids to be pumped or permitted to run into the 
  waters of the harbour. </p><h2> Fire extinguishing equipment 
  to be available for use at all times </h2><p>The master of every vessel 
  within the harbour with the exception of rowing boats and other similar light 
  non-powered vessels shall have adequate fire-extinguishing equipment available 
  for immediate use in any part of the vessel at all times and the nature and 
  amount of such equipment shall take into account any abnormal fire risk associated 
  with any such vessel. </p><h2>Non-interference with fire equipment 
  </h2><p>No person shall without 
  lawful authority displace or interfere with any safety or fire equipment within 
  the harbour except in the event of an emergency. </p><h2>Landings </h2><p>No person shall tie any 
  vessel or houseboat to any landing steps, landing stage, pier, jetty, railings 
  or other property at which a notice prohibiting such action is displayed. </p><h2>Inspection facilities to be available 
  to Harbour Master </h2><p> The master of any vessel 
  or houseboat in the harbour shall when so required by the Harbour Master afford 
  every reasonable facility to enable the Harbour Master to ascertain whether 
  these guidelines are duly observed. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=780"> Providing Information
		(780)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
