<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=116}]"><cms:name>batch-17-116</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Council housing - current tenant arrears</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=116}]"><cms:name>batch-17-116-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>council, housing, current, tenant, arrears</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=116}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>How the Council deals with tenants who fall behind with their rent and what you can do to avoid this.  </i></p><hr/><p>The Council is reliant upon rental income to pay for the services that it delivers 
  to its Council tenants. If rent arrears increase it does have a definite effect 
  on the services that the Council tenants receive. For that reason it is critical 
  that rent arrears levels are kept to the minimum. </p><p>If a tenant falls into arrears the Council is sympathetic and will permit repayment 
  of those arrears by instalments. However, the most important thing is that a person 
  falling into arrears should make contact with the Housing Management Section. </p><p>The Council can only assist in solving the problem if the tenant contacts us to 
  let us know what the problem is. If arrears continue to rise, and the Council can 
  see no prospect of that changing, then the Council does have to take its tenants 
  to Court. </p><p>At the Court the Council will normally ask for what is termed a 'Suspended Possession 
  Order'. That is where the Court orders that the tenant must start paying the rent 
  and a small amount per week, fortnight, or month off of the arrears. Tenants are 
  encouraged to attend Court, should they be summoned. Even at this stage the Council 
  would much prefer to have the problem of the arrears resolved rather than have the 
  tenant evicted. </p><p>If a person has a Suspended Court Order against them the Council would still wish 
  to know if the tenant encounters any difficulty in making payments. We will exercise 
  some discretion, rather than just seeking to evict.</p><p>Regrettably, there does come a time when the Council appears to be faced with no 
  alternative but to evict a tenant. This is very much a last resort and it is not 
  an action taken lightly by the Council. If a person is evicted they do have a right 
  to make an appeal to the Council as being homeless. Whilst every case has to be 
  dealt on its merits the Council may well argue that if a person had the ability 
  to pay the rent, but did not do so, then they may be considered to be 'intentionally 
  homeless' and the Council would have no obligation to rehouse them. That would apply 
  even where there are children in the household. For this reason it is very important 
  that tenants deal with arrears issues at an early stage and the Housing Management 
  Section are always happy to give help and advice at an stage in an arrears problem.</p><p>When a person leaves a Council tenancy they become known as a 'former tenant'. 
  If there are arrears at the end of the tenancy the Council will continue to pursue 
  these. In practice, this may mean summonsing the former tenant to Court to get an 
  Order for payment. However, the addition of court costs against the former tenant 
  makes this an expensive option for the former tenant. In practice, we would much 
  rather negotiate repayment by instalments if clearing the debt in a single payment 
  is not possible. As always, it is important that people contact our Housing Management 
  Section to discuss these issues so that a mutually convenient solution can be negotiated.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=116"> Providing Information
		(116)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
