<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=120}]"><cms:name>housing-3-120</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing rents</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=120}]"><cms:name>housing-3-120-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, rents</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=120}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Council sets a rent for each property. There are a number of ways in which council tenants can pay their rent. We will help tenants to claim any available assistance with paying their rent. When tenants are in arrears we will make agreements to reduce the arrears. However, we do take legal action if tenants persistently fail to pay their rent. </i></p><hr/><h2>Paying your Rent </h2><p>There are a number of ways to pay your rent such as at you local Post Office, by Direct Debit, by cheque, Switch or debit card. </p><p>Direct Debit is an easy way in which you can pay your rent to the Council from your bank or building society account each month. </p><p>There are lots of advantages in paying your rent by Direct Debit, many of our tenants are just doing that.</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Once you have agreed to pay by Direct Debit, payments will be made automatically. You will no longer have to remember to pay each month.</li>
  <li title="*">You can put behind you worry of overlooking a payment, perhaps due to illness or being on holiday.</li>
  <li title="*">If a credit or debit is created on your rent account, your Direct Debit payment will be recalculated to take into consideration any changes to your rent account for the remanding monthly payments. You will receive 14 days notification of any changes to your Direct Debit to make sure it is correct.</li>
  <li title="*">When a tenancy ends the Direct Debit automatically ends.</li>
    <li title="*">The Council will update your Direct Debit every year and inform you of any changes. </li>
</ul><h2>Post Office Payment Card </h2><p>You can now pay your rent and council tax at Post Offices throughout the region using the Post Office Payment Card. You can request a Payment Card by using the contact details above.</p><h2>Help with paying your rent </h2><p>If you need help paying your rent you may be entitled to 
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=69">Housing Benefit</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 69</span> or your Housing Officer could give you advice and assistance on paying your rent. </p><h2>Repaying your rent  </h2><p>If you are in arrears we will try and reach a realistic agreement for you to repay the amount due over a period of time. The Council follows a legal procedure to recover arrears. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=120"> Providing Information
		(120)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
