<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=652}]"><cms:name>housing-3-652</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>General housing information and advice</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=652}]"><cms:name>housing-3-652-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>general, housing, information, advice</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=652}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We provide advice and assistance on a wide range of housing related problems. </i></p><hr/><p>Many people living in accommodation in the private sector, are 
  unsure of their rights and are unsure where they can go for help. Also, many landlords 
  renting out accommodation are not aware that we can offer 
  impartial advice regarding problems they may experience with their tenants.</p><p>We provide advice on:</p><p>
			<strong>Notices to Quit Accommodation</strong> - this includes notices 
  given to tenants because a tenancy is coming to an end, tenancy agreements that 
  have expired or are expiring, and issues where tenants may have breached the terms 
  of their tenancy agreement (for example, by non payment of rent).</p><p>
			<strong>Rent Increases</strong> - in most situations, a landlord 
  must follow a set procedure if he wants a tenant to pay more rent. </p><p>
			<strong>Disrepair</strong> - people living in private rented accommodation 
  can often have problems with disrepair and many landlords and tenants are not aware 
  of their obligations. There are also some schemes available to people that own their 
  homes.</p><p>
			<strong>Deposits</strong> - at the end of a tenancy, deposit money 
  may be withheld for different reasons. Advice can be given to landlords and tenants 
  in relation to this.</p><p>
			<strong>Relationship Breakdown</strong> - many people are not aware 
  of their rights when they separate from a partner. Advice can be given regarding 
  their housing situation and any benefits they may be entitled to.</p><p>
			<strong>Mortgages</strong> - people fall into mortgage arrears for 
  many different reasons, such as unemployment or health problems. There are various 
  options available which can prevent someone from losing their home, even if court 
  proceedings have already begun.</p><p>
			<strong>Long Leaseholders with a private Freeholder</strong> - problems 
  can be experienced with the Freeholder, for example, in relation to Service Charges.</p><p>
			<strong>Welfare Benefits</strong> - many people are not aware of 
  the wide range of benefits they may be entitled to. For example, checks can be carried 
  out for people wanting to return to work if they are unsure how their benefits will 
  be affected.</p><p>
			<strong>Homelessness</strong> - advice can be given at any time if 
  people think they may be homeless in the future, or where they are already homeless.</p><p>
			<strong>Housing Options</strong> - there are a range of options which 
  are available to people who are looking for alternative housing.</p><p>
			<strong>Landlords</strong> - if you have a property to rent within 
  the <span class="gen">enter council name here</span>, there are a variety 
  of schemes available to assist you.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=652"> Providing Information
		(652)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
