<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=163}]"><cms:name>batch-22-163</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Counselling</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=163}]"><cms:name>batch-22-163-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>counselling</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=163}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>At present there are no national standards for counselling and psychotherapy.</i></p><hr/><p>Under current regulations anyone can set themselves up as a 
  psychotherapist or counsellor and charge patients for consultations. This leads 
  to a wide variation in the level of competence and expertise available.</p><p>Until such time as statutory regulation is introduced, those 
  employing counsellors should ensure that their recruitment arrangements are stringent 
  and that therapists meet the training and supervision standards identified by the 
  relevant professional organisations.</p><p>Those individuals using counselling services should be aware 
  of what to expect from a counsellor and should be encouraged to work with counsellors 
  who subscribe to professional bodies recognised codes of ethics and practice.</p><p>We have found it helpful to explain what counselling is at the 
  beginning so that you may get most benefit from it.</p><p>Counselling is different from other forms of help; the focus 
  is to enable you to clarify the issues about which you are troubled. This will involve 
  you in exploring those issues in private with someone who is trained to listen and 
  has no other role in your life. Through this confidential process, your counsellor 
  will be seeking to enable you to clarify your thoughts and feelings. Counselling 
  is a positive process, which is often associated with times of personal crisis. 
  It may involve talking about painful parts of your life and therefore, you may feel 
  worse before you feel better! It is also a very effective way of developing personal 
  potential. If we are not the best people to help we will refer you elsewhere or 
  suggest alternatives which may be more appropriate.</p><p>Counselling and Psychotherapy can be helpful for a wide range of difficulties such as: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Depression </li>
  <li title="*">Relationship Problems </li>
  <li title="*">Stress </li>
  <li title="*">Anxiety/Panic Attacks </li>
  <li title="*">Low Self-Esteem </li>
  <li title="*">Eating Problems </li>
  <li title="*">Sexual Problems </li>
  <li title="*">Bereavement and Loss </li>
  <li title="*">Trauma Resulting from Accident, Assault or Abuse </li>
</ul><p>The Counsellors in this service work within the British Association 
  for Counselling and Psychotherapy's (BACP) 'Ethical Framework for Good 
  Practice', which ensures that what you speak about in your session, remains 
  confidential. The details of the confidentiality contract will be explained to you 
  in your first session. All counsellors within the service have supervision, which 
  involves presenting their work anonymously, to ensure that quality is maintained.</p><p>Counsellors keep written records of their sessions with clients. 
  These are kept according to data protection guidelines and service record keeping 
  procedures. Each session lasts for <span class="gen">enter amount</span> minutes. To get the most from the session 
  please ensure you arrive on time, as your counsellor will need to finish promptly. 
</p><p>If you are unable to keep the appointment please let us know, 
  giving at least <span class="gen">enter amount</span> hours notice.</p><p>We hope you find counselling a positive and helpful experience.</p><p>Please contact us for more details using the details above.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=163"> Providing Information
		(163)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
