<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=164}]"><cms:name>batch-22-164</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Harassment Help</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=164}]"><cms:name>batch-22-164-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>harassment, help</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=164}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Harassment is any form of unwanted and unwelcome behaviour which may range from mildly unpleasant remarks to physical violence.  </i></p><hr/><p>Harassment is termed <strong>sexual harassment</strong> if the unwanted behaviours are linked to your gender or sexual orientation. The EU definition of sexual harassment is &quot;unwanted conduct of a sexual nature or other conduct based on sex affecting the dignity of men and women at work&quot;. </p><p>
<strong>Racial harassment</strong> is when the behaviours are linked to your skin colour, race, cultural background, etc. In countries with sectarian tradition (eg as in Ireland) the term <strong>sectarian harassment</strong> is often used if the behaviours are linked to your religious beliefs or perceived religious origin or inclination. If the harassment is physical, the criminal law of <strong>assault</strong> may be appropriate. If the harassment comprises regular following, watching, repeated unsolicited contact or gifts, etc, the term <strong>stalking</strong> may be appropriate. </p><p>Discrimination is when you are treated differently (eg less favourably) because of your gender, race or disability. </p><p>Bullying is the common denominator of harassment, discrimination, abuse and violence etc. The source of most bullying and harassment can usually be traced to one individual. </p><p>The differences between harassment and bullying are, briefly; harassment tends to have a strong physical component and is usually linked to gender, race, disability or physical violence; bullying tends to be a large number of incidents (individually trivial) over a long period comprising constant unjustified and unsubstantiated criticism. </p><p>Bullying and harassment (at work, in society, at school and at home) is a major cause of injury to health, both physical and mental. Over time, bullying and harassment result in trauma, which is a psychiatric injury, the collective symptoms of which often constitute Post Traumatic Stress Disorder, or PTSD. </p><h2> Areas of UK law that apply to harassment </h2><p>The principal areas of UK law relating to harassment comprise: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">
<strong>Sex Discrimination Act 1975</strong>: discrimination on the grounds of sex by dismissing an employee or submitting them to &quot;any other detriment&quot;</li>
  <li title="*">
<strong>Race Relations Act 1976</strong>: ditto on racial grounds</li>
  <li title="*">
<strong>Disability Discrimination Act 1995</strong>: ditto on grounds of disability</li>
  <li title="*">
<strong>Protection from Harassment Act 1996</strong>: harassment and stalking</li>
  <li title="*">
<strong>Criminal Justice and Public Order Act 1994</strong>: intentional harassment for causing another person harassment, alarm or distress by using threatening, abusive or insulting words or behaviour</li>
  <li title="*">Criminal law of <strong>assault </strong>
</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>

		<a href="http://www.bullyonline.org/">Bully Online</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to external website</span>is the world's largest resource on bullying and related issues.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=164"> Providing Information
		(164)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
