<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=12}]"><cms:name>education-3-12</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Nursery school places</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=12}]"><cms:name>education-3-12-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>nursery, school, places</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=12}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We seek to ensure that as many 4 year old children as possible are offered a one year, part - time place in a nursery school or class which provides quality Early Years education.</i></p><hr/><p>If your child will be 4 years old between <span class="gen">enter date</span> 
  and <span class="gen">enter date</span> and you would like to take advantage of part-time nursery education, 
  you should contact as soon as possible the headteacher of the school whose nursery 
  you would like your child to attend. </p><p>The headteacher will keep a list of pupils whose parents have 
  asked for a place. This place will normally be for 5 morning or 5 afternoon sessions 
  a week. The headteacher will inform you by letter in March if a place is available 
  for your child. If there are more requests for places than there are places available, 
  the following criteria will be used to decide admissions, in order of priority. 
</p><h4>1. Children with Special Educational Needs</h4><p>Those children who have been identified as having special educational 
  needs, or who require assessment to decide if they have such needs and would benefit 
  from nursery education. </p><h4>2. Children with Medical Needs</h4><p>These children will be children whose medical needs have been 
  identified by professional services but would not receive a statement of special 
  educational needs. </p><h4>3. Children from Families with Exceptional Home Circumstances</h4><p>This would include giving consideration to children whose families 
  are unable to give them appropriate pre-school experience or who are recommended 
  by other professional services. </p><h4>4. Age (older children receive priority)</h4><h4>5. Distance from Home to School (taking into account ease of 
  access to and distance from alternatives)</h4><p>In practice, most places will be allocated using criteria 4 
  and 5. </p><p>The headteacher is responsible for informing parents if they 
  have been allocated a place for their child. </p><h4>Parents not allocated a place</h4><p>Parents who are not allocated a place at a nursery class will 
  be informed in writing by the headteacher. A booklet of alternative providers of 
  nursery education will accompany this refusal letter. Parents should then make their 
  own enquiries about vacancies directly with another school, private day nursery 
  or pre-school. </p><h4>Younger Children</h4><p>Children who become 3 between <span class="gen">enter date</span> and <span class="gen">enter date</span> may be offered a place at a Nursery from <span class="gen">enter date</span> after their third birthday, 
  if places are still available. Headteachers cannot save places for 'rising 3' year 
  olds. </p><h4>Please note:</h4><p>If your child attends the nursery class attached to a mainstream 
  Infant or Primary School, this is not a criterion for admission to the reception 
  class at that school and no place can be guaranteed for your child. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=12"> Providing Information
		(12)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
