<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=13}]"><cms:name>education-3-13</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Primary school places</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=13}]"><cms:name>education-3-13-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>primary, school, places</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=13}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Basic information regarding primary school places</i></p><hr/><p>In September <span class="gen">enter date</span>, 
  there will be over <span class="gen">enter amount</span> children 
  starting primary school in <span class="gen">enter council name</span>
		</p><p>If the number of places at each school in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> were unlimited, then every child would be able to 
  attend their preferred primary school, but unfortunately this is not the case. The 
  number of children each school can accept is limited, and the Council cannot guarantee 
  that a place will be available at your preferred school.</p><p>The Government has introduced a class size initiative. No 5, 
  6 or 7 year old at Key Stage 1 should be in a class of over 30 pupils for a normal 
  teaching session.</p><p>If you cannot be allocated a place at your preferred school, 
  consideration will be given to your named alternative on the application form.</p><h4>Application Procedures</h4><p>The normal procedure is that you tell the school of your choice 
  that you would like a place there for your child.</p><p>Admission arrangements for Community schools and Voluntary Controlled 
  church schools are different from arrangements for Voluntary Aided church schools.</p><p>Details of how to apply and how places are allocated are given 
  on this page.</p><h4>Applying for a place at a community/voluntary controlled school</h4><p>The Council is responsible for allocating places at all Community 
  schools and Voluntary Controlled schools and all requests for places are dealt with 
  by officers of the Council.</p><p>You should make sure that your child's name is known to your 
  preferred primary school. In most cases this will be your local primary school. 
  </p><p>An 
			 is available <span class="gen">link to online form</span>, and ALL copies should be completed 
  and returned to your preferred school by <span class="gen">enter date</span>
		</p><p>Should a preferred school not be named on the form, a place 
  will be allocated to the school nearest to your home that has places available. 
  </p><p>The form will be signed upon receipt, on behalf of the school. 
  The schools will then pass one copy of all forms to the School Organisation Section 
  at the Council Offices. One copy will be retained by the school for their records. 
  The remaining copy will be made available to the parent to acknowledge receipt of 
  the application. </p><p>All requests for schools are considered at the same time. Late 
  applications will be dealt with after all places have been allocated to pupils whose 
  Admission Forms were submitted on time, if the available class has been filled to 
  the maximum of 30 it will not be possible (in normal circumstances) to offer a place 
  at that school.  </p><h4>Special Circumstances</h4><p>On the Admission Form there is a box marked Special Circumstances. 
  You should tick this box if you have special reasons for wanting a place at a particular 
  school. These could be medical or exceptional family circumstances. </p><p>Please give as much information as you can which might help 
  us when allocating places, by filling in the Special Circumstances sheet. If your 
  child has particular needs relating to accommodation, please include these details 
  as part of your 'Special Circumstances'. The sheet should be attached to the Admission 
  Form . All information will be treated in the strictest confidence. </p><h4>How places are allocated to community and voluntary controlled 
  schools</h4><p>Each school has an admission limit, which has been agreed by 
  the Council following discussion with the Governing Body of the school.</p><p>If there are fewer requests for places at a particular school 
  than the admission limit, the Council will ask the headteacher to offer a place 
  to each child. </p><p>If the school is oversubscribed, ie. there are more requests 
  for places at a school than places available, the Council apply criteria to decide 
  which children should gain places </p><p>Please note: All applications submitted by the closing date 
  will be dealt with at the same time. This means that your child will not get greater 
  priority if his/her name has been known to the school longer than other children. 
  </p><p>It is also important to remember that attendance at a nursery 
  school which is attached to, or near to, a particular primary school does not guarantee 
  your child a place at the school. </p><h4>Applying for a place at a voluntary aided church school</h4><p>The Governing Body of each Voluntary Aided (Church) school deals 
  with admissions to that particular school. </p><p>You should make sure that your child's name is known to your 
  preferred primary school. Closing dates vary and you should contact your preferred 
  school as soon as possible. If you are not offered a place at a Voluntary Aided 
  school before the closing date for admission to Community schools, you should apply 
  for a place at a Community school. </p><p>Each Voluntary Aided school has its own criteria for deciding 
  admission if the school is over subscribed (ie. if more pupils want places at the 
  school than there are places available). </p><p>The headteacher of the school concerned can inform you of the 
  criteria that he or she is required to apply. In general the following guidance 
  may be of help. </p><h4>
			<strong>Church of England Voluntary Aided Schools</strong>
		</h4><p>These schools wish to preserve the denominational character 
  and ethos of the spiritual tradition on which they are founded. </p><p>Criteria for allocations may include factors such as membership 
  of a church. Both length of time and frequency of attendance, are taken into consideration, 
  and often written confirmation of attendance from a clergyman is requested. </p><p>A sibling connection is important in all cases, but not necessarily 
  a priority. </p><p>In the case of oversubscription, (too many requests for the 
  places available) a practicing Christian family is the first criterion in over 50% 
  of the schools, while a sibling connection is the first criterion in the remaining 
  schools. </p><p>These are general features, common to all these schools. To 
  obtain more detailed information about an individual school, parents are advised 
  to consult each school's own prospectus. </p><p>
			<strong>Roman Catholic Voluntary Aided Primary Schools</strong>
		</p><p>These schools wish to preserve the denominational character 
  and ethos of the spiritual tradition on which they are founded. In many cases, when 
  considering admissions, the Governing Body insists that the child should be a baptised 
  Catholic, and should attend the church regularly. Proof of baptism may be requested. 
  </p><p>Baptised Catholic children from neighbouring churches will also 
  be considered. </p><p>These are general features, common to all these schools. To 
  obtain more detailed information about an individual school, parents are advised 
  to consult each school's own prospectus. </p><p>A number of Voluntary Aided Roman Catholic schools have an agreement 
  with the Local Education Authority under Section 91 of the School Standards and 
  Framework Act 1998. This means that the school can limit the number of children 
  admitted to the school who are not of the school's particular faith. These agreements will cease to operate, 
  as a result of changes in legislation, for admissions from <span class="gen">enter date</span> onwards. 
  If you have any queries about this, please speak to the headteacher of the school. 
  </p><p>If you are seeking a place from a Roman Catholic Voluntary aided primary school and you are unsuccessful, you have the right of appeal to the Governing Body. The headteacher 
  will inform you, on request, about the appeal arrangements at the school. In normal 
  circumstances the Appeal Panel cannot admit pupils if there are already 30 in the 
  class. </p><h4>Criteria for allocating places at oversubscribed community 
  and voluntary controlled schools </h4><p>You should be aware that a number of schools are oversubscribed 
  each year. Where a school is oversubscribed, places will be offered on the basis 
  of the four criteria indicated below, in order of priority, and will take into account 
  the availability of accommodation at other schools in the area. </p><li title="*">
				<strong>Brothers/Sisters</strong> - If there are any brothers/sisters living at the same 
    address, attending the school or its associated junior school, provided that the 
    school is chosen as first preference, and the application is received on time.</li><li title="*">
				<strong>Exceptional Medical Reasons</strong> - If a medical reason is claimed, evidence 
    from the child's own doctor that the child has an ongoing medical condition which 
    means that admission to a particular school is essential, must be provided at 
    the same time as the admission form. This information will be passed on in confidence 
    to the Community Health Physician and/or the Educational Psychology Service for 
    further discussion and an appointment would usually be made to consider the condition.</li><li title="*">
				<strong>Exceptional Family Reasons</strong> - Where admission to a particular school is 
    essential for the wellbeing of the family, written evidence should clearly demonstrate 
    this need. Many families have complex childcare arrangements, for example, and 
    factors such as these are not considered as exceptional.</li><li title="*">
				<strong>Distance</strong> - Preference will be given to pupils living nearest the school 
    taking into account ease of access to and distance from alternative schools. 
    <p>The 'statutory walking distance', measured over the 'nearest available 
    route' is two miles, for children under the age of eight. (Section 199 Education 
    Act 1993).</p>
				<p>Ease of access will be considered when no other school is within a reasonable travelling 
  distance and the school in question is the nearest school. </p>
				<p>Places are allocated on the basis of the parent's principal home address. The only 
  address that the Authority can consider is the address of the parent/guardian with 
  whom the child is permanently resident. Where the proposed admission is to coincide 
  with a change of address, the Authority will require evidence such as a solicitor's 
  confirmation of exchange of contracts.</p>
				<p>If the child is cared for on a daily basis at another address, for example, 
      by a childminder, grandparents or another member of the family, this address 
      cannot be considered by the authority for the purpose of its admission process.</p>
				<p>Where schools are likely to be oversubscribed, parents will be asked to provide 
  proof of the principal address, by way of official documents displaying the name 
  and address of the parents. </p>
				<p>Please note that strong action will be taken by the Council if a false address 
  is given, including withdrawal of the offer of a place at the named school(s). </p>
			</li><p>What happens if you do not gain a place at your preferred school?</p><p>If you are not offered your preferred school, a place in another 
  school will be offered. If you have stated a second preference, the Council will 
  offer a place at this school if the places have not been filled with parents who 
  made it their first preference. More information regarding 
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=705">
				<strong>appeals</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to pid 705.</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=13"> Applications for services
		(13)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset><cms:links oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contentassets.RelatedLink:{id=13}]"><cms:targetType>internalLink</cms:targetType><cms:linkOrder>1</cms:linkOrder><cms:linkTitle>PDF Form</cms:linkTitle><cms:targetItem oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.FileStorageItem:{id=13}]"/></cms:links></cms:item>
