<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=14}]"><cms:name>education-3-14</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Secondary school places</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=14}]"><cms:name>education-3-14-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>secondary, school, places</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=14}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Frequently Asked Questions regarding admission to Secondary School</i></p><hr/><ul>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#1">Where can I get detailed information about individual schools?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#2">What types of schools are there?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#3">When can my child start school?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#4">Supporting information</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#5">Applying out of authority</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#6">Changing schools other than at the normal transfer age</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#7">Parental Preference</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#8">Community schools over subscription criteria</a>	
</li>
		</ul><h4>

			Where can I get detailed information about individual schools?</h4><p>Every school publishes its own prospectus which it will give to parents on request. In the prospectus parents will find information about the school's</p><ul>
				<li title="*">aims and values</li>
				<li title="*">organisation of teaching</li>
				<li title="*">public examination results</li>
				<li title="*">National Curriculum assessment results</li>
				<li title="*">attendance figures</li>
				<li title="*">admissions policy</li>
				<li title="*">level of demand for places in the previous year (secondary schools)</li>
			</ul><p>Information about examination results will be available from secondary schools each November. You can contact a school direct</p><h4>

			What types of school are there?</h4><p>
<strong>Community Schools</strong>
</p><p>These are schools which are established, maintained and controlled 
  by the Council. The majority of schools in the borough are community schools. The 
  Council is responsible for all admissions to community schools. </p><p>
<strong>Voluntary Schools</strong>
</p><p>Some schools were established and are owned by a voluntary body. 
  Usually it is a church body, either Church of England or Roman Catholic, but this 
  does not have to be the case. The governing body of a voluntary school has a majority 
  of its governors appointed by the church authority or foundation which provides 
  the school. The purpose of these foundation governors is to look after the interests 
  of the founding authority. This would, for example, seek to preserve any religious 
  associations which the school has. Voluntary Aided Schools are responsible for all 
  their own admissions arrangements. Admissions decisions are taken by the governing 
  body. Voluntary Controlled Schools, like community schools, have their admissions 
  handled by the Council.</p><h4>

			When can my child start school?</h4><p>Transfer from primary to secondary education takes place in 
  the September following a child's eleventh birthday. In October parents of children 
  in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> schools who are 
  due to transfer in the following September will receive a letter from the Director 
  Education and Children's Services along with an application form and notes of guidance 
  which explain how to fill it in.</p><h4>

			Supporting Information</h4><p>The admissions authority, which is the local education authority 
  for community schools and the governing body for voluntary aided schools, has a 
  duty to operate its published admissions procedures fairly and equally for all applicants. 
  So that this can happen, it is important that all the information which parents 
  provide in support of an application is accurate and honest. This ranges from the 
  child's normal place of residence through to information about any exceptional medical 
  or social circumstances which the authority is being asked to take into consideration. 
  If any of this information is shown to be false, for example if a child is not normally 
  resident at the address given on the application form, then the offer of a place 
  may be withdrawn at any time. Parents who get a place for their child as a result 
  of false information are taking away from another child who is more deserving of it.</p><h4>
				
			Applying out of authority</h4><p>Parents of children living in the areas of other local education 
  authorities who wish to apply for secondary places in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> schools are advised to apply in writing to the Admissions 
  Officer, Education and Children's Services at the address given below for applications 
  for community schools.</p><p>Parents resident in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> who wish to apply for places in schools maintained by other 
  authorities should apply to the authority concerned (see list of all neighbouring 
  authorities below) and, at the same time, notify the Education and Children's Services 
  Directorate in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> that 
  they are seeking a place elsewhere.</p><p>Parents living in the areas of other local education authorities 
  and whose children are attending a <span class="gen">enter council name</span> primary school, are advised to also apply for places in schools 
  maintained by their local education authority. Doing so will not reduce their chances 
  of being offered a place in a <span class="gen">enter council name</span> 
  school, but will ensure their child is not left without an offer of a school place.</p><h4>
				
			Changing schools other than at the normal transfer 
  age</h4><p>Parents who wish their child to transfer to another school at 
  any time other than the normal stages of 11 plus or 16 plus should first of all 
  discuss it with the headteacher of the school concerned, before completing an application 
  form. Parents applying for places in voluntary aided schools should write to the 
  Headteacher direct. Parents applying for places in community and voluntary controlled 
  schools other than in the normal intake year will be offered a place in the nearest 
  school with a vacancy in that age group.</p><h4>
				
			Parental Preference</h4><p>Parents have the right to express a preference for the school 
  they would like their child to attend. All schools must admit children up to their 
  admission limit which is published in this brochure and in each school's own prospectus. 
  Wherever possible places are offered in the school which the parents prefer. However, 
  if there are more applicants for a school than there are places available, there 
  has to be a way of deciding which children will be admitted.</p><h4>
				
			Community Schools over subscription criteria:</h4><p>Priority 1. Children who are normally resident in the catchment area of a school *(see note below)</p><p>Priority 1a. Children who have been unsuccessful at obtaining a catchment area place at priority 1.</p><p>Priority 2. Applications on medical grounds. Medical grounds must relate to the individual child's medical condition.</p><p>Priority 3. Applications on social grounds, or on grounds of having an older brother or sister at the school at the same time;</p><p>Priority 4. All other applications allocated on the actual distance measured in a straight line from the child's home to the school.</p><p>(*) Please note, in the event that a school is over-subscribed from within the catchment area the over subscription criteria will be applied to the catchment area children using the following principles:</p><ul>
				<li title="*">Applications on medical grounds. Medical grounds must relate to the individual child's medical condition.</li>
				<li title="*">Applications on social grounds, or on grounds of having an older brother or 
    sister at the school at the same time</li>
				<li title="*">Applications from children attending one of the school's linked primary schools</li>
				<li title="*">All other applications allocated on the actual distance measured in a straight 
    line from the child's home to the school.</li>
			</ul><p>Places are offered in February. Parents will then be given four 
  weeks in which to accept or decline the offer.</p><p>At the end of the four week period the offer of a place, including 
  a catchment area place, will be withdrawn from any parent who has declined the offer 
  or who has not responded. Those places will then be offered immediately to children 
  on the waiting list.</p><p>All applications received by the closing date on the form are 
  treated equally. Any late or amended applications will be considered after these, 
  unless there are particular circumstances which prevented the application being 
  made earlier.</p><p>If parents are refused the school of their preference, including 
  if this is the catchment area school they will be entitled to stay on the waiting 
  list of the school they have a preference for. Please note places will only be offered 
  off the waiting list on a monthly basis following the initial offer date. Please 
  note that a child's waiting list position can move up or down.</p><p>The places which are offered in February are provisional offers 
  only. It is important that parents provide the local education authority with any 
  information relating to changes in circumstances, as soon as they occur. If you 
  have been offered a catchment area place or a place on distance and you change address 
  this offer of a place can be withdrawn as a result.</p><p>The admissions authority does have the power under the Education 
  Act 1998 to set aside these arrangements and refuse a place if the admission of 
  additional children would prejudice the provision of efficient education or the 
  efficient use of resources. These Admission Arrangements apply for one year only. 
  The admissions policy is reviewed on an annual basis. This includes any catchment 
  area arrangements.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=14"> Providing Information
		(14)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
