<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=15}]"><cms:name>education-3-15</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>School records for an individual pupil</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=15}]"><cms:name>education-3-15-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>school, records, individual, pupil</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=15}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We are often asked how long certain records should be retained by a school before they can be disposed of. It is important to remember that many school records are of invaluable help for local historical and genealogical research and there should be a presumption against destroying any records unless it is considered that they are of no such value.</i></p><hr/><p>
				The following guidance is by no means exhaustive but covers 
  the items most frequently asked about:
			</p><p>
				<strong>School Log Books</strong> - must be retained permanently. 
  When a log book is completed send it to the Record Office.
			</p><p>
				<strong>Admission Registers</strong> - these should be retained permanently 
  - note that this is not the same as the class register in which daily attendance 
  is marked.
			</p><p>
				<strong>Pupil Record cards or printouts</strong> - to be retained 
  for a minimum of seven years after the pupil has left school or until the pupil 
  has reached the age of 25 years, whichever is the later date.
			</p><p>
				<strong>Class registers</strong> - to be retained whilst the pupils 
  are still at school. For example, if a pupil enters school in September 2001 and 
  leaves in July 2008, the September 2001 register for that class can only be destroyed 
  in 2008.
			</p><p>
				Schools often have presentations, open days, pageants, plays, 
  old photographs and other records that play an important part in the life of the 
  school. These records can be deposited with the Record Office but we would suggest 
  that they be given a free hand to decide which should or should not be retained.
			</p><p>
				In every case, the Record Office will confirm what they have 
  retained and send a copy of the retention details to the school for their information. 
  Often, schools will want to put on a display of old records for special events. 
  So long as advance notice is provided for the Record Office they will be able to 
  arrange for the loan of the records for the school subject to certain safeguards 
  concerning the security of the items whilst on display. Please contact the Record 
  Office for full details of the terms under which such loans can be made. Please 
  remember that the Record Office has two vital advantages concerning the storage 
  of records - they have a proper temperature and humidity controlled environment 
  and access to conservation experts both internal and external.
			</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=15"> Providing Information
		(15)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
