<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=29}]"><cms:name>education-3-29</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>School governors</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=29}]"><cms:name>education-3-29-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>School Governors</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>school, governors</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=29}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>What do governors do and how can I become one?</i></p><hr/><h4>What do governors do?</h4><ul>
			<li title="*">promote high standards of educational attainment</li>
			<li title="*">set targets for pupil achievement</li>
			<li title="*">take general responsibility for the conduct of the school</li>
			<li title="*">manage the school's budget, including deciding how many staff will work there and their pay</li>
			<li title="*">make sure that the curriculum is balanced and broadly based,in particular that the National Curriculum and religious education are taught, and report on pupils' achievement in National Curriculum assessments and examination results.</li>
			<li title="*">participate in the appointment of senior staff (including appointing the head 
    teacher) and regulate staff conduct and discipline; and</li>
			<li title="*">draw up an action plan after an inspection by the Office for Standards in Education (Ofsted)</li>
		</ul><h4>Why do schools need governors?</h4><p>Every School has a Governing Body to represent the public in 
  the running of schools. School Governors bring perspectives from ordinary life and 
  work with the staff and the Local Authority to help secure the best possible education 
  for the children in the school. They have important responsibilities like managing 
  the school budget, overseeing the curriculum and appointing staff.</p><h4>Becoming a governor</h4><p>
			<strong>I declare that I am aged 18 or over and the following statements are true:</strong>
		</p><li title="*">I do not already hold a governorship at the same school;</li><li title="*">I am not liable to be detained under the Mental Health Act 1983;</li><li title="*">I am not a member of the governing body of more than two schools (excluding ex-officio governors, temporary governors, or additional governors at schools 
    causing concern);</li><li title="*">I am not an ex-officio governor specified in the instrument of government of 
    more than two schools;</li><li title="*">I am not a bankrupt or subject to a disqualification order under the Company Directors Disqualification Act 1986 or to an order made under section 429(2)(b) 
    of the Insolvency Act 1986;</li><li title="*">I have not been removed from the office of a charity trustee or trustee for 
    a charity by an order made by the Charity Commissioners or the High Court on the 
    grounds of any misconduct or mismanagement or, under section 7 of the Law Reform 
    (Miscellaneous Provisions) (Scotland) Act 1990, from being concerned in the management 
    or control of any body;</li><li title="*">I am not included in the list (List 99) of teachers and workers with children 
    or young persons whose employment is prohibited or restricted;</li><li title="*">I am not disqualified from being the proprietor of any independent school or 
    for being a teacher or other employee in any school;</li><li title="*">I have not, in the five years prior to becoming a governor, received a sentence of imprisonment, suspended or otherwise, for a period of not less than three months 
    without the option of a fine;</li><li title="*">I have not, in the twenty years prior to becoming a governor, been convicted as aforesaid of any offence and has had passed on me a sentence of imprisonment 
    for a period of not less than two and a half years;</li><li title="*">I have not, at any time, had passed on me a sentence of imprisonment for a period of not less than five years;</li><li title="*">I have not been fined, in the five years prior to becoming a governor, for causing a nuisance or disturbance on education premises;</li><li title="*">I am not subject to a disqualification order under the Criminal Justice and 
    Court Services Act 2000.</li><p>If you require further information or advice regarding becoming 
  a governor, please contact us using the details above.</p><h4>
			
			Selection Criteria for Governors</h4><p>In making decisions on the appointment of LEA Governors the following criteria needs to be met:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Has a commitment to, and an interest in, education; </li>
			<li title="*">Has a desire to support the school concerned;</li>
			<li title="*">Has a willingness to serve the local community;</li>
			<li title="*">Has skills and experience which will support the work of the school;</li>
			<li title="*">Has the ability to work as a member of a team;</li>
			<li title="*">Is able to arrange their commitments to fit in with membership of a Governing 
    Body;</li>
			<li title="*">Will respect the Council's views on education matters at Governing Body meetings.</li>
		</ul><p>An <strong>
				
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=29a">Application</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to online form</span> to become a LEA governor is available</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=29"> Applications for services
		(29)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
