<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=34}]"><cms:name>education-3-34</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>School - permanent exclusions</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=34}]"><cms:name>education-3-34-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>school, permanent, exclusions</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=34}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Frequently Asked Questions regarding Permanent Exclusion</i></p><hr/><ul>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#1">If my child is at risk of permanent exclusion what happens?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#2">Can my child be permanently excluded for a serious first incident?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#3">What if my child has emotional and behavioural difficulties, or a learning difficulty...?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#4">What if my child has a statement for special Educational Needs?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#5">How am I told that my child has been permanently excluded?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#6">The Headteacher should then write a letter to you within one school day that gives.</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#7">What if I disagree with my child's permanent exclusion?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#8">What is the Discipline Committee?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#9">What happens at the Discipline Committee Meeting?</a>	
</li>
		<li title="*">

		<a href="#10">If the Governors uphold the permanent exclusion, is there anything else I can do...?</a>	
</li>
		</ul><p>Permanent Exclusion is a very serious matter.</p><p>Only a school's headteacher can permanently exclude a pupil 
  or a named deputy if the headteacher is out of school.</p><p>A Headteacher may decide to permanently exclude a pupil only 
  when he is sure that:</p><ul>
				<li title="*">the pupil has seriously breached the school's discipline policy.</li>
				<li title="*">if the pupil remains in school, it would seriously harm the education or welfare of the pupil or others in the school.</li>
			</ul><h4>

			If my child is at risk of permanent exclusion 
  what happens?</h4><p>In <span class="gen">enter council name</span> 
  a school should refer your child to the Education Welfare Service if they feel that 
  your child is at risk of permanent exclusion.</p><p>An Education Welfare Officer will contact you.</p><p>They will work with the school and yourself to try to prevent 
  your child from being permanently excluded.</p><p>The school can draw up a Pastoral Support Programme to outline 
  ways of helping your child. This plan will be agreed with you and may set targets 
  for the pupil, parent/carers, school and other support groups.</p><h4>

			Can my child be permanently excluded for a 
  serious first incident?</h4><p>Not normally. Permanent exclusion should not normally be used 
  for a first serious incident unless the Headteacher feels that he must take action 
  immediately to protect the pupils and staff in the school. Even then he/she must 
  take time to consider the matter carefully and use permanent exclusion as a last 
  resort.</p><h4>

			What if my child has emotional and behavioural 
  difficulties, or a learning difficulty that affects their behaviour in school?</h4><p>The school can ask the LEA to review the statement if your child 
  is at risk of permanent exclusion. You would be invited to the review meeting. At 
  the review meeting other ways of dealing with your child's behaviour can be 
  discussed to try to avoid permanent exclusion.</p><h4>

			What if my child has a statement for special Educational Needs?</h4><p>The school may present evidence about your child's educational 
  ability, behaviour and social background as well as the facts surrounding the incident 
  which led to the permanent exclusion. The LEA will give its view and say whether 
  it feels that permanent exclusion is appropriate or not. You will receive copies 
  of this information in advance of the hearing.</p><h4>

			How am I told that my child has been permanently excluded?</h4><p>Once the Headteacher has decided to permanently exclude your 
  child he/she should contact you immediately to explain his/her decision. He/she 
  should telephone you if possible on the day and the exclusion should normally begin 
  the following day.</p><h4>

			The Headteacher should then write a letter to you within one school day that gives:</h4><ul>
				<li title="*">the reason for your child's permanent exclusion</li>
				<li title="*">the steps taken to avoid permanent exclusion</li>
				<li title="*">the date that the permanent exclusion begins</li>
				<li title="*">arrangements for your child to have school work to do at home</li>
				<li title="*">your right to see a copy of your child's school record</li>
				<li title="*">your right to give your views on your child's permanent exclusion at a 
    meeting with school governors on the Discipline Committee</li>
				<li title="*">a final date for you to send any written statements to the Discipline Committee before the meeting</li>
				<li title="*">the phone number of someone in the LEA who can advise you and the phone number of the national Advisory Centre for Education</li>
			</ul><h4>

			What if I disagree with my child's permanent exclusion?</h4><p>You can put your views in writing and in person to school governors 
  at a meeting of their discipline committee. The Clerk to the discipline committee 
  will write to give you the date and time of the meeting.</p><h4>

			What is the discipline Committee?</h4><p>The Discipline Committee is made up of three to five of the 
  school's governors. They follow guidance from the government and the local education 
  authority to decide whether exclusion is being carried out correctly in the school.</p><h4>

			What happens at the Discipline Committee Meeting?</h4><p>The Governors will consider the views of the school, you and 
  your child and the LEA. The governors can decide to uphold your child's permanent 
  exclusion or allow your child to return to school.</p><h4>

			If the governors uphold the permanent exclusion, 
  is there anything else I can do to return my child to school?</h4><p>You can appeal to an Independent Appeal Panel.</p><p>For more information, please contact us using the details above.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=34"> Providing Information
		(34)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
