<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=705}]"><cms:name>education-3-705</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>School admissions - appeals</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=705}]"><cms:name>education-3-705-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>school, admissions, appeals</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=705}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>You may appeal for a place at any school to which you apply and for which you have been refused a place.</i></p><hr/><p>For voluntary aided schools in <span class="gen">enter council name</span>, the responsibility for appeal arrangements rests with the school, and you should contact them directly for details.</p><p>For community schools, the responsibility for appeals rests with <span class="gen">enter council name</span> Education Authority. If you want to appeal for a community school, you can ask your child's primary school headteacher or the <span class="gen">enter council name</span> Admissions Team for a form.</p><p>When completed, the appeal form should be returned to <span class="gen">enter address</span>
</p><p>Please note: appeals for first and second preferences must be 
  received by <span class="gen">enter date</span> Appeals for third and fourth preferences must be received by <span class="gen">enter date</span>
</p><p>Appeals are heard by an independent panel. A decision by an 
  appeal committee whether or not to offer a school place is binding on the admissions 
  authority. If your appeal for a <span class="gen">enter council name</span>
  community school is unsuccessful, you may not appeal for the same school within 
  one calendar year unless there has been a material change in your circumstances.</p><p>Acceptance of a place at a school does not affect your right 
  to appeal for a place at another school. However, if you decide to appeal for any 
  of your preferences, it is wise to secure a place for your child at an alternative 
  school in case your appeal is unsuccessful. This is because secondary transfer appeals 
  are normally heard during the second half of the summer term. By this time, there 
  will be very few alternative schools which still have vacancies. <span class="gen">enter council name</span> LEA is always willing to discuss alternative schools with vacancies at any stage in the process.</p><p>The acceptance of a place at an alternative school does not affect your right of appeal.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=705"> Providing Information
		(705)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
