<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=711}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--change-of-tenancy-711</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing Allocations - Change of Tenancy</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=711}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--change-of-tenancy-711-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, allocation, change, of, tenancy</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=711}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Your tenancy agreement is the document you sign when you agree to become the tenant of your home. </i></p><hr/><p>It is a contract between you and us and records information such as your name, the date you became our tenant and the rent. It also lists the other conditions you must keep to as a tenant. </p><p>There are a number of ways you can apply to have your tenancy agreement changed. </p><h2>Joint Tenancy </h2><p>You may want to share the responsibilities of your tenancy with someone who lives with you. In this case, you should apply to your housing office for a joint tenancy. We will process your application and tell you our decision within <span class="gen">enter amount</span> working days. </p><h2>Transferring your Tenancy </h2><p>If you are leaving to live somewhere else, you can apply to transfer your tenancy to your partner or a member of your family who has lived with you for at least a year. In this case, you should apply to your Housing Office to transfer your tenancy. We will process your application and tell you our decision within <span class="gen">enter amount</span> working days. </p><h2>Succession to Tenancy </h2><p>If you die, your partner or any adult permanently living in your home can take over your tenancy. This is what we call a 'succession to tenancy'. In this case, you can apply to the Housing Office and we will process the application within <span class="gen">enter amount</span> working days. </p><p>If the person who takes over your tenancy dies, no one living with them will have an automatic right to take over the tenancy in the same way. However, they can apply to have the tenancy transferred to them. Staff in the housing office will be able to give you more advice about this. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=711"> Providing Information
		(711)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
