<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=84}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--general-information-84</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing Allocations - General Information</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=84}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--general-information-84-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, allocations, general, information</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=84}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Housing Act 1996 requires the Council to keep a housing register from which offers of secure housing will be made. The Council is required to give &quot;reasonable preference&quot; when allocating housing to the following: </i></p><hr/><li title="*">People occupying unsanitary or overcrowded housing or otherwise living in unsatisfactory housing conditions.</li><li title="*">People occupying housing accommodation which his temporary or occupied on insecure terms.</li><li title="*">Families with dependent children. </li><li title="*">Households consisting of or including someone who is expecting a child. </li><li title="*">Households consisting of or including someone with a particular need for settled accommodation on medical or welfare grounds.</li><li title="*">Households whose social or economic circumstances are such that they have difficulty in securing settled accommodation.</li><li title="*">People to whom the local authority owe a duty under the following homelessness legislation:<br/>
-  Part VII Housing Act 1996 <br/>
- Part III Housing Act 1985</li><p>It also requires that additional preference be given to households within the definition at (e) consisting of someone with a particular need for settled accommodation on medical or welfare grounds, who cannot reasonably be expected to find settled accommodation for themselves in the foreseeable future. </p><h2>Who Can Apply? </h2><p>
				<strong>Connections with the Area</strong>
			</p><p>The Council's main responsibility is towards applicants who currently live or work in the area. Applicants living in the area will normally be offered accommodation before those who do not. Your application will also be considered if you work in the area, used to live in the area, or if you have close relatives who currently live here. If you do not have any connection with this area, you may still register but it is not likely that an offer of housing will be made, you may, however, be able to move to this area through the 
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=88">
<strong>Exchange Scheme</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 88</span>, or through the National Mobility Scheme. </p><p>
				<strong>Owner-occupiers </strong>
			</p><p>Owner-occupiers who wish to put their name on the housing register can do so but are advised to state very clearly why they feel they need Council housing. If you own your home you are only likely to be offered housing if you are faced with severe financial or medical difficulties, and cannot resolve your housing problem in any other way. </p><p>
				<strong>Age </strong>
			</p><p>People over 18 years may apply for Council accommodation. However, people between 16 and 18 years may be considered for Council accommodation, and we will normally ask that they have the agreement of a responsible adult or agency to act as a guarantor. </p><h2>
How is my Application Considered? </h2><p>When a vacancy arises in the area and of the type you need, the housing register is checked. The cases with the highest number of points including transfer cases (people who wish to move from one Council property to another) are then closely considered. We identify the case or cases in the most housing need using the points as a clear guide. </p><p>We will then consider other factors such as how long people have been in need of housing, the ages of children if there are any, how long a person has been a tenant if it is a transfer case, and what the likelihood is of another vacancy arising which would be more suitable. We will recommend an allocation and this will be recorded and checked by a Senior member of staff and the allocation will then be made. The successful person will be offered the property in writing. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=84"> Providing Information
		(84)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
