<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=87}]"><cms:name>housing-association--nomination-to-join-the-register-87</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing Association - Nomination to Join the Register</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=87}]"><cms:name>housing-association--nomination-to-join-the-register-87-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, association, nomination, to, join, the, register</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=87}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>To join the Housing Register, applicants must complete a housing application form. If you would like us to send you an application form please use the contact details above. </i></p><hr/><p>It is important to answer all the questions otherwise we may not be able to register your application and/or your points may not be correct. You must answer all questions honestly as if you deliberately give false or misleading information to gain housing, court action may be considered and this could lead to a fine and/or eviction. </p><p>Anyone over the age of 16 years or over may apply to join the register and it is not necessary to live or work in the area. </p><p>In broad terms those who are <strong>unable </strong> to join the register are: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">Owner/occupiers who have sufficient resources to enable them to secure suitable alternative accommodation.</li>
			<li title="*">Applicants with second homes.</li>
			<li title="*">Applicants who are subject to immigration control, unless they are a group specified by the Secretary of State as eligible for housing assistance. </li>
		</ul><p>The Council works closely with several Housing Associations to develop affordable housing for rent.</p><p>Some people on our Transfer List or Housing Register (waiting list) are offered a Housing Association property instead of a Council home. </p><p>Housing Associations are 'Registered Social Landlords' not private landlords. They provide housing in a very similar way to the Council and are non-profit making. They are run by Committees, who are unpaid, and managed by paid, professional housing officers. People who rent a Housing Association property must meet their rules and conditions of tenancy. The Housing Association will carry out most repairs. </p><p>Most Associations are registered with the 
		<a href="http://www.housingcorp.gov.uk/">Housing Corporation</a>	.<span class="gen">link to external website</span> The Housing Corporation is a 'Non Departmental Public Body', sponsored by the 
		<a href="http://www.odpm.gov.uk/">Office of the Deputy Prime Minister</a>	.<span class="gen">link to external website</span> Its role is to fund and regulate Registered Social Landlords (RSLs) in England. </p><p>Housing Associations offer &quot;assured tenancies&quot; which offer security similar to a Council tenancy. There is a special Tenants Charter which protects tenants' rights. </p><p>Housing Association rents tend to be higher than Council rents. But, many of their properties are a lot newer than Council properties. Also, the Government has recently announced that Council and RSL rents must be brought into line over the next 10 years. The rent is very reasonable compared to the cost of renting a similar home privately. People living on a low incomes may qualify for housing benefit. </p><p>In certain cases Housing Association tenants may be able to buy their home. All tenants have the right to buy if the property is part of a Housing Association Scheme built with Housing Corporation grant since April 1997. </p><h2>Can Tenants Transfer to a Council Property? </h2><p>Housing Association tenants can apply to their Association for a transfer, in the same way as Council tenants. After two years in the tenancy they can join the Council's Transfer List, if they have a housing need. They are dealt with in the same way as our own tenants. </p><p>The 'Public RSL Register' gives some basic information on Housing Associations (RSLs) currently registered with the Housing Corporation. The Register can be accessed directly from the link below: </p><p>
			
		<a href="http://www.housingcorp.gov.uk/resources/register/select.htm">www.housingcorp.gov.uk/resources/register/select.htm </a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=87"> Providing Information
		(87)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
