<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=88}]"><cms:name>mutual-council-home-exchange-88</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Mutual Council Home Exchange</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=88}]"><cms:name>mutual-council-home-exchange-88-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>mutual, council, home, exchange</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=88}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If you are a Council or a Housing Association tenant you normally have the right to a mutual exchange. This means you can swap your home with another tenant provided your landlord agrees. </i></p><hr/><p>There are lists in most Council and Housing Association offices of tenants wishing to move, either within the area or to other areas.  If you find someone whose home you would like and they have seen you home and agreed they would like yours, you should ask your landlord to approve the exchange.  It is very important that you do not move until you have your landlord's approval in writing and you have signed the Assignment documents. </p><p>Your landlord has <span class="gen">enter amount</span> weeks from the date your application is received to make a decision.  An exchange may be refused if one of the tenants is in rent arrears or under notice to leave.  An exchange may also be refused if the properties are too big or too small for the family intending to occupy, or if one of the properties is designated for elderly or disabled persons.  If your request is refused, you have the right to appeal against the decision. </p><p>With a mutual exchange you will be asked to accept the property in the condition it has been left by the last tenant.  The Council will carry out routine repairs in accordance with the Tenancy Agreement, but it will be your responsibility to repair any damage caused by the previous tenant.  </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=88"> Providing Information
		(88)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
