<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=89}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--allocation-points-89</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing Allocations - Allocation Points</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=89}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--allocation-points-89-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, allocation, points</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=89}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Council uses a point system as a guide when allocating housing and the points system reflects the sort of situations mentioned in the legislation. </i></p><hr/><p>The Council's first responsibility is to those who live in unsatisfactory housing within the area, and this means that people living in better conditions may have to wait a long time. Please remember that having your name on the housing register is not a guarantee that you will eventually be offered a house. </p><p>Once your application has been accepted on to our housing register, it is awarded a certain number of points to reflect the conditions in which you live. </p><p>Points are given for such factors as medical conditions, overcrowding and lack of modern facilities, as well as for length of time on the housing register. The total points score of each applicant is then used as a guide in allocating properties. </p><h2>Deferred Points</h2><p>There will be some situations where an applicant has enough points to be offered a secure tenancy but this may not occur because of the reasons shown below. In the first five of the cases mentioned below, the points will be deferred for a period of 12 months. </p><li title="*">Homeless applicants found to be intentionally homeless.</li><li title="*">Applicants refusing an offer of accommodation and that refusal being seen to be unreasonable including people who have been offered accommodation to discharge the Council's duty to them as homeless.</li><li title="*">Where advice has been given to an applicant to resolve their housing problem and this advice has not been acted upon. </li><li title="*">Where enquiries are being made into a homeless application. </li><li title="*">Applicants who put themselves in a worse position than needed in order to gain more points. </li><li title="*">Applicants with a former tenant or current debt to the Council would not normally be rehoused until the debt is cleared therefore points will be deferred until then. However, each case will be judged individually.</li><li title="*">Where advice has been given to an applicant to resolve their housing problem and this advice has not been acted upon.</li><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=89"> Providing Information
		(89)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
