<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=92}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--registering-for-a-council-property-92</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Housing Allocations - Registering for a Council Property</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=92}]"><cms:name>housing-allocations--registering-for-a-council-property-92-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>housing, allocations, registering, for, council, property</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=92}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Each Council has different criteria for entry to its register, but if you are eligible, you will be invited to complete an application form. </i></p><hr/><p>When we receive this back, we will acknowledge it and your needs will be assessed in accordance with the Council's points scheme. These points schemes vary from district to district, but details are readily available on request. 
    
</p><p>If you indicate you have special health or care needs, these will be assessed and taken into account in the priority given to your application. This may involve the Council liaising with Social Services to ensure that your specific needs are catered for, if at all possible. 
      
</p><p>Geographical areas vary in popularity and in the availability of the type of housing you may be seeking, but we will discuss your needs with you and advise you of the number of points your application has been given and we will endeavour to tell you approximately how long you will have to wait to be housed by the Council or Housing Association.
        
</p><p>Generally once your pointed application reaches the top of the list, you will be offered the next appropriate dwelling in your area of choice. You will have a specified number of days to decide whether you wish to accept the offer. If you refuse it, you may be offered further accommodation later, but policies vary from Council to Council. 
          </p><p>If you need special accommodation such as extra care, sheltered housing or supported housing, your needs will be assessed by both Housing and Social Services and, depending on the points awarded, you will be allocated a dwelling, in due course, by the Housing Authority. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=92"> Providing Information
		(92)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
