<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=828}]"><cms:name>tenders-828</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Tenders</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=828}]"><cms:name>tenders-828-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>tenders</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=828}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Revenues and Benefits/Finance</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The following is a list of contracts that are available for tender, or are coming up for tender. </i></p><hr/><h3>Current Opportunities</h3><p>Please note that, if the closing date for expressions of interest has passed, then no more applications can be considered.</p><table width="90%" cellpadding="5" class="centre" summary="Current Opportunities">
			<tr>
				<th>Contract Description</th>
				<th>Closing date for expressions of interest</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table><h3>Forthcoming Programme</h3><table width="90%" cellpadding="5" class="centre" summary="Forthcoming Programme">
			<tr>
				<th>Contract Description</th>
				<th>Closing date for expressions of interest</th>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
			<tr>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
				<td>
					<span class="gen">enter details here</span>
				</td>
			</tr>
		</table><p>Should your company decide to respond to an advertisement and express an interest in bidding for Council work, here are some brief tips which you should bear in mind. </p><h3>Background</h3><p>The Council usually run two types of tenders - open and restricted.</p><p>Under an open tender procedure all suppliers who respond to an advertisement are supplied with tender documentation which they can return as appropriate. This approach is usually followed when purchasing standard items such as goods.</p><p>The restricted procedure can best be described as a two stage approach in which the Council invites interested suppliers to undergo a pre-qualification assessment before inviting them to tender. The restricted route is normally used for non-standard or large service requirements where it would not be economic for all parties concerned, if too large a tender field was invited to bid for
  the work e.g. consultancy contracts.</p><p>The tender documents you will receive usually consist of the following:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Covering letter</li>
			<li title="*">Instructions to Tenderer - this document details important administrative procedures relating to the tender eg. dates and times, method of tender return, evaluation criteria to be used in the selection of the successful supplier, details of where tender queries should be directed.</li>
			<li title="*">Tender Questionnaire - this document covers basic financial and technical information about your company eg. accounts, insurance levels, etc.</li>
			<li title="*">Specification - this details the Council's requirements and must be read carefully and complied with.</li>
			<li title="*">Contract Conditions -  This  document gives details of the terms under which the Council wishes to do business. These should be read carefully, since it is our policy to contract only on its terms and conditions of contract.</li>
		</ul><h3>Tips</h3><p>Whichever procedure the Council follows, you should nevertheless read the advertisement carefully and submit or request the information required by the dates stipulated by the Council.</p><p> The Council normally requires all suppliers to complete a questionnaire detailing information about their financial/economic standing and their technical capability. This usually covers information about when your company was formed, what experience you have in providing the goods/services/works being tendered for, details of where the Council may obtain references on your company,
and details of your company's finances. To ensure your bid is considered, you must:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Provide all the information requested</li>
			<li title="*">Make sure that you answer all questions accurately</li>
			<li title="*">Return the information by the closing date specified</li>
		</ul><p>Sometimes the information the Council receives from suppliers is unclear or in need of further clarification. Once again you should provide any additional information sought by the closing date set.</p><p>The tender documents the Council sends out to suppliers contain details of our requirements. The documents, particularly the specification, should be read carefully and all information completed fully and accurately. If you do not understand any part of the specification you should ring the Council Officer named in the tender documentation and request further information. This must be done before the tender period closes.</p><h3>Equal Opportunities</h3><p>The Council is an equal opportunities employer and is committed to promoting equality of opportunity for all people irrespective of sex, age, race or disability. The Council is keen to ensure that its suppliers abide by the law and are working to best practice in this area. All suppliers, as part of the tender process, will thus be required to provide evidence that they have equal opportunities
policies in place and are committed to them.</p><h3>Environmental Policies</h3><p>The Council is committed to using the resources entrusted to it to ensure best value for money at the least possible cost to the environment. As part of this commitment to the environment, the Council&#x2019;s procurement policy will, wherever practicable, focus on.</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Specifying less environmentally damaging products.</li>
			<li title="*">Promoting greater use of renewable sources.</li>
			<li title="*">Encouraging suppliers to use environmentally friendly practices throughout the
    production process.</li>
		</ul><p>When applying for certain Council contracts, you may be requested to supply evidence of your practices and procedures as they relate to the environment.</p><h3>Health and Safety</h3><p>The Council is committed to ensuring the health, safety and welfare of its employees and that of all others affected by its undertakings. Contracts to supply goods or services will only be awarded to contractors who can satisfy the Council requirements in terms of resources required and their health and safety competence.</p><p>Successful contractors/suppliers are expected to demonstrate compliance with current health and safety legislation including: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">A commitment to the health and safety of its employees, clients and others</li>
			<li title="*">Up to date health and safety policies and procedures</li>
			<li title="*">Adequate risk assessment procedures</li>
			<li title="*">An adequate system of monitoring and reporting accidents, incidents and ill-health</li>
			<li title="*">Access to competent health and safety advice</li>
			<li title="*">Contracts are monitored to ensure compliance with contract standards and health and safety requirements.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=828"> Providing Information
		(828)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
