<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=68}]"><cms:name>backdating-claims-68</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Backdating Claims</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=68}]"><cms:name>backdating-claims-68-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>backdating, claims</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=68}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Revenues and Benefits/Finance</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>You can claim Housing Benefit for a past period - called backdating.</i></p><hr/><p>A claim can only be backdated for maximum of 52 weeks from the date of your claim for backdated benefit.</p><p>In order for a claim to be backdated we must be satisfied that:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">you have shown good cause for failing to claim earlier and</li>
			<li title="*">that good cause existed continuously during the period for which backdating is being requested</li>
		</ul><p>You will need to show continuous good cause for not claiming earlier and we must be satisfied that your circumstances, during this time were such that any reasonable person of your age and experience would also have failed to claim benefit.</p><p>You have to prove &quot;good cause&quot; but we must take account of all the facts of your case.</p><p>Some examples of when you may have &quot;good cause&quot; are:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">If you did not immediately claim benefit after leaving hospital</li>
			<li title="*">If you were ill and had no-one to make a claim on your behalf</li>
			<li title="*">If you did not understand that you could claim benefit perhaps because of age, inexperience or language difficulties.</li>
			<li title="*">If you have suffered a recent family bereavement.</li>
		</ul><h3>What happens when a backdated claim is made</h3><p>Your claim will be considered by a Benefits Officer. The more information and evidence you give in support of your claim the quicker a decision can be made.</p><p>Sometimes it may be necessary to write to you for more information or to ask you to come in for an informal interview. </p><p>Your claim will be looked at within <span class="gen">enter amount</span> days and you will be sent a letter telling you of our decision.</p><p>If we have decided that you have not shown &quot;good cause&quot; and that we cannot backdate your claim, the reasons for this will be explained in our letter.</p><p>You will then have the right of <strong>
				
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=72">appeal</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to pid 72</span> against our decision not to backdate your claim.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=68"> Providing Information
		(68)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
