<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=70}]"><cms:name>current-claim-70</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Current Claim</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=70}]"><cms:name>current-claim-70-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>current, claim</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=70}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Revenues and Benefits/Finance</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>If you currently receive Housing Benefit and there is a change in any of your personal circumstances, you must let us know as soon as possible.</i></p><hr/><p>You can use the 
			 <span class="gen">link to online form</span> in the first instance and we will send you the appropriate form(s) to fill in.</p><h4>Moving Address</h4><p>As a private tenant and the change in circumstance is due to a move of address then you should complete a new claim form. </p><p>If the entitlement relates to a Council Housing Benefit Claim then you should also complete a new claim form, unless you have more than 13 weeks outstanding on your current claim. You would find this information out by looking at your notification letters for your current address or on visiting one of our Information Points. If this is the case, you need only provide a signed statement showing the current address, the forwarding address and the date of the move and confirmation that you want the claim to continue.</p><p>If you have had other changes in your circumstances since last time you claimed then a new form should be completed. </p><h4> Income support/Job Seekers Allowance has stopped</h4><p>If Job Seekers Allowance (Income Based) or Income Support has ceased then a new claim form should be completed and returned as soon as possible.</p><p>You should also provide proof of your new income and any savings you may have.</p><h4>What happens if there are changes in my income or savings?</h4><p>If your savings and/or income has changed (not Income Support or Job Seekers Allowance) you should contact us, notify us either in writing or directly. We will require you to provide proof.</p><h4>What happens if there is a change in my rent?</h4><p>If private rent charges change then you should confirm the rent changes in writing. Proof of the new rent level will be required. </p><h4>What happens if there are changes to the people living with me?</h4><p>If you or your partner leave the household, then a new form should be completed by the person remaining in the home. It will be likely that your income will have changed and details and proof will be required. </p><p>If a non-dependant or a dependant leave the household, you need to contact us to let us know what date they left and their forwarding address.</p><p>This is also the case if a boarder, tenant, sub-tenant or carer leave.</p><p>The service may not be able to remove someone from an address without details of their forwarding address and if you are unable to provide a forwarding address you will have to provide an explanation.</p><p>We need to be informed of all changes in your circumstances as soon as possible. If you delay, you may lose benefit. </p><p>In all cases, except where people are claiming through the &quot;Job Centre plus&quot; It is your duty to notify us of circumstances. Where you claim through the &quot;Job Centre Plus&quot;, it is your responsibility to notify them.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=70"> Applications for services
		(70)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset><cms:links oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contentassets.RelatedLink:{id=70}]"><cms:targetType>internalLink</cms:targetType><cms:linkOrder>1</cms:linkOrder><cms:linkTitle>PDF Form</cms:linkTitle><cms:targetItem oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.FileStorageItem:{id=70}]"/></cms:links></cms:item>
