<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE use_case SYSTEM "use-case.dtd">
<use_case>
	<id category="PSRV" number="00810" />
	<title>Browsing Bookmarks within a Portal </title>
	<author name="Jim Parsons" email="jparsons@redhat.com" />
	<last_modified date="2001/11/21" />
	<status value="in_progress" />
	<description>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="option"></span>
This Use case is the Base Case for Bookmark functionality. General Bookmark
attributes and procedures are detailed here.
<p>
<br>
The Collaborative Portal bookmarking model has one important distinction from browser bookmarking: In CW, Bookmarks can be shared. In a Collaborative 
Portal, the bookmark portlet is available for reading and use in most cases, by all participants. The ability to create a bookmark and have it appear within the bookmark portlet for a particular portal, is controlled by write privelage on the bookmark portlet.</p>
<br>
<p>
A system user may have participant status in many different portals, including their own personal portal. When using a collaborative portal or an application associated with a collaborative portal, the bookmark portlet 
instanced by that portal only shows bookmarks associated with that portal.
When a user is at his or her own personal portal, the Bookmark portlet can be configured to show just personal bookmarks, or import bookmarks as read/use only from collaborative portals that include the user as a member.
</p>

		]]>
	</description>
	<goal_level value="user_goal" />
	<actors><actor name="Portal Participant" /></actors>
	<trigger value="A Portal participant is referred to a bookmark available  within a portal" />
	<preconditions>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>
This Use Case pre-supposes that the Bookmark portlet is present in the portal, and that it has at least one bookmark saved there.
</p>

		]]>
	</preconditions>
	<basic_path>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="required"></span><br>
<ol>
  <li>The portal participant chooses a bookmark entry from the bookmark portlet.</li>
  <li>The participant is taken to that content item.</li>
</ol>
</p>

		]]>
	</basic_path>
	<postconditions>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>
</p>

		]]>
	</postconditions>
	<success_end_conditions>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="required"></span>
The portal participant arrives at the desired content destination.
</p>

		]]>
	</success_end_conditions>
	<alternative_paths>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>

</p>

		]]>
	</alternative_paths>
	<exception_paths>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>

</p>

		]]>
	</exception_paths>
	<failure_end_conditions>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>

</p>

		]]>
	</failure_end_conditions>
	<sample_narrative>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span>
</p>

		]]>
	</sample_narrative>
	<open_issues>
		<![CDATA[
<p> <span class="optional"></span><br>
</p>




		]]>
	</open_issues>
<iteration>
Focused
</iteration>
</use_case>
