<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=172}]"><cms:name>batch-23-172</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Action plan orders</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=172}]"><cms:name>batch-23-172-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>action, plan, orders</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=172}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Action Plan Order was created by the 1998 Crime and Disorder Act as a way of dealing with young 
    people between the ages of 10 and 17, who have to be dealt with by the Youth Court.</i></p><hr/><p>It is a community sentence which is intended to offer an early opportunity for 
    work and/or support to help prevent further offending.  The Action Plan Order lasts for three months from the date of the Order being made. </p><p>The Action Plan Order aims to prevent re-offending by ensuring that the young person complies with 
    the requirements of an Action Plan, which will be designed to address the causes 
    of such behaviour by requiring the young person to complete any of a number of 
    specific tasks.</p><p>It aims to encourage the young person to take responsibility for their actions 
    and to consider the wishes and feelings of victims of crime. It will also consider 
    the need for 'reparation' (putting things right) to the victim(s).</p><p>Specific requirements of an Action Plan Order may include:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Participation in activities.</li>
			<li title="*">Attendance at offence focused work groups.</li>
			<li title="*">Attendance at an Attendance Centre.</li>
			<li title="*">Staying away from specified places.</li>
			<li title="*">Monitored school attendance.</li>
			<li title="*">Reparation, either to the victim of the offence or to the community as a whole.</li>
			<li title="*">Attendance at a review hearing at the Youth Court.</li>
		</ul><p>The Court can use a combination of any of the above elements 
  to create an Action Plan for any individual. It may also choose to impose a Parenting 
  Order on the parents of a young person subject to an Action Plan Order.</p><p>A Responsible Officer will be appointed from the Youth Offending 
  Team to supervise/co-ordinate the programme of work.</p><h2>
What will happen if the young person fails 
  to co-operate?</h2><p>At most, two warnings within the period of the Order may be 
  given before Breach Proceedings are taken.  
  Breach Proceedings will involve the young person being returned to Court. The Court 
  may discharge the Order and re-sentence for the original offence.</p><p>Breach Proceedings can be taken at any stage of the Order (regardless 
  of the length of time it has to run) and without prior warning if the failure to 
  comply is serious, such as an attempt to avoid its completion or serious misconduct. 
  </p><h2>
			
			What do Parents/Guardians have to do?</h2><p>Parents/Guardians should:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Attend Court with the young person.</li>
			<li title="*">Encourage the young person to appreciate fully the consequences of their offending 
    behaviour.</li>
			<li title="*">Ensure that the young person successfully completes the activities assigned 
    to him/her.</li>
			<li title="*">Co-operate with any Parenting Order that may be imposed. </li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=172"> Providing Information
		(172)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
