<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=173}]"><cms:name>batch-23-173</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Final warning</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=173}]"><cms:name>batch-23-173-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>final, warning</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=173}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Final Warning was created by the 1998 Crime and Disorder 
  Act as a way of dealing with offences committed by young people aged 10 to 17, 
  provided that the offence is not so serious that it needs to go to court.</i></p><hr/><p>It was introduced in an effort to encourage young people to 
  take responsibility for their criminal actions and to keep them from committing 
  further offences and it replaced the old system of police cautions for young people. 
  </p><p>A young person arrested for a further offence within two years 
  will virtually always go to court. </p><p>The Final Warning:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">aims to prevent re-offending by ensuring that the young person is made aware 
    of the consequences and impact of criminal activity.</li>
  <li title="*">aims to take into account the wishes and feelings of victims of crime.</li>
  <li title="*">aims to find out the reason for the offence, and do something about the things 
    in the young person's life, which create a risk of further offending.</li>
</ul><p>Youth Offending Teams have been set up in every local authority 
  to work with the Police Officers on Final Warnings to ensure that these aims are 
  met and to prevent offending by children and young people.</p><p>The Final warning is given on the understanding that the Youth 
  Offending Team will work with the young offender and their parent/guardian to 
  complete a short programme of intervention.</p><p>This will begin with an appointment for the young person and 
  parent/guardian to see someone from the Youth Offending Team. This might be at 
  the YOT office, the family home or at a central location. This appointment will 
  either be made at the Police station immediately after the Final Warning has been 
  given, or the Youth Offending Team will contact the family within <span class="gen">enter amount</span> working days 
  of the Warning being given.</p><p>It is very important that this appointment is kept! If a problem 
  should arise to prevent you from keeping the appointment, please contact the YOT 
  to re-arrange it.</p><h2>What the programme of work might involve</h2><p>
<strong>Work on offending:</strong> Brief sessions of Offence and Victim 
  focused work will be carried out at the YOT office by a member of the team. This 
  is to ensure that the young person fully understands the purpose of the Final Warning.</p><p>
<strong>Reparation</strong>: may involve the offender meeting his/her 
  victim in person to make a verbal apology. Alternatively, the young person may be 
  required to write a letter of apology and/or take part in several hours of practical 
  activity, which benefit the victims of crime, or the community as a whole.</p><h2>What do parents/guardians have to do?</h2><p>Parents/Guardians should:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Attend all meetings with the young person.</li>
  <li title="*">Encourage the young person to appreciate fully the consequences 
    of their offending behaviour.</li>
  <li title="*">Ensure that the young person successfully completes the activities 
    assigned to him/her.</li>
</ul><p>For further information on the Final Warning Scheme please contact us using the details above.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=173"> Providing Information
		(173)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
