<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=835}]"><cms:name>batch-23-835</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Probation orders</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=835}]"><cms:name>batch-23-835-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>probation, orders</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=835}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A Community Rehabilitation Order was previously a Probation Order and it is a Court Order, which is made to help you to avoid further offending. It can last up to three years. </i></p><hr/><p>This Order is supervised by a Youth Offending Team worker who is there to advise, assist and encourage you, and to help to prevent you re-offending. It means that you will be given:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Help in keeping out of further trouble with the Police</li>
  <li title="*">Advice in areas in which you may be having problems, e.g. at home, school/college or work, or with other people or with drugs</li>
  <li title="*">Support from your Youth Offending Team worker who is there to see you regularly and listen to what you have to say </li>
</ul><p>A detailed plan for what is going to be done during your Order will be agreed with you and your parents/carers within the first week. This is called a Supervision Plan. The Plan will be reviewed every three months. </p><h2>What part do I play in the Order? </h2><p>Under a Community Rehabilitation Order you will have to:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Keep your appointments with your Youth Offending Team worker which will be once a week for the first three months. These appointments will usually be at the Youth Offending Team Office or at your home</li>
  <li title="*">Work with them to look at why you offend and ways in which you can change your behaviour</li>
  <li title="*">Carry out any other things you have agreed to do</li>
  <li title="*">Act responsibly whilst on supervision in your community and when attending for appointments</li>
  <li title="*">Keep to any additional requirements that have been agreed in your Supervision Plan </li>
</ul><p>Other conditions may be attached to your Order. These will be explained to you separately by your YOT worker </p><h2>Who will know I am on this Order? </h2><p>Under the Community Rehabilitation Order there will be times when your Youth Offending Team worker will visit you at home and discuss your progress with your parents/carers. </p><p>It may also be helpful to talk to your school, youth club, or employer. You will be asked what you think about this before it happens. </p><h2>What can go wrong? </h2><p>If you do not co-operate with your Youth Offending Team worker you will be taken back to Court for being in breach of the Community Rehabilitation Order.</p><p>If the breach is proved, the Court may then deal with you in some other way, such as:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">Giving you another chance under supervision on the Order</li>
  <li title="*">Making an Attendance Centre Order</li>
  <li title="*">Imposing a fine wither on you or your parents (depending on your age)</li>
  <li title="*">Re-sentence you for the original offence </li>
</ul><h2>What if I do well? </h2><p>When this happens, your Youth Offending Team worker will contact the Court and ask for the Order to be ended early. This cannot happen until at least half of the Community Rehabilitation Order has been successfully completed. </p><p>To do this, you will go back to Court with a report from your Youth Offending Team worker saying how well you have done. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=835"> Providing Information
		(835)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
