<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=796}]"><cms:name>explosives-licence-796</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Explosives Licence</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=796}]"><cms:name>explosives-licence-796-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>explosives, licence</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=796}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Explosives Act 1875 permits the storage of a limited quantity of fireworks/ explosives (5kg) for an unlimited period of time, or the storage of an unlimited quantity of fireworks for up to 14 days prior to their use. </i></p><hr/><p>It is generally
    taken that these provisions apply to 'private use', ie for use by the keeper
    or associates (eg. for a school bonfire) but not for sale. It also applies
    where local operators are storing fireworks prior to them firing a professional
  display.</p><p>Where a greater quantity of explosives is being stored, the premises needs
    to be registered with their local authority.
  </p><p>The Council registers premises
      (mainly retailers) for the keeping of fireworks, safety cartridges and/or
      mixed explosives. Registration
    runs annually from 1st April.
  </p><p>Different parts of
explosives/firework law are enforced by various bodies:</p><ul>
<li title="*">The
    Department of Trade and Industry</li>
<li title="*">The Fire
    Brigade</li>
<li title="*">The Health
    and Safety Executive (or their agents)</li>
<li title="*">Local
    Authority Trading Standards Departments</li>
<li title="*">The
    Police</li>
</ul><h2>Registration</h2><p>  The premises must be registered with the Council in the name of the
    occupier, either for 'Gunpowder' or 'Mixed Explosives', and the registration
    must be renewed annually.</p><h2>Storage of Explosives</h2><p>  Where the premises registered for the keeping of explosives is a shop
              or other similar dwelling, the explosives shall be kept in Mode
              B ie. in a substantial
      receptacle, closed and secured so as to prevent access to unauthorised
              persons. This container must be exclusively appropriated to keeping
              explosives. The
      maximum quantity to be kept on such premises must not be more than 25kg.
              Please contact your local Trading Standards Department for further
              information. </p><h2>Storage of Fireworks</h2><p> Generally, storage
      of fireworks for retail sale would be in a Mode B store, for which the
      following applies:</p><ul>
      <li title="*">The
          maximum amount of fireworks that can be kept in a room where the public
          might go is 50kg. You can keep fireworks in glass showcases, metal
          containers, wooden boxes, cupboards or drawers, but these must be locked
          shut or positioned so that no unauthorised person can reach them. You
    must not put glass showcases containing fireworks in your shop window.</li>
<li title="*">A
          quantity of fireworks over that 50kg limit (up to a further 200kg)
          can be stored elsewhere in the building, but must be kept in closed
    metal containers. Each container must hold not more than 50kg.</li>
<li title="*">Any
          container being used for storing fireworks must not contain other items.
          You must keep anything flammable (or likely to cause a fire or explosion)
    a safe distance away from any fireworks.</li>
</ul><h2>Modes</h2><p> There are two 'Modes'
      (sets of rules) for keeping fireworks for sale at registered premises:  </p><ul>
      <li title="*">
<strong>Mode
            A</strong> - requires a safe and secure building or room, not attached
            to a dwelling and used only for storing fireworks, up to a maximum
            weight of 1000kg. Please contact your local Trading Standards for
    further information if you wish to apply for a Mode A store.</li>
<li title="*">
<strong>Mode
            B</strong> - allows the storage of up to 250kg of fireworks in a building
            which is also used for other purposes (such as a shop), with strict
    regulations about how the fireworks are contained.</li>
</ul><h2>Exposure of Fireworks
  for Sale</h2><p>  All due precautions must be taken to prevent accidents by fire or explosion.
      Fireworks must not be kept dangerously near to oils, paints, matches or any
      other article of a highly inflammable or explosive nature, and must not be
      kept in shop windows or on open shelves and counters. Empty boxes and dummy
    fireworks can be used for show purposes.</p><h2>Sale to Children</h2><p>  It is illegal to sell fireworks to any person apparently under the age
    of eighteen years. </p><h2>Accidents</h2><p>  Whenever an accident occurs by explosion or fire in registered premises,
          causing loss of life or personal injury, the occupier of the premises must
          notify the
  Health and Safety Executive. You can visit their website at: 
		<a href="http://www.hse.gov.uk">
<strong>www.hse.gov.uk</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
</p><h2>Inspection of Registered
  Premises</h2><p>  The occupier of registered premises must allow any authorised officer of the
    Council to inspect the place and receptacles where explosives are kept.</p><h2>Useful Links</h2><p>Health and Safety
      Executive (HSE) Website: 
		<a href="http://www.hse.gov.uk">
<strong>www.hse.gov.uk</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
</p><p>Department of Trade and Industry (DTi) Website: 
		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/homesafetynetwork/fw_intro.htm">
<strong>www.dti.gov.uk</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>  </p><p>UK Firework Safety Website: 
		<a href="http://www.fireworksafety.co.uk">
<strong>www.fireworksafety.co.uk</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
</p><p>Explosive Industry Group: 
		<a href="http://www.eig.org.uk">
<strong>www.eig.org.uk</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
   </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=796"> Providing Information
		(796)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
