<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=797}]"><cms:name>entertainments-licensing-797</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Entertainments Licensing</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=797}]"><cms:name>entertainments-licensing-797-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>entertainments, licensing</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=797}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A Public Entertainment Licence is issued by the Local Authority for all buildings at which entertainment is provided to the public. </i></p><hr/><p>A Licence is issued either for
      one or more occasions (an Occasional Licence) or for a period
    of one year (an Annual Licence).
    The main purpose of licensing entertainments is to enable the Local Authority
      to ensure the health, safety and welfare of members of the public.
    </p><p>Licences are, therefore, only
      granted when the premises (or site), and ancillary arrangements, meet the
      standards required by the Police,
        the Fire Service, and the relevant Council Service. 
   </p><p>The
    Fire Service are responsible for advising the Council as to whether the
    fire
      safety arrangements
      for
  a building are satisfactory for the intended use. </p><p>When you apply for a new
    annual licence, a copy of your application will be sent to the Fire Safety
    Officer (FSO). The FSO will normally contact you within
    14 days to make an appointment to inspect the building. During the inspection,
    the FSO will discuss the intended uses and the maximum number of people expected
    to use the building/site at any one time. Following the inspection, you will
    be advised whether the existing fire precautions are considered to be satisfactory
    and, if not, what can be done to improve the situation. Advice will also
    be given on what to do if a fire occurs and calling the Fire Service. The
    FSO
  will then send a written report to the Council. </p><p>If you are applying to renew an annual licence, the FSO will check the application
    form to see whether there has been any change in circumstances since a licence
    was last issued. If so, you will normally be contacted within 14 days to discuss
    what changes have been made and whether a further inspection is necessary.
    The FSO may need to visit even if no changes have been made although this will
    depend on how long it has been since the last visit. Should a further inspection
  be necessary, the FSO will, of course, make an appointment. </p><p>Although your contact with the Fire Service will normally be when an inspection
      is made, please remember that the FSO will be pleased to deal with your queries
    on fire safety matters at any time.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=797"> Providing Information
		(797)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
