<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=800}]"><cms:name>arson-reduction-800</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Arson Reduction</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=800}]"><cms:name>arson-reduction-800-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>arson, reduction</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=800}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Deliberately started fires are a serious threat to business premises of all kinds. It is a problem that effects all sections of the population and is not confined only to urban areas. </i></p><hr/><p>Arson in the countryside, be it an isolated rural farm or
    a business in the local market town, can be devastating especially when you
    take into account the distances fire appliances may have to travel to reach
    the scene
    of the fire and the possibility of delayed calls to the fire service due
    to the remote nature of the fire. </p><p>When the public hears the
      word &quot;arson&quot; it
      often conjures up the idea of revenge, fraud, financial gain or ideology
      but by far the biggest threat
    comes from vandalism. Those involved are generally children or adolescents
    who set fire to combustible material left easily accessible to them for no
    reason other than a mindless urge to be destructive.
</p><p> UK fire statistics indicate that of some 4000 fires each year in retail and
      distribution premises around 35% are malicious. There are many more small fires
      dealt with by staff that are mistakenly not reported to the Fire Service. A
      substantial number of these fires are deliberate.
</p><h2>Assessing the Risk</h2><p>By carrying out a risk assessment, addressing the vulnerable areas and adopting
  some simple measures, it is possible to substantially reduce the risk. Many
  risk reduction procedures involve little or no cost but are simply part of
  good management practice and will, of course, be welcomed by insurers. Set
  out below are some of the precautions that can be taken to protect your business.</p><h2>Reducing the Risk</h2><p>The
      majority of deliberate fires in commercial and industrial premises are started
in waste material left easily accessible to the arsonist.</p><ul>
<li title="*">Waste material should
        not be allowed to accumulate anywhere on the premises, in yards or loading
    areas or at perimeter fences.</li>
<li title="*">Any waste should
        be stored in metal containers with lockable lids and should be located
    in areas inaccessible to vandals or arsonists ideally in a secure area.</li>
<li title="*">Skips should be emptied
        regularly and should be sited at a safe distance, ideally 8 metres from
        any building or at least far enough away so that any fire that is started
        in the skip can not
spread to that building. </li>
<li title="*">Never leave pallets,
        plastic crates or trays in open yards adjacent to the premises, vandals
    and arsonists frequently use them to start fires.</li>
</ul><p>At closedown it is essential
for a responsible person to check:</p><ul>
<li title="*">External
    doors are locked</li>
<li title="*">Internal doors closed</li>
<li title="*">Windows closed and
    locked</li>
<li title="*">No unauthorised persons
    left on the premises</li>
<li title="*">No accumulation of
    waste or rubbish</li>
<li title="*">Alarms switched on </li>
<li title="*">Lights switched on
    as required</li>
</ul><p>It is essential that when considering security and locking of doors and windows
  that any fire legislation applicable to the premises in respect to means of
  escape is not compromised. If you are in any doubt, contact your local fire
  safety officer who will be pleased to advise you.</p><p>We have attached a series of risk assessment sheets and check lists to assist
  you in carrying out a risk assessment of your premises and maintaining a high
  level of fire safety awareness. These are very simple to use and should only
  take a few minutes of your time but could help to prevent the devastating consequences
  of a fire.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=800"> Providing Information
		(800)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
