<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=801}]"><cms:name>automatic-fire-alarms-801</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Automatic Fire Alarms</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=801}]"><cms:name>automatic-fire-alarms-801-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>automatic, fire, alarms</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=801}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The safety of your building and its occupants can be greatly enhanced by the installation of an Automatic Fire Detection and Alarm System. </i></p><hr/><p>Properly used and
    maintained, the automatic system with its fast response to incipient fire
    can be a significant factor in reducing the risk to life and the limiting
    of damage
    to your property in the event of a fire. </p><p>Unfortunately, the very features
that provide this fast response can also produce unwanted signals arising from
activities other than a real fire. These
  can prove both costly to the Fire Service, by initiating unnecessary turnouts
  of fire appliances and to the building operator where evacuation of a building
  as a result of a false alarm signal can result in loss of production and general
  disruption of normal business activities.</p><h2>General Rules</h2><p>Many unwanted fire signals are the result of ignorance on the part of
  employees or contractors who may not be aware that an automatic fire system
is in operation.</p><p>A few simple rules coupled with normal good house-keeping practices can
help to keep these unwanted nuisance signals to a minimum.</p><p>
<strong>Rule 1 - Staff
      or contractors to be made aware that the building is protected by an automatic
      detection
      system.</strong>
</p><ul>
      <li title="*">Display
          permanent notices at the entrances to all areas equipped with automatic
          fire detection, notice to read: <br/>
<br/>
         &quot;This area is
          protected by automatic fire detectors. Before undertaking any work
          involving heat, smoke, flame or sparks, please obtain clearance to
          proceed from the Plant Manager or Security Officer&quot;<br/>
<br/>
     Location .......................................................................................................................... </li>
      </ul><p>
<strong>Rule 2 - Staff
      or visiting contractors to be instructed that no activity, generating heat,
      smoke,
      flame or sparks
    is to be carried without prior authorisation from the Fire Safety Officer
or other responsible member of the managerial staff.</strong> </p><ul>
<li title="*">Incorporate
          instruction in staff contracts and operating manuals.</li>
          <li title="*">Contracts for subcontractors
        to include clause requiring them to acknowledge in writing, their responsibility
    for ensuring that their on-site staff follow the rules.</li>
</ul><p>
<strong>Rule 3 - No renovation
      work involving the generation of dust or paint spray to be carried out
      in any area protected
    by automatic smoke detectors, unless proper precautions have been taken to
protect the automatic fire detectors against the entry of dust.</strong>
</p><ul>
<li title="*">Transfer
          contractual liability to subcontractor as for Rule 2. Establish a named
          person in your own organisation to be responsible for engaging qualified
          persons to remove smoke detectors and replace with heat detectors when
          necessary. If removal is not possible arrange for detectors to be covered
          whilst dust raising work is carried out.</li>
          <li title="*">
<strong>Warning:</strong> 
      The operation of detectors covered with plastic or paper covers will be impaired, if not disabled, by this action.  Alternative manual surveillance must be instituted whilst the system is so disabled.</li>
<li title="*">A named, senior member
        of the occupiers staff should be made responsible for ensuring that the
        covers are removed and the system reinstated, as soon as all residual
    dust has been removed.</li>
    <li title="*">An operational test
        of the system by a qualified person is bly recommended, following
    any redecorating or building work in a protected area.</li>
</ul><h2>General  </h2><p>Compliance with these simple
    rules will help to release the Fire Service for more essential duties, they
    may also help to save you from the permanent
  loss of business so frequently associated with a major fire.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=801"> Providing Information
		(801)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
