<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=806}]"><cms:name>fire-certificates--offices-806</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Fire Certificates - Offices</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=806}]"><cms:name>fire-certificates--offices-806-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>fire, certificates, offices</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=806}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Virtually all places of work will fall within the scope of Fire Safety Legislation. Namely, these are The Fire Precautions (Workplace Regulations) 1997 (as Amended) or The Fire Precautions Act 1971. </i></p><hr/><p>Basically, larger premises
    will be covered by the Fire Precautions Act and the 'Workplace Regulations'. In the case of smaller premises, they
  have to comply with the requirements of the 'Workplace Regulations'</p><p>The Criteria is detailed
  below.</p><h2>  Who should apply?</h2><p>An
            Application for a fire certificate is required under the Fire Precautions
            Act 1971 as amended by the Fire Safety and Safety at Places of Sport
            Act 1987 in respect of any premises which are put to a use designated
            by Order made by the Secretary of State under section 1 of the Act.
            Orders have so far been made relating to hotels and boarding houses,
      factories, offices, shops and railway premises.</p><h2>Factories, Offices, Shops and Railway Premises  </h2><p>An
              application for a fire certificate is required for any premises used
      as factory, office, shop or railway premises in which:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">more than 20 persons are at work at any one time; or</li>
			<li title="*">more than 10 persons are at work elsewhere than on the ground floor.</li>
		</ul><p>  Additionally a fire certificate is required if a building contains 2
          or more premises of this kind and the aggregate of persons at work in
          all these premises
        in the building exceeds 20 or the aggregate number at work elsewhere than
          on the ground floor in these premises exceeds 10.</p><h2>Definition of Factory, Office, Shop and Railway Premises  </h2><p>The Designation Order defines these premises as places where people are
            employed to work by reference to the definitions contained in the
            Factories Act 1961 and the Offices, Shops and Railway Premises Act
            1963, subject to the addition in the former of electrical stations
            and institutions and the exclusion in the latter of premises consisting
            of a covered market place where a market is held by virtue of a grant
            from the Crown or of prescription or under statutory authority wherein
            shop premises are aggregated. Railway premises (including structures)
            to which regulations made under section 12 of the Fire Precautions
            Act 1971 apply are also excluded. If you are uncertain where your
            premises come within the definitions you should consult the fire
      authority for your area.</p><h2>Where do I send the application for a Fire Certificate to?                </h2><p>If
            your premises need a fire certificate, the application form should
      be completed and sent to:</p><p>
			<span class="gen">enter address</span>
		</p><h2>Who should complete the Application Form  </h2><p>The
            occupier of premises should complete the application form and send
            it to the fire authority (or in the case of Crown owned or occupied
            premises, to HM Inspector of Fire Services). If, however, the premises
            are factory, office, shop or railway premises and are held under
            a lease and consist of part of a building, all parts of which are
            in the same ownership, or consist of part of a building in which
            different parts are owned by different people, the Fire Precautions
            Act 1971, as modified, makes the owner(s) of the building responsible
            if the premises are used without a fire certificate being in force.
            Thus in such cases application should be made on behalf of the owner(s)
            of the building and the occupier(s) must supply information as appropriate
            to the owner(s). The occupiers of such premises are advised to check
            that a fire certificate is in force or that an application has been
      made for one.</p><p>
			
			
			<span class="gen">link to online form</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=806"> Applications for services
		(806)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset><cms:links oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contentassets.RelatedLink:{id=806}]"><cms:targetType>internalLink</cms:targetType><cms:linkOrder>1</cms:linkOrder><cms:linkTitle>PDF Form</cms:linkTitle><cms:targetItem oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.FileStorageItem:{id=806}]"/></cms:links></cms:item>
