<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=811}]"><cms:name>health-and-safety--construction-regulations-811</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Health and Safety - Construction Regulations</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=811}]"><cms:name>health-and-safety--construction-regulations-811-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>health, safety, construction, regulations</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=811}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Building Regulations are legal requirements aimed at achieving adequate standards for the construction of domestic, commercial and industrial buildings. They are laid down by Parliament and are supported by separate documents containing practical and technical guidance on compliance, which are known as 'Approved Documents'. These are produced in different parts.</i></p><hr/><p>Building Regulations have three purposes:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">To ensure the health
    and safety of people in and around buildings.</li>
			<li title="*">The conservation of
    energy.</li>
			<li title="*">Access and facilities
    for disabled people.</li>
		</ul><h2>  What are the Building Regulations? A summary of the 'Approved Documents'</h2><p>The
    Approved Documents that run from Part A to Part N reproduce the legal requirements
    and give practical and technical guidance on how to meet them.</p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part A - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-a">Structural Safety</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part B - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-b">Fire Safety</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part C - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-c">Site Preparation and Damp	Proofing</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part D - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-d">Toxic Substances</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part E - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-e">Soundproofing</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part F - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-f">Ventilation</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part G - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-g">Hygiene</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part H - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-h">Drainage and Waste Disposal</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part J - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-j">Heating Appliances</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part K - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-k">Stairs, Ramps and Guards</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part L - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-l">Conservation of Fuel and Power</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part M - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-m">Access and Facilities for People with Disabilities</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Part N - </strong>
				
		<a href="#part-n">Glazing Materials and Protection</a>	
			</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part
      A - Structural Safety</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">The
                weight of the building from the walls, furniture and people in
                the building will be transmitted to the ground, so as not to
          cause instability to the building or other buildings.</li>
			<li title="*">Requires buildings
              to be built in a way ensuring no collapse will occur disproportionate
          to its cause.</li>
			<li title="*">Ground movement
                such as freezing of subsoil will not impair the stability of
          the building.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part B
	      - Fire Safety </h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Requires
          safe means of escape from the building.</li>
			<li title="*">Requires
                the stability of a building to be maintained in a fire, both
          internally and externally.</li>
			<li title="*">Internally
                - The wall lining i.e. plaster, plasterboard or wooden boards
                on the walls and ceiling will resist the spread of flames and
          give off reasonable levels of heat, if on fire.</li>
			<li title="*">Internal
                stability will be maintained during fire and fire spread will
          be prohibited.</li>
			<li title="*">Fire and smoke
              will be prohibited from spreading to concealed spaces in a buildings
          structure.</li>
			<li title="*">Externally -
              The external walls and roof will resist spread of fire to walls
          and roofs of other buildings.</li>
			<li title="*">The building
          will be easily accessible for fire fighters and their equipment.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part
	      C - Site Preparation and Damp Proofing</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Nothing
          should be growing on the ground covered by the building.</li>
			<li title="*">Precautions
              must be taken to stop gases and dangerous substances from previous
              land use from entering the building and endangering the health
          and safety of occupants.</li>
			<li title="*">Subsoil drainage
                will be in place, if needed, to stop the passage of ground moisture
                to the interior of the building and to prevent damage to the
          fabric of the building.</li>
			<li title="*">The walls,
                floors and roof of the building shall prevent moisture passing
          to the inside of the building.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part D
	      - Toxic Substances</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Insulating
                materials inserted into cavity walls can give off fumes. Prevention
          must be taken to stop these fumes reaching occupants of the building. </li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part E
	      - Soundproofing</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Floors and
                    walls between domestic buildings should have a certain resistance
          to the passage of sound. </li>
			<li title="*">Sound insulation requirements also apply to floors and certain walls within individual
    dwellings and new schools.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part F
	        - Ventilation
      </h2><ul>
			<li title="*">The
              building must have adequate ventilation and provision to prevent
          condensation occurring in the roof structure.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part G
	      - Hygiene</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Adequate
          sanitation facilities ie. toilet.</li>
			<li title="*">A house must
          have either a bath or shower with ability to heat hot water.</li>
			<li title="*">Unvented
                hot water storage systems - Restrictions apply to who can install
          the system.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part
          H - Drainage and Waste Disposal</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">An
                adequate system to carry water used for cooking, washing, toilet,
                bath or shower to a sewer cesspool or settlement tank must be
          in place.</li>
			<li title="*">A cesspool
                or settlement tank must be impermeable to liquids and have adequate
                ventilation. It must also have means of access for emptying,
                not harm the health of any person and not contaminate water or
          water supply.</li>
			<li title="*">An adequate
                system to carry rainwater away from the roof of a building eg.
          guttering carrying water to a sewer.</li>
			<li title="*">A place to put
              a wheelie bin or dustbin. The place must not harm anyone's
          health.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part J
	      - Heating Appliances</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Must
                have an adequate air supply for combustion and for efficient
          working of a fluepipe or chimney.</li>
			<li title="*">Appliances shall
          discharge the products of combustion to the outside.</li>
			<li title="*">The appliance,
                      fireplace and chimney shall reduce the risk of the building
          catching fire.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part K
	      - Stairs, Ramps and Guards</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Stairs,
                ramps and ladders shall provide safety for people, when moving
          between different levels of a building.</li>
			<li title="*">Stairs, ramps,
          floors and balconies shall be adequately guarded.</li>
			<li title="*">Safety shall
          be provided for people using vehicle ramps and loading bays.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part
	          L - Conservation of Fuel and Power </h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Provision
          must be made for the conservation of fuel and power in a building.</li>
			<li title="*">The fabric of
          the building must limit heat loss.</li>
			<li title="*">Controls
          to operate the heating of the building and heating of water.</li>
			<li title="*">By limiting
          heat loss from hot water tanks and hot water pipes.</li>
			<li title="*">Lighting
                      systems in buildings should use no more energy than needed
          and have adequate controls.</li>
			<li title="*"/>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part
	              M - Access and Facilities for People with Disabilities </h2><p>In Part M, &quot;people
	            with disabilities&quot; means people who have an impairment which
	            limits their ability to walk or which requires them to use a
	            wheelchair for mobility or have impaired hearing or sight.</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Reasonable
                    provision shall be made for people with disabilities at entrances
          to and within new dwellings and buildings.</li>
		</ul><p>An existing building should have reasonable provision:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">For people
          with disabilities to gain access and use the building.</li>
			<li title="*">If toilets
                are provided, reasonable provision shall be made available for
          people with disabilities.</li>
			<li title="*">If a building
              has seating such as audience or spectator seating, reasonable provision
          should be made for people with disabilities.</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			Part N
	      - Glazing Materials and Protection</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Glazing
                that people come into contact with whilst in a building, should,
                if broken, break in a way unlikely to cause injury, resist impact
          without breaking or be shielded or protected from impact.</li>
			<li title="*">Buildings,
                other than dwellings that have transparent glazing which people
                come into contact with while moving around a building, must have
                features to make it apparent. Windows that can be opened must
          be operated safely and provision made for safe accessible cleaning.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=811"> Providing Information
		(811)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
