<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=813}]"><cms:name>workplace-regulations-813</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Fire Safety - Workplace Regulations</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=813}]"><cms:name>workplace-regulations-813-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>fire, safety, workplace, regulations</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=813}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Workplace Fire Precautions Legislation brings together existing Health and Safety and Fire Legislation to form a set of dedicated Fire Regulations with the objective:</i></p><hr/><p>

			<strong>To Achieve a Risk Appropriate Standard of Fire Safety for Persons in the Workplace</strong>

		</p><p>These Regulations were

    amended on the 1st December 1999 in order to confirm the concept of the employer<strong> </strong>

    having unconditional responsibility for the safety of employees. As a result

    most

    workplaces are now subject to the legal requirements

    of the above Regulations. The Regulations apply to workplaces where persons

    are employed  to

    work, but do not apply in workplaces that

  are:

  </p><ul>

			<li title="*">Private Dwellings</li>

			<li title="*">Used only by the self

    employed</li>

			<li title="*">Construction Sites</li>

			<li title="*">Means of Transport</li>

			<li title="*">Mineshafts</li>

			<li title="*">Ships within the meaning

        of the Merchant Shipping Act (not those permanently moored, under construction

    or repair etc)</li>

			<li title="*">Offshore installations

    or open farm/forestry land</li>

		</ul><p>This means that those workplaces

    that are subject to the requirements of a Fire Certificate (or Application)

    have additional legal obligations in

    respect

  of the Workplace Regulations. An existing Fire Certificate may form the basis

  of the fire risk assessment (it is not a substitute for a Fire Risk Assessment),

    supplemented as required by

    attaching

    the risk

    assessment

    findings

    to reduce

duplication of work.</p><p>The Fire Precautions Workplace Legislation requires employers to:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">Carry out a Fire Risk

        Assessment</li>

			<li title="*">Provide and maintain,

        to the extent that it is appropriate, determined by the Risk Assessment:<br/>

        - Means for Detecting and Giving Warning in Case of Fire<br/>

        - Means of Escape

              and Emergency Lighting<br/>

        -  Fire Safety Signs<br/>

        -  Firefighting Equipment<br/>

			</li>

			<li title="*">Monitor and review the Risk Assessment and revise as appropriate</li>

			<li title="*">Inform staff of their representatives of the risk</li>

			<li title="*">Plan for an emergency</li>

			<li title="*">Provide staff information and training</li>

			<li title="*">Nominate persons to assist</li>

		</ul><h2>Where the Employers do

not have Control of all Parts of the Building</h2><p>If the

      workplace

      is

      shared

      with other persons, they should be informed of any

    significant risks identified. The person who has to any extent control (landlord,

    owner or other employer etc) has a responsibility to make sure the Regulations

    are complied with, in the parts they control. This may require communication

    and co-operation between all parties to ensure co-ordination of fire safety

  provisions, firefighting measures, evacuation procedures etc.</p><h2>Objective of the Fire Risk

    Assessment </h2><p>The principle of the Regulations

    and the risk assessment approach, is goal based and flexible to employers

    needs. The employer generates the risk in workplaces,

  therefore, to safeguard the safety of employees, the employer must:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">Identify hazards and

        people at risk</li>

			<li title="*">Remove or reduce the

        hazards</li>

			<li title="*">Manage the remaining

        risks to acceptable levels by:<br/>

        - Ensuring that all

              occupants are alerted and can leave the premises safely in the event

              of fire<br/>

           - Reducing the probability

              of a fire starting<br/>

        - Limiting the effects

        should a fire occu

     </li>

		</ul><p>Providing the premises

    have been built and maintained in accordance with Building Regulations and

    the use

    of the workplace is normal risk or lower, undertaking

  a risk assessment will be a simple matter to achieve without significant expenditure.

  If however, the premises are not in accordance with the above categories and

  are classified as a high risk, further action will be necessary and an action

  plan should be produced and implemented based on the complexity, size, occupancy

  and consequential risks. </p><p>The employer can enlist

    the help of other persons who have the necessary experience or skills (ie.

    competence)

    to carry out part or all of the risk assessment.

  This &quot;competent person&quot; (possibly a current employee with knowledge

  of safety and company working practices) does not have to be an expert to assist

  the employer, but they need to have sufficient experience/training with regard

  to the problems they are advising on. But remember the employer always remains

  responsible for the outcome. This is worth remembering, should

  you

  require

  help with your risk assessment.</p><h2>Key Stages of Fire Risk

    Assessment</h2><p>There are several methods

    of carrying out a fire risk assessment, the one described below is based

    on the method

    contained within &quot;Fire Safety

  An Employers Guide&quot; issued by the Home Office and the HSE. A systematic

  approach, considered in simple stages, is generally the best practical method.

  This may be undertaken as part of the general health and safety workplace risk

  assessment, or carried out separately.</p><h2>Stage 1 - Identify Fire

    Hazards </h2><p>For a fire to occur it

    needs sources of heat and fuel. If these hazards can be kept apart, removed

    or reduced, then the risks to people and your business

  is minimised. In order to do this you must first identify fire hazards in your

    workplace.</p><ul>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Identify Any Combustibles</strong>      - These can be divided into two main groups, combustible fuels such as

        paper, wood, cardboard, etc and highly combustible fuels such as Thinners,

    Solvents, Polyurethane Foam, etc</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Identify Any Sources of Heat</strong> - All workplaces will contain heat/ignition sources, some will

        be obvious such as cooking equipment or open flames (heating or process).

        Others may be less obvious such as heat from chemical processes or electrical

    equipment.</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Identify Any Unsafe Acts</strong> - Persons undertaking unsafe acts such as smoking next to combustible

    materials etc.</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Identify Any Unsafe Conditions</strong> - These are hazards the may assist a fire to spread in your

        workplace, e.g. if there are large areas of hardboard or polystyrene

        tiles etc, or open stairs that can cause a fire to spread quickly, trapping

    people and involving the whole building.</li>

		</ul><p>An ideal method of identifying and recording these hazards is by means of

  a simple single line plan. Checklists may also be used.</p><h2>Stage 2 - Identify Location

    of Persons who are at Significant Risk</h2><p>Consider the risk to any

    people who may be present. In many instances and particularly for most small

    workplaces the risk(s) identified will not be significant,

  and specific measures for persons in this category will not be required. There

  will, however, be some occasions when certain people may be especially at risk

  from the fire, because of their specific role, disability, sleeping, location

  or the workplace activity. You need to consider matters carefully if:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">Sleeping

    accommodation is provided.</li>

			<li title="*">Persons are

    challenged, eg. physically, visually, mentally, etc.</li>

			<li title="*">People are

    unable to react quickly.</li>

			<li title="*">Persons are

    isolated.</li>

		</ul><p>You must consider all persons, ask questions in particular of visitors to

  your workplace, not all disabilities are obvious. You may need to put special

  provisions in place (see stage 3).</p><h2>Stage 3 - Reduce the Risks,

    Evaluate the Risks and Determine if the Existing Arrangements are Adequate,

    or Need Improvement </h2><p>If the building has been

    built and maintained in accordance with Building Regulations and is being

    put to its designed use, it is likely that the means

  of escape provisions will either be adequate, or you will be able to decide

  easily what is required in relation to the risk. Having identified the hazards

  you need to reduce the chance of a fire occurring and spreading, thereby minimising

  or removing the chance of harm to persons in the workplace by:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Removing</strong>    the hazard altogether</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Reducing</strong> the hazard

    to the point where there is little or no risk</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Replacing</strong> the existing

    hazard with a safer alternative</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Segregating</strong> the hazard

    from the workplace</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Developing A Prevention Policy and Culture</strong> to ensure hazards do not occur in the workplace. This

        should be a dynamic assessment, involving preplanning if introducing

        new processes or working practices and appropriate control measures put

    in place</li>

		</ul><p>The above measures should be straightforward using basic common sense, having

  the additional benefits for your business continuity by managing risks.</p><h2>Evaluate the Risk</h2><p>Attempt to classify each

    area as &quot;high&quot;, &quot;normal&quot;,

  or &quot;low risk&quot;. If &quot;high risk&quot;, you may need to repeat

  the above stages, otherwise additional compensatory measures will be required

  (see overleaf).</p><p>

			<strong>Low Risk</strong> - Areas where there is minimal risk to persons lives, where the risk

  of fire occurring is low, or the potential for fire, heat and smoke spreading

  is negligible and people would have plenty of time to react to an alert of

  fire.</p><p>

			<strong>Normal Risk</strong> - Areas will account for nearly all parts of most workplaces.

  Where an outbreak of fire is likely to remain confined or spread slowly, with

  an effective fire warning allowing persons to escape to a place of safety.</p><p>

			<strong>High Risk</strong> -

    Areas where the available time needed to evacuate the area is reduced by

    the speed of development of a fire, e.g. highly flammable or explosive

  materials stored or used (other than small quantities under controlled conditions).

  Also where the reaction time to the fire alarm is slower because of the type

  of person present or the activity in the workplace, eg. the infirm and elderly

  or persons sleeping on the premises.</p><h2>Determine if the Existing

    Arrangements are Adequate of Need Improvement</h2><p>Matters you will have to

consider are:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Means for Detecting and Giving Warning in Case of Fire</strong> - Can it be heard by

    all occupants; does it need to be automatic in operation?</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Means of Escape</strong> -

        Are they adequate in size, number, location, well lit, unobstructed,

    safe to use, etc?</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Signs</strong> - for exits,

    fire routines, etc.</li>

			<li title="*">

				<strong>Firefighting Equipment</strong>      - Wall mounted by exits, suitable types for hazards present and sufficient

    in number?</li>

		</ul><p>Arrangements for warning all occupants in the event of a fire must be adequate

  and failsafe. Fire alarm systems, smoke detectors and alarms, hand bells or

  a single shout may be suitable depending on the size and complexity of the

  workplace. Arrangements should be made to ensure a telephone is available in

  a place of safety in order to call the Fire Service in the event of fire.</p><p>Escape predominantly without

    the use of a key, should be possible from all parts of a workplace to a place

    of safety in fresh air normally within two

  and half minutes, if the premises are considered &quot;high risk&quot; this

  should be undertaken in much less time (consult &quot;Fire Safety An Employers

  Guide&quot; for details).</p><p>A fire starting in any location should not go undetected and reach a size

  that could cause persons to become trapped. This is more likely to happen where

  there is only one way out of an area. Ideally, persons should be able to turn

  their back on a fire and walk in the opposite direction towards a fire exit.

  Many workplaces, however, will have areas from which there is no alternative

  way out, for part or all of the escape route, (i.e. most rooms have only one

  way out). If your workplace is small and the fire risk has been assessed as

  normal or low then there may be no need to have alternative ways out but where

  your escape is in one direction only, the dead end areas should be kept as

  short, as few, and as low risk as possible.</p><p>The maximum advisable travel

    distances from any area in a workplace to a fire exit door leading out to

    a relative place of safety should be in accordance

  with the table below:</p><table width="90%" cellpadding="5" class="centre" summary="maximum advisable travel      distances from any area in a workplace to a fire exit door leading out to      a relative place of safety">

			<tr>

				<th>Maximum Travel Distances *Measured 

    to a Place of Relative Safety</th>

				<th>Low Fire Risk</th>

				<th>Normal Risk Production Areas (Factory Only)</th>

				<th>Normal Fire Risk</th>

				<th>Normal Fire Risk Sleeping</th>

				<th>High Fire Risk</th>

			</tr>

			<tr>

				<td>More than one route is provided</td>

				<td>60m</td>

				<td>45m</td>

				<td>45m</td>

				<td>32m</td>

				<td>25m</td>

			</tr>

			<tr>

				<td>Only a Single escape route is provided</td>

				<td>45m</td>

				<td>25m</td>

				<td>18m</td>

				<td>16m</td>

				<td>12m</td>

			</tr>

		</table><p>*To an exit (open air where persons can disperse safely), storey exit (staircase

    separated from the remainder of the premises by fire resisting walls and

    self closing fire doors, etc), or a compartment wall (fire resisting wall

and self closing fire doors).</p><p>The above guidelines are to be used with caution. You must look at each part

  of the workplace and decide how quickly persons would react to an alert of

  fire in each area. Adequate safety measures will be required if persons are

  identified as being at risk. Where these travel distances cannot be achieved,

  you will be required to provide extra fire safety precautions and you should

  contact your local Fire Safety Officer or a suitably qualified fire safety

  consultant (once you have completed your fire risk assessment).</p><p>Where persons are at risk or an unacceptable hazard still exists, additional

  fire safety precautions will be required to compensate for this, or alternatively

  repeat previous stages to manage risk to an acceptable level. It is important

  that all fire safety provisions are maintained in good order.</p><h2>Stage 4 - The Findings

    (always recommended, see Stage 5 Review)</h2><p>The findings of the assessment and the actions (including maintenance) arising

  from it should be recorded. If there are five or more employees you <strong>must</strong> retain

  a record which may be in writing, or by electronic or other means. It should

  indicate:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">The date

        the assessment

was made</li>

			<li title="*">The hazards identified</li>

			<li title="*">Any staff and other

    people especially at risk</li>

			<li title="*">What action needs

    to be taken, and by when (Action Plan)</li>

			<li title="*">The conclusions arising</li>

		</ul><p>

			<strong>Prepare the Emergency

      Plan</strong>    - The aim of the plan is to ensure that in the

    event of

    fire

    everyone,

    including contractors and casual employees are sufficiently

  familiar with the action they should take, and that the workplace can be safely

  evacuated to a location where persons will not be in danger. The employer is

  responsible for preparing the plan, and in most small workplaces this should

  not be difficult. In smaller workplaces it may simply take the form of a Fire

  Action Notice.</p><p>

			<strong>Training</strong> -

    All staff should receive induction and regular training relating to the action(s)

    to

    be taken

    in case of fire in particular evacuation procedures,

  fire extinguisher training, where appropriate, and any specialist duties assigned

  eg. calling the Fire Brigade, assisting disabled persons to safety etc. Escape

  routes should be walked regularly and an evacuation drill practised at least

  annually. Visitors and contractors should also be informed of relevant procedures,

  in particular evacuation and other matters such as permits to work etc.</p><h2>Stage 5 - Monitor and Review

    on a Regular Basis </h2><p>The fire risk assessment is not a one-off procedure. It should be continually

  monitored to ensure that the existing fire safety arrangements and risk assessment

  remains realistic. The assessment should be reviewed if there is a significant

  change in the occupancy, work activity, the materials used or stored when building

  works are proposed, young persons are employed, or when it is no longer thought

  to be valid an annual review should take place, irrespective of no changes.</p><h2>Advice and Information </h2><p>If further practical advice

    or information is required following completion of the Risk Assessment, the

    Fire Brigade may be able to assist. Any advice

  given is usually free of charge and impartial.</p><p>Further advice is also

available from:</p><ul>

			<li title="*">Fire Safety

        an Employers Guide published by the Home Office and HSE from Stationery

        Office Bookshops Telephone number (0870) 600 5522, HSE Bookshops Telephone

        number (01787) 881165 and any good book sellers priced &#xA3;9.95 (ISBN

    0-11-341229-0).</li>

			<li title="*">Fire Risk Assessment

        in the Workplace, A Guide for Employers, book and video from the Fire

    Protection Association Telephone number (0181) 2072345.</li>

			<li title="*">Fire Risk Assessment,

        A Guide to Complying with the Fire Precautions (Workplace) Regulations

    from the Fire Industry Council Telephone number (0181) 549 5855.</li>

		</ul><p>Information regarding managing process risks and highly flammable materials

  is available from your local HSE Offices. Advice on reducing the risk of arson

  may be obtained from the Arson Prevention Bureau, Telephone number (0181) 236

9700.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=813"> Providing Information
		(813)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
