<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=814}]"><cms:name>railway-regulations-814</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Fire Safety - Railway Regulations</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=814}]"><cms:name>railway-regulations-814-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>fire, safety, railway, regulations</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=814}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Fire and Emergency Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>All premises that employ persons, with a few exceptions and including offices, shops, railway premises, hotels and factories are subject to the Fire Precautions (Workplace) Regulations 1997 as amended by the Fire Precautions (Workplace) (Amendment) Regulations 1999. </i></p><hr/><p>All offices, shops, railway premises, hotels and factories that require a
  Fire Certificate are subject to the Fire Precautions act 1971. Any offices,
  shop, railway premises, or factory requires a Fire Certificate if, more than
  20 persons are employed in the building or more than 10 person employed anywhere
  other than on the ground floor. If you own a hotel or boarding house and provide
  sleeping accommodation for more than six persons, being guests or staff, or
  this sleeping accommodation is above the first floor or below the ground floor
  you require a Fire Certificate. </p><p>All you are required to do, is to apply for a Fire certificate to your local
  fire brigade on form FP1. Until you are issued with a fire certificate you
  are obliged to carry out certain interim duties which are detailed by the fire
  brigade. The building will be eventually inspected and if the fire precautions
  are below a necessary standard, you will be required to be carried out certain
  works before a fire certificate can be issued. </p><p>This has produced a legislative overlap of fire safety requirements and it
  is hoped that this overlap will be resolved in future legislation hopefully
  when the proposed Fire Safety Act is placed on the statute book. </p><p>When a Fire Certificate
    is issued the owner or occupier is required to provide and maintain four
  principle items:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">The
    Means of Escape</li>
<li title="*">Other
          Means for Securing that the Means of Escape can be safely and effectively
    used at all Material Times</li>
<li title="*">Means
    of Fighting Fire</li>
<li title="*">Means
    of Giving Warning in Case of Fire</li>
</ul><h2>  The Means of Escape from
    Fire with which the Premises are Provided</h2><p> A means
    of escape is designed using a code of practice and in the case of existing
    offices it is &quot;Fire Precautions in Offices and Shops&quot; issued by the
      Home Office. In new buildings an approved document is used and all structural
      fire precautions should be resolved at building control stage, before you take
      occupancy. However you may have to provide portable fire extinguishers depending
      on the fire risks you introduce when you take occupancy. Further advice can
      be got from the Fire Brigade usually in the form of &quot;Notes for Guidance&quot; on
      any fire precaution matters. </p><h2>Other Means for Securing
    the Means of Escape</h2><p>  Other means for securing the means of escape are for example, the provision
      of emergency lighting. If the premises are used at times, and the mains
          electricity was to fail, escape routes would not become impassable
          due to the darkness.
      Emergency lighting ensures a minimum level of light will always be present
      no matter what circumstances prevail. Another example is the provision
          of fire exit signs to indicate the path to safety. Also other signage
          to ensure
      the means of escape is always clear of obstructions and available. </p><h2>Means of Fighting Fire</h2><p>  All premises should be provided with adequate and effective fire fighting
          equipment. It should be able to deal with any small outbreak of fire
          in any part of
      the premises. </p><h2>Means of giving warning in case of Fire </h2><p>  This means, maybe giving a warning verbally or the use of a manual gong,
          in a very small premises to a fully blown electrical fire alarm system
          in the
      larger premises. It usually means a break glass fire alarm system with
          or without the means of detecting devices which are required in certain
          circumstances. </p><p>In addition requirements
may be imposed regarding:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Maintenance
    of the means of escape</li>
<li title="*">Training
    of employees and keeping of records</li>
<li title="*">Occupancy
    numbers</li>
<li title="*">Precaution relating to fire risk to persons</li>
</ul><h2>  Maintenance of Means of Escape </h2><p>  Your means of escape in case of fire has to be maintained and unobstructed.
    All fire doors should be operating correctly and all doors be available when
    the premises are occupied. Other requirement may be enforced such as magnetic
    door catches be released at certain times and checked to see if they are
          working satisfactory. </p><h2>Training and keeping of records </h2><p>  You will be required to carry out regular fire training and record the
          results of that training. You will be required to keep records on other
          fire provisions
      like the testing of fire alarms, fire extinguishers and fire alarm equipment. </p><h2>Occupancy Numbers </h2><p>  In most cases the means of escape is designed to evacuate all the occupants
      of the premises in the required time. However in a number of rare occasions
      when the means of escape cannot cope with the maximum number of people
          who could occupy the premises, a limit is placed on the premises. The
          occupancy
      number is recorded in the Fire Certificate and it is illegal to exceed
          this number if that is possible. </p><h2>Fire risk to persons</h2><p>  If there is any risk considered to be higher that the normal risk to persons
      residing on the premises additional requirements can be included in the
  Fire Certificate. </p><h2>  Other Legislation Specifically
    Relevant to Railways:</h2><p>The following legislation may be relevant to a contracting entity preparing 
        to seek authorisation for new or upgraded works etc. on the high-speed 
        rail network:</p><ul>
        <li title="*">Railways
              and Other Transport Systems (Approvals of Works, Plant and Equipment)
          Regulations 1994 (SI No. 157)</li>
<li title="*">Health and Safety
          at Work etc. Act 1974</li>
          <li title="*">Principal regulations
                made under this Act with important implications to the railway
          industry include:<br/>
          - the Electricity
              at Work Regulations 1989 (SI No. 635)<br/>
             - the Health and
              Safety (Fees) Regulations 2002 (SI No. 655)<br/>
          - the Management
              of Health and Safety at Work Regulations 1999 (SI No. 3242)<br/>
           - the Railways
              (Safety Case) Regulations 2000 (SI No. 2688<br/>
           - the Railways
              (Safety Critical Work) Regulations 1994 (SI No. 299)<br/>
           - the Carriage
              of Dangerous Goods by Rail Regulations 1996 (SI No. 2089)<br/>
           - the Railway Safety
              (Miscellaneous Provisions) Regulations 1997
      </li>
          <li title="*">Construction
          (Design and Management) Regulations 1994 (SI No. 3140)</li>
<li title="*">Factories Act
          1961</li>
              <li title="*">Fire Precautions
          Act 1971: <br/>
          - Health and
                  Safety Fire Certificates (Special Premises) Regulations 1976
                  (SI No. 2003) <br/>
          - Fire Precautions
                  (Factories, Offices, Shops and Railway Premises) Regulations
                  1989 (SI No. 76)  <br/>      
           - Fire Precautions
                  (Sub-surface Railway Stations) Regulations 1989 (SI No. 1401)    </li>
              <li title="*">Building Act
          1984 and Building (Scotland) Act 1959</li>
              <li title="*">Building Regulations
          1991 (SI No. 2768)</li>
              <li title="*">Town and Country
          Planning Act 1957</li>
              <li title="*">Office, Shops
          and Railway Premises Act 1963</li>
         <li title="*">British Transport
          Commission Act 1957</li>
<li title="*">Level Crossings
          Act 1983</li>
<li title="*">Regulation of
          Railways Acts 1868, 1873 and 1889</li>
<li title="*">Railways Regulations
          Acts 1840 and 1842</li>
<li title="*">Railways Clauses
          Consolidation Act 1845</li>
<li title="*">Transport and
          Works Act 1992</li>
<li title="*">Rail Vehicle
              Accessibility Regulations 1998 (SI No. 2457) (note: these Regulations
              were notified by the UK to the European Commission as containing
          a national standard)</li>
 </ul><p>There are a large number of acts and orders covering the construction 
        of existing railways. There may be relevant information in any such act 
      that relates to any railway that it is intended to modify.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=814"> Providing Information
		(814)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
