<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=734}]"><cms:name>arts-and-leisure-734</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Accommodation</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=734}]"><cms:name>arts-and-leisure-734-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Tourist</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>accommodation</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=734}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Arts and Leisure</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Information regarding Accommodation in the locality</i></p><hr/><h2>How to book</h2><p>To book your accommodation simply telephone or write to the 
  establishment of your choice. Remember to state your requirements clearly and precisely 
  and advise the establishment of your expected time of arrival. It is strongly recommended 
  that you confirm your booking in writing. Also, if you are delayed on your journey, 
  a telephone call to inform management that you may be late might help to avoid problems 
  on arrival.</p><p>Please note, that acceptance of accommodation bookings made 
  by telephone or in writing are legally binding contracts. If the accommodation is 
  cancelled, not taken up or left prematurely, the proprietor may be entitled to compensation. 
  Check cancellation terms in advance.</p><p>All prices are correct at time of print but may be subject to 
  change. Please confirm price before booking. The inclusion of any establishment 
  in this guide does not indicate recommendation. No responsibility can be taken for 
  any errors or omissions. The list of facilities is intended as a general guide. 
  If you have specific requirements, please check with the establishment concerned.</p><h2>Complaints</h2><p>If you are dissatisfied with your accommodation, you should 
  inform the management at the time of the incident. This gives the management the 
  opportunity to take prompt action and to put things right without delay.</p><p>Complaints can also be directed to the Tourist Information Centre 
  in writing stating at which establishment you stayed, when, and the nature of the 
  complaint. The staff at the centre will record and investigate complaints, but please 
  note that they have no statutory control over establishments in their method of 
  operation and cannot become involved in legal or contractual matters.</p><p>Please find the list of local accommodation below;</p><p>
<span class="gen">enter details</span>
</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=734"> Providing Information
		(734)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
