<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=535}]"><cms:name>recycling-535</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Recycling - composters</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=535}]"><cms:name>recycling-535-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>composters, recycling, garden, waste, kitchen</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=535}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Frequently asked questions about composters</i></p><hr/><ul>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t1">What is a Composter?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t2">Why Compost?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t3">Where is the best place to put a Compost bin?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t4">What can I put in my Compost bin?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t5">How do you know when the compost is ready?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t6">How much do they cost?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="#t7">How can I order one?</a>	
				</strong>
			</li>
		</ul><h3>

			What is a Composter?</h3><p>Composters are recycled plastic bins for the garden. Waste deposited in a composter prevents odour you would normally find in your bin. All composters have a lid and hatch.</p><h3>

			Why Compost?</h3><p>The majority of waste is disposed of in landfill sites throughout the country. The council is committed to reducing the amount of waste sent to landfill sites, in accordance with the National Waste Strategy 2000. The Strategy specifies that we must recycle or compost 30% of household waste by 2010. The government has also set the target of ensuring that 40% of households with a garden compost by 2001. As a council we are dependant upon the help and support of our residents to enable these targets to be met.</p><p>
<strong>Did you know that 20% of the average household dustbin is comprised of organic material.</strong>
</p><p>Organic waste is biodegradable and when it is buried in landfill sites it rots and produces methane gas. Methane gas can escape into buildings near landfill sites and lead to explosions. It is not necessary to send organic waste to landfill sites as it can be converted into a useful product by householders. Compost bins can be purchased which convert food waste and other organic material into compost. Composting is one of the Best Practicable Environmental Options for the reduction of waste to landfill. It is possible to reduce 20% of the waste in a bin without causing any environmental damage. This is more environmentally friendly than recycling as no energy input is required for transport or in the recycling process.</p><h2>How to get the best results from your compost bin.</h2><h3>

			Where is the best place to put a compost bin?</h3><p>For the best results from your compost bin it should be positioned in a sunny spot on well drained soil. The soil below the bin should be loosened to improve drainage and increase access for worms and bacteria. Place a few inches of kitchen waste on the soil at the bottom of the bin, this will attract worms and bacteria to the bin and increase the rate of compost formation. For the best results, organic waste should be put in the bin in layers of different material between 6 12 cm deep.</p><h3>

			What can I put in my Composter?</h3><p>You can compost almost anything that is organic, i.e. anything that has been grown. This includes:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">fruit and vegetable scraps</li>
			<li title="*">tea bags, coffee grounds</li>
			<li title="*">crushed egg shells</li>
			<li title="*">grass cuttings, prunings and leaves</li>
			<li title="*">small amounts of shredded paper and soft cardboard</li>
			<li title="*">animal hair</li>
			<li title="*">vacuum dust (only if you have woollen carpets)</li>
		</ul><p>The following can <strong>not</strong> be put into your composter</p><ul>
			<li title="*">cat or dog excrement</li>
			<li title="*">meat</li>
			<li title="*">cheeses</li>
			<li title="*">fish</li>
			<li title="*">disposable nappies</li>
			<li title="*">shiny card</li>
			<li title="*">hard objects</li>
		</ul><p>For best results, ensure your compost bin contains some grass cuttings or vegetarian animal manure. They heat up and speed up the composting process. However they should be mixed with other organic waste to avoid slime formation.</p><p>It is essential that your compost bin is kept warm and moist. Placing the bin in the sun and out of the wind is therefore preferable. Ensure you always put the lid on your compost bin and do not let the compost dry out.</p><p>To ensure that air is getting to the centre of the bin, turn the material regularly. This will also speed up the decomposition process.</p><h3>

			How do you know when the compost is ready?</h3><p>Your compost is ready for use when the material does not resemble anything that you put in the bin. Collect the compost from the small hatch at the bottom of the bin. The compost can then be spread on the garden where it will act as a fertiliser.</p><h3>

			How much do they cost?</h3><p>Compost bins are available to purchase from the Council at a subsidised rate.</p><ul>
			<li title="*">enter details</li>
		</ul><p>Prices are inclusive of VAT and all bins are delivered to your door (please allow 28 days for delivery).</p><h3>

			How can I order one?</h3><p>
<strong>This offer is open to residents only</strong>
</p><p>To order your composter bin you can either:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Pay <strong>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/535h">on-line</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to online form</span> with your Creditcard:</li>
			<li title="*">by Cheque - print out the <strong>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/535h">form</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to online form</span> and post it back 
    to us together with your payment.</li>
			<li title="*">Telephone us using the contact details above</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=535"> Paying for goods and services
		(535)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
