<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=160}]"><cms:name>adoption-160</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Adoption</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=160}]"><cms:name>adoption-160-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>adoption</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=160}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Adoption is about meeting the needs of children, not meeting the needs of adults who wish to adopt. </i></p><hr/><p>Recently we have seen the 
  introduction of much new legislation to govern Adoption Practice. We now have 
  National Minimum Standards for Adoption as well as the Adoption and Children 
  Act 2002, which is gradually being phased in. There is also procedural guidance 
  for the provision of Post Adoption Support and for Inter Country Adoption. </p><h2>Children Placed for Adoption</h2><p> Adoption has changed markedly 
  over the past 30 years. In 1970, 20,000 children were placed for Adoption. The 
  majority of these were babies. Thirty years later as society's views and 
  attitudes have changed this figure has decreased greatly. In 1999, 2,2000 children 
  were placed for adoption. Over the past 4 years, however, this figure has grown 
  due to greater acknowledgement of the role adoption can play in making permanent 
  plans for children. Although the number of children adopted has dropped in the 
  past 30 years the number of children adopted from care has grown. </p><p> The majority of children 
  placed for Adoption will have been removed from their parents through the court 
  system due to maltreatment in one form or another. All of these children will 
  have had their plan for adoption approved by the court.  These children come to adoption 
  with their own identity, background and family history, all of which will impact 
  on their adoptive home and require understanding and acceptance in order to 
  increase the possibility of a successful placement. </p><p>Children who come into care 
  are in most cases initially placed in foster care. Great efforts are made to 
  keep siblings together. </p><p>Children awaiting adoption 
  need careful preparation and explanation about what is going to happen to them 
  and why. </p><p>Most children will need 
  to maintain some level of contact with their birth parents in order to promote 
  their self-esteem and identity. In most cases this is achieved through indirect 
  letterbox contact. </p><h2>People wishing to Adopt</h2><p> Prospective adopters must 
  be 21 or over. There is no upper age limit.</p><p> A couple wishing to adopt 
  together must be married, although this is very likely to change in the near 
  future with the implementation of new legislation. </p><p>Currently one member of 
  a co-habiting couple can adopt and the other partner would need to apply for 
  an order giving them Parental Responsibility. </p><p>Applications are welcomed 
  from single people who can also adopt. </p><p>We welcome applicants from all areas of society and 
  does not discriminate in any way. </p><p>We offer a service to all our residents and also welcome applications 
  from those living outside the area, particularly from people wishing to adopt 
  older children, sibling groups or children with special needs. </p><p> All applicants undergo 
  statutory checks carried out through the police, social services, health, education 
  and probation services. Anyone with an offence against children is barred by 
  law from becoming an adopter. Personal references, eg. from friends or employers 
  are also taken up. </p><p>All prospective adopters 
  undergo a medical examination carried out by their own GP. </p><p>Adopters are viewed by the 
  Local Authority as an important and valuable resource for children in need of 
  adoption. As a result great care is taken in the training, assessment and support 
  of all applicants.  </p><p>Interest is particularly 
  welcomed from people who can offer a home to: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">children 4 years and 
      older</li>
			<li title="*">brothers and sisters</li>
			<li title="*">children with uncertain 
      developmental futures</li>
			<li title="*">people who have already 
      parented and have older children</li>
			<li title="*">children of black or 
      mixed race</li>
		</ul><p>The Council also accepts applications from people wishing to adopt from overseas. Such assessments 
  are carried out by a voluntary adoption agency and the cost, of around &#xA3;2,500 
  is met by the adopters. </p><p>Anyone contacting us 
  will be able to talk to a social worker experienced in Adoption practice. An 
  information pack is available and will be sent to anyone who wants to know more. 
  </p><h2>Children waiting to be placed for 
  adoption</h2><p> Each child is the subject 
  of a Care Order made by a court. The Authority has to present a Care Plan to 
  the court outlining and timetabling its plan to place the child for Adoption. 
  </p><p>A referral is made to the 
  local Adoption Consortium to access approved families within this pool. </p><p>Advertisements are placed 
  in specialist magazines and interest sought from approved adopters. </p><p>Detailed and informative 
  profiles of the children are prepared and sent to other Local Authorities and 
  Voluntary Adoption Agencies throughout the country. </p><h2>Post Adoption Support</h2><p>The value of post adoption 
  support has been recognised more in recent years as being crucial to the success 
  of adoptive placements. A child's need for explanation and knowledge about 
  his background may grow as he gets older. His behaviour may increasingly reflect 
  the impact of poor or abusive parenting in his early years. </p><p> We will support all adoptive placements through our 
  own services or those of a family's adoption agency. </p><p>The Local Authority also 
  has a responsibility to the birth parents of children placed for adoption and 
  will provide support and counselling to them. </p><p>We operate 
  a Post Adoption Letter Box service to facilitate the exchange of photographs 
  and letters between adopters and birth family members. </p><h2>When A Local Authority is Planning 
  to Place a Child for Adoption</h2><p>Adoption is a way of providing 
  a new permanent family for a child, not able to be brought up in the birth family. 
  A Local Authority acts as an Adoption Agency and is legally allowed to arrange 
  adoptions. This is done by the Social Worker gaining an understanding of the 
  child's needs and seeking the adoptive family best able to meet them. </p><p>The Local Authority however 
  cannot make such an arrangement legally binding. Only the court can do this, 
  by the making of an Adoption Order. This ends the child's legal relationships 
  with the birth family and gives the child new legal parents. The child becomes 
  a full member of the adoptive family, the same as being born to the adopters. 
  </p><p>Adoption means the permanent 
  transfer of parental responsibility. This is such an important thing to happen 
  in a child's life, that the law requires Adoption Agencies and courts to make 
  sure that they put the child's long-term welfare first when they make decisions 
  about adoption. </p><p>If your child is adopted, 
  you will no longer have any legal rights and responsibilities. It may not be 
  possible for you to see each other but there will be the opportunity for you 
  to have 'indirect contact' via the Local Authority in the form of 
  news about your child from the adoptive family. </p><p>If you have any worries, 
  doubts or questions your child's Social Worker will try to help you as much 
  as possible with these. You should also talk to your solicitor if you have one. 
  You may find it helpful to talk things over with your family and friends too. 
  In the past few years several independent organisations have been formed to 
  offer advice and support to people in your position. </p><h3>Knowing about you 
  is important</h3><p> Before an adoption can 
  be arranged, the agency is required by law to ask for a lot of information about 
  you and your child. This information is personal and will be treated as confidential, 
  however there are some circumstances where the agency might need to pass particular 
  information on to other people. Wherever possible, such circumstances will be 
  explained to you. </p><p>All this information is 
  needed for us to have the fullest possible knowledge and understanding of your 
  child and family of birth. This helps those making the decisions about the future. 
  You can therefore help your child by agreeing to provide as much information 
  as you can about yourself and your family and by understanding our need to ask 
  your doctor about your family's health. </p><p>We try to arrange for all 
  birth parents to meet the prospective adopters of their child if it is felt 
  to be appropriate. This is to help both sets of parents to have an image of, 
  and a little more knowledge about each other. It will also be helpful for your 
  child's adoptive parents to know as much as possible about your family background. 
  Origins and birth family will be important to your child growing up. The information 
  about your family's health will be important. Brothers and sisters (including 
  half-brothers and sisters) are also very important to adopted children. If brothers 
  and sisters have to be placed separately, each adoptive family will usually 
  be asked to keep in touch with each other. Sometimes this is done through our &quot;Letter Box Scheme&quot;. The &quot;Letter Box&quot; is explained 
  later on this page. If you have any more children, or any other important changes 
  occur in your life or your family, the Letter Box is a way of keeping your adopted 
  child informed. </p><h3>Choosing a family 
  for your child</h3><p> The law requires that Adoption 
  Agencies make very thorough enquiries about families wishing to adopt. All prospective 
  adopters undergo lengthy training and assessment by an Adoption Agency and must 
  be approved by an Adoption Panel before they can be considered for adoption. 
  </p><p>They are asked all sorts 
  of information about themselves and their family background. </p><p>From having knowledge of 
  their own family experiences and their skills and interests, the agency gets 
  a picture of their family life and gains an understanding of what kind of upbringing 
  they would offer a child. When your child's social worker looks for a family, 
  one will be chosen because it is thought they are able to meet your child's 
  needs. Your child's long-term welfare is the first consideration. A placement 
  will not be made until it is believed that the right family is available. When 
  a suitable family is found a recommendation is made to the Director of Social 
  Services, who considers the needs of your child and the family recommended and 
  makes the final decision. It is hoped that parents are reassured to know that 
  so much thought goes into choosing the right family. </p><p>There may be special considerations 
  you would like to be included in choosing your child's family. You might, for 
  example, want your child to have a particular religious or cultural upbringing 
  or to have the opportunity to develop a special interest or skill. Tell your 
  child's social worker if you would like to make a list of what you would like 
  in a family for your child. </p><p>It is not possible to promise 
  to do as you wish, because your child's overall welfare must always be considered 
  in choosing the adoptive family. However, your wishes will be taken into account 
  wherever possible. </p><p>Older children will be given 
  help to understand how adoption affects them in relation to you and your family 
  and will be asked their views about the type of adoptive family they wish to 
  live with. </p><h3>Adoption by foster 
  carers</h3><p> Perhaps your child has 
  been looked after by foster carers for a long time and they would like to adopt. 
  In this case, the same thorough enquiries have to be made as are made with any 
  other adopters. It is still very important to be sure that it would be best 
  for your child to be adopted by that family, before adoption can be recommended 
  and an adoption application made to the court. </p><h3>Applying to adopt 
  a child</h3><p> Adoption can be carried 
  out in one stage or two. The prospective adopters can make an application to 
  adopt to the court of their choice and this application will be heard by a Judge. 
  This is usually the case when birth parents agree to the adoption. However, 
  in certain circumstances the agency may apply to the court for an Order freeing 
  a child for adoption. This Order is then used by the adoptive parents at a later 
  stage when they apply to the court for an Adoption Order. </p><h3>Freeing for adoption</h3><p> This procedure is not used 
  in situations where parents are agreeing to their child's adoption. It is more 
  likely to be used if you wish to oppose your child's adoption. </p><p>A Freeing Order transfers 
  your rights and responsibilities wholly to the agency. Later on, when adopters 
  make their application to adopt, the court transfers the parental right from 
  the agency to the adoptive parents. </p><p>If an application to free 
  your child for adoption is made, you will be asked to decide at that stage whether 
  you would like to be informed about your child's placement and when the Adoption 
  Order has been made. If you want to be kept in touch and within a year of the 
  Freeing Order your child has not been adopted, you will be able to apply to 
  the court for leave to resume your legal rights and responsibilities as the 
  child's parent. </p><p>When a Freeing Order is 
  granted to the Local Authority it is normal for the prospective adopters to 
  then make their application to adopt to the court of their choice. This application 
  will then be heard by a judge at an Adoption hearing. </p><h3>Are you willing 
  for your child to be adopted?</h3><p> It may be that your child 
  is the subject of a Care Order and an adoption plan was agreed upon by the court. 
  Alternatively, it may be that you have asked this agency to arrange your child's 
  adoption and an adoptive family has been sought at your request. In either circumstance, 
  if you are willing for your child to be adopted, the court will ask a Social 
  Worker independent of this agency (known as a Reporting Officer) to visit you 
  and make sure that you understand what adoption involves. The Reporting Officer 
  will need to be sure that you are willing to agree to your child's adoption 
  quite freely and without any conditions. If the Reporting Officer is satisfied 
  that you have thought about it carefully and know what you are doing, you will 
  be asked to sign a formal document giving your agreement. The Reporting Officer 
  will sign too, as a witness. This form will then be given to the court, who 
  will also be told that you do understand what is involved. </p><h3>Are you unhappy 
  at the prospect of your child being adopted?</h3><p> If you are, it is important 
  for you to have legal advice from a Solicitor experienced in childcare matters 
  as soon as possible. We will be able to give you a list of the Solicitors in 
  this area that specialise in childcare cases. You may be entitled to Legal Aid 
  and your Solicitor will be able to advise you about this. </p><p>One of two things must happen 
  before a court can take away your rights as a parent and make an adoption order: 
  either you must agree to this or the court must decide to dispense with the 
  need for you to agree. However it can only do so if one of the circumstances 
  set out in the law applies in your case and the court will need to have satisfactory 
  evidence of this. The court will send you a copy of the statement of evidence 
  they are given, and you should discuss it with your Solicitor as soon as you 
  can. </p><p>In order to safeguard your 
  child's interests the court will also ask a Social Worker independent of this 
  agency (known as a Guardian ad Litem) to visit you. The Guardian ad Litem will 
  want to know why you do not think it is a good idea for your child to be adopted. 
  Your views will be reported to the court, because it is very important for them 
  to know how you feel about your child's future. You will also have an opportunity 
  to go to the court yourself if you want to, to explain why you are not willing 
  to agree to your child's adoption. An Adoption Order cannot be made unless the 
  court is sure it would be in your child's best interests to be adopted, and 
  they have to take account of your views in deciding this. </p><h3>What happens after 
  adoption?</h3><p> When your child moves to 
  live with the adoptive family, the adoptive parents will already have received 
  much information that will be important to your child growing up. Your child 
  will also understand as fully as possible what is happening and will have their 
  very own &quot;Life Story Book&quot; explaining their life in words pictures 
  and photos. Hopefully, this book will have been made with your help, as knowing 
  about you is important. As the years go by, your child will be given more information 
  according to their level of understanding. </p><p>A decision will be made 
  about the type of contact you are to have with your child once the placement 
  for adoption has been made. This Department believes that in most cases some 
  form of continued contact with the birth family and ongoing knowledge of them 
  is important to a child growing up and developing in his adoptive family. There 
  are two important factors in deciding what sort of contact is appropriate. Firstly 
  any contact must be in the child's best interests and secondly any contact must 
  not have a harmful effect on the adoptive placement. </p><p>There are two types of contact 
  in adoption, direct and indirect. </p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				<p>
					<strong>Direct 
        Contact</strong>
					<br/>
      This is face to face 
        contact between the birth family and the child. This does not happen very 
        often in adoption and usually only when the child has a positive relationship 
        with a member of the birth family. This person, either a parent or relative, 
        must also be in agreement with the plan for adoption and be able to support 
        the adoptive placement. </p>
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				<p>
					<strong>Indirect 
        Contact</strong>
					<br/>
      This is contact by 
        letter and photographs or videos. This is usually arranged by Social 
        Services through its Post Adoption Letterbox. All adopters 
        chosen are willing to have indirect contact if it is 
        appropriate. This is usually in the form of a letter about your child 
        and photographs sent once or twice per year. When an adoptive home has 
        been found for your child an agreement will be drawn up outlining what 
        information is to be passed on. Say what you would like to know about 
        your child's progress e.g. school, interests, health and ask for this 
        to be put in the agreement. The agreement will be drawn up specially to 
        meet the needs of the people involved. </p>
			</li>
		</ul><p>You may also like to write 
  a letter and send photographs about yourself and your family. Ask if this is 
  possible. If it is not then you can still send them and ask for them to be kept 
  by us  until your child is an adult. It is possible that your child 
  may then contact us seeking more information about the past and they will be 
  given these letters. </p><p>It is important that adopted 
  children are able to have further significant information about their birth 
  families over the years. It is also important and reassuring to families to 
  have news of their child from time to time. </p><h3>The Post Adoption 
  Letter Box Scheme</h3><p> This is the means by which 
  information will be exchanged between yourself and your child's adoptive family. 
  The scheme is run by the Letter Box Co-ordinator who will try to answer any 
  queries you may have about the scheme or pass you onto a Social Worker who will 
  try to help you. If you have not made an agreement to either give or receive 
  information at the time of your child's placement it may be possible to arrange 
  one sometime later. We would be prepared to look into this for you. </p><p>It should be pointed out 
  that the agreements mentioned above are not legally binding and are not formally 
  linked with any Court Order. </p><h3>When your child 
  becomes an adult</h3><p> When babies and toddlers 
  are placed for adoption, the adopters sometimes change the child's first name. 
  They get an adoption certificate from the Registrar General which shows the 
  child's new name only and shows the adopters as parents. This certificate takes 
  the place of a birth certificate for all legal purposes. On reaching 18, your 
  child will be legally entitled, to get a copy of the original birth certificate. 
  However, your child is likely to still have a Life Story Book completed in earlier 
  life. It is usual for a copy of the original birth certificate to be put in 
  the Life Story Book. </p><p>The birth certificate will 
  show your child's original name, your name and the address you were living at 
  when the birth was registered. </p><p>For birth fathers, who were 
  not married to the mother or present at the child's registration, you need to 
  understand that your child may not be able to learn of your identity from the 
  birth certificate. </p><h3>Post adoption services 
  in this area</h3><p> This agency is now developing 
  post-adoption services more comprehensively and is prepared to work in many 
  ways to assist and support: </p><ul>
			<li title="*">Adopted 
      children and their adoptive families.</li>
			<li title="*">Adopted adults.</li>
			<li title="*">Birth parents and 
      grandparents.</li>
			<li title="*">Siblings of adopted 
      children.</li>
		</ul><p>You should use the contact 
  details above for more information on this and any other points on this page.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=160"> Providing Information
		(160)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
