<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=260}]"><cms:name>respite-care-for-children-260</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Respite Care for Children</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=260}]"><cms:name>respite-care-for-children-260-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>respite, care, children</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=260}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Respite care provides a series of pre-planned short term placements of a particular child with the same carer. The length and timing of the arrangements can vary according to the specific needs of the child and their family. </i></p><hr/><p>The 1989 Children Act provides a clear legislative framework for the provision of short-term care. The Act requires children to be consulted about their needs and about the services to be provided and if a child is using &quot;respite care&quot;, the local authority's Social Services must draw up a care plan, visit the child from time to time and review the placements on a regular basis. Whichever agency is providing the short-term care, it should always be part of an integrated and co-ordinated approach to meeting the child's needs.  </p><p> Respite care can be arranged on a one off or a regular basis. It can also be arranged for short periods of time (such as a few hours) or for longer stays of a week or more. Respite care is usually arranged on a planned basis, but it may be arranged quickly in an emergency situation. </p><p>Primarily, the respite care provides day care for children, which could involve providing respite for just mornings, afternoons, after school or at times over the weekend.  On occasions, where appropriate, respite carers can be asked to have the child for overnight stays.  There are instances when respite carers can be asked to provide longer terms of care.  This would be subject to their availability, approval and providing that this does not exceed a period of four weeks. </p><p>The conditions of working within the respite carer scheme means that the carer can regulate their level of commitment.  This can be suited to meet their availability and the circumstances of their own family needs.  Some carers find it easier to work with just one or two children while others enjoy the dynamics and demands of working with a number of children.  Some placements can be planned to be with carers for different periods throughout the weeks. </p><h2>Why do children need respite care? </h2><p>The respite carer scheme has been established for the benefit of the children and their families.  For children to be placed within the scheme there has often been some family crisis or problem for which they need some support or assistance.  This includes a family illness, the parents finding the child's behaviour very difficult to handle or the parent is not coping.  Respite care offers a break or a series of breaks that could act to prevent a family breakdown or the child being placed in foster care. </p><p>The true value of the respite carer scheme is that it seeks to maintain a child in their own home and helps to keep families together. </p><h2>Are all children who need respite care difficult and disturbed? </h2><p>All children who are referred to the respite carer scheme will have gone through change in their lives by being withdrawn from their own family, if only for a short time.   They may have been emotionally disturbed and upset due to the events of a family crisis.  Children in respite care could also have had to cope with other moves, maybe with relatives or alternative respite carers.  Indeed there could have been many circumstances in their lives that mean they need sensitive care. </p><p>The way in which children react and respond to changes whilst being introduced into an alternative home will be different.  Some can be aggressive and uneasy, others may at first be over polite and willing to please.  Others will withdraw into themselves, or act as if they  haven't a care in the world.  In some circumstances children can come from very deprived homes and on other occasions, they may have been neglected and not provided with the same level of care that you would be able to offer. </p><p>What respite care does do, is provide the family and the child with the opportunity of a break while at the same time enabling social services to gain more understanding of both the child and family's needs. </p><p>Respite carers do work very closely with families to help parents overcome the problems they experience. </p><h2>What is involved in being a respite carer? </h2><p>Respite carers are a group of caring, responsible people who are trained to work with children and families offering them support, respite, advice and attention. All repite carers:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">work for the Council's Social Services </li>
  <li title="*">work from their own home </li>
  <li title="*">prepare reports and assessments </li>
  <li title="*">provide short term emergency placements </li>
  <li title="*">support first time mothers before and after birth and assist with parenting skills </li>
  <li title="*">are available at short notice </li>
  <li title="*">work with children up to 14 years old </li>
  <li title="*">provide planned summer holiday care. </li>
</ul><p>From a child's point of view, a respite carer will:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">always treat them as part of the family </li>
  <li title="*">listen and talk to them </li>
  <li title="*">discipline them </li>
  <li title="*">protect them and look after their needs </li>
  <li title="*">be there for cuddles, reassurance and trust </li>
  <li title="*">help build ongoing relationships with people who are important to them and will provide them with information </li>
  <li title="*">work with different children at different times. </li>
</ul><h2>Requirments of becoming a respite carer </h2><p>Becoming a respite carer requires:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">commitment </li>
  <li title="*">flexibility </li>
  <li title="*">energy </li>
  <li title="*">tolerance </li>
  <li title="*">ability to satisfy requirements of statutory checks and references </li>
  <li title="*">attendance at support training meetings. </li>
</ul><p>You would not be considered suitable if:</p><ul>
  <li title="*">you are over 58 years old </li>
  <li title="*">you and your partner work full time (unless you wish to do weekend respite) </li>
  <li title="*">any member of your household has a serious criminal conviction </li>
  <li title="*">you already respite or foster for another agency </li>
  <li title="*">you are currently waiting to adopt </li>
  <li title="*">you have a child currently being looked after by a social services department. </li>
</ul><h2>Assessment for becoming a respite carer </h2><p>An initial visit to your home will take place to discuss the respite scheme. </p><p>With agreement to continue, your permission will be sought to undertake statutory checks and references.  These include police, probation, health visitor (where appropriate) and two referees.  You will be asked to attend a medical with your own doctor, paid for by Social Services.  A health and safety inspection will be made on your home and garden. </p><p>Subject to satisfactory references and checks, you will be invited to attend a series of training sessions. </p><p>A family assessment will be completed during a number of visits to your home. </p><p>The completed assessment is submitted to the Council's Panel.  Subject to the Panel's agreement, you will be approved and registered as a  Council respite carer. </p><p>For more information, please use the contact details above. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=260"> Providing Information
		(260)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
