<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=263}]"><cms:name>residential-care-for-children-263</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Residential Care for Children</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=263}]"><cms:name>residential-care-for-children-263-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>residential, care, children</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=263}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Residential Care for Children/Children's Homes are 
  there to ensure that the needs of children are met when they cannot live with 
  their own family. They are a place for children to develop and grow, as well 
  as providing food, shelter, and space for play and leisure in a caring environment. 
  Children's Homes look after children with many different needs.</i></p><hr/><p/><p>When children and young 
  people come to live in a Children's Home they will have a Care Plan. Their Care 
  Plan says why a child is living in a home, what is supposed to happen while 
  they are living there and what is supposed to happen at the end of their stay. 
  Most children will go home, but a few go to live with other families and a few 
  go to live in other homes. Older children who are not planning to return home, 
  are given help to prepare them for living on their own - this is called Aftercare.</p><p>Education is important. 
  Children go to their own school if they have a school place, or we help to get 
  them back into school. Although some young people may still attend different 
  resources in the community, for example school, college, etc.</p><p>It is very important that 
  children and young people stay in touch with their family and friends. It is 
  only when they might be hurt, or a Court Order says that contact is not allowed, 
  that some children will not be able to have visits from their family or will 
  not be able to visit them.</p><p>Children and young people 
  are respected as individuals. By providing for their religious and cultural 
  needs children are encouraged to keep their sense of personal identity and community. 
  </p><h2>Eligibility For The Service</h2><p> Children and young people 
  have to live away from their own families for all sorts of reasons. These include: 
  </p><ul>
  <li title="*">Their parents are unwell</li>
  <li title="*">They have problems with their family and need to spend some time away from 
      home, eg: behaviour problems or educational difficulties</li>
  <li title="*">They may have a disability and need a break from living with their families</li>
  <li title="*">They 
      are in the care of local authority subject on a Court Order or an Interim 
      Care Order, and,</li>
  <li title="*">Generally, when children 
        and young people need to live away from their families, they will stay 
        with foster carers. It is only when Foster care is either not possible 
        or not desirable accommodation or may not be what the young person would 
        choose</li>
  </ul><p> In all cases, we make sure 
  that all the alternatives are fully considered before recommending residential 
  care.
			</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=263"> Providing Information
		(263)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
