<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=158}]"><cms:name>home-ownership-service--home-move-purchase-grants-158</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Home Ownership Service - Home Move Purchase Grants</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=158}]"><cms:name>home-ownership-service--home-move-purchase-grants-158-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>home, ownership, service, move, purchase, grant</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=158}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Under the scheme, the Council will pay tenants a grant to help them buy their new home. The size of the grant depends on where tenants are moving and the type of property they are giving up. </i></p><hr/><p>  This not only helps those residents who want to own their home to get on the property ladder, but also helps to free up homes for people on the Council's Housing List. </p><p>  The eligibility criteria is set out below, but anyone who would like more information about the scheme should use the contact details above.</p><p>  To be eligible to apply for a grant you must: </p><ul>
				<li title="*"> Be a Council tenant or housing association tenant living in the area, in a property with one or more bedrooms </li>
				<li title="*"> Have been a Council tenant for a minimum of two years. (For grants of over &#xA3;13,000 you must have been a tenant for at least five years). </li>
				<li title="*"> Be under six weeks rent arrears at the time you apply and clear when you vacate </li>
			</ul><p>  It is important to note that priority will be given to tenants from larger properties and those on the ground floor, especially those with gardens. Tenants in severely overcrowded accommodation or those with urgent medical needs will also receive priority </p><p>  The grant is paid when the sale is completed - it is not available to be used as a deposit. </p><p>  If an application for a Cash Incentive Grant is successful, the applicant will be contacted by the Council within two weeks and will be informed about further details relating to the scheme. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=158"> Providing Information
		(158)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
