<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=25}]"><cms:name>education-1-25</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Higher education - student loan</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=25}]"><cms:name>education-1-25-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Student</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>higher, education, student, loan</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=25}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Student loans are available to students who require help with living costs. Unlike support towards tuition fees, you have to repay any loans. However you will not have to start paying them back until you have finished or left your course and you begin earning.</i></p><hr/><p>Interest on the amount that you owe will be linked to inflation - inline with the Retail Prices Index (RPI). This means the value of the amount you pay back will be broadly the same, in real terms, as the value of the amount you borrowed.</p><h4>How much will I have to pay towards my tuition fees?</h4><p>Full-time students starting courses of higher education have to pay up to &#xA3;1,125 a year towards their tuition fees. Most students, though, are eligible for support to help meet these fees. This is means tested and it depends on your or your family's income. The amount of Government support you get towards your tuition fees depends on the following main factors.</p><ul>

			<li title="*">Whether you study full time or part-time.</li>

			<li title="*">The level of your income and that of your parents, husband, or partner.</li>

			<li title="*">Which course you study. For example, some courses automatically qualify for free tuition for certain years. </li>

			<li title="*">Whether or not you study at a publicly funded university or college.</li>

			<li title="*">Whether you have previously been on a higher education course and received Government support to do so. </li>

			<li title="*">Whether you meet the residence requirement.</li>

		</ul><h4>How do I apply?</h4><p>You need to contact our Student Awards Section as soon as possible after applying for a university or college place. They will decide if you are eligible for financial help with fees and living costs, and how much help you will be entitled to. If you currently attend a <span class="gen">enter council name</span> school or college, information is available from them.</p><h4>When will I receive the financial support?</h4><p>As long as you have applied in time and your university or college has confirmed your place, you will be paid your first loan at the start of the academic year. The Government's contribution to your tuition will be paid direct to your university or college. The majority of payments are made by the Student Loans Company, Not <span class="gen">enter council name.</span>

		</p><h4>Am I entitled to any help for my dependants while I am studying?</h4><p>You may get a special grant if your children are financially dependent on you. Please contact our Student Award Section on <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span> for advice. The university or college you are planning to go to may also be able to offer you help with the costs of childcare through their access fund.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=25"> Providing Information
		(25)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
