<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=401}]"><cms:name>advice-to-business-401</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Advice to Business</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=401}]"><cms:name>advice-to-business-401-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Businesses</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>advice, business</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=401}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>We enforce and advise on legislation designed to protect the consumer from dishonest traders. This assists the vast majority of reputable companies by ensuring fair trading methods for everyone.</i></p><hr/><p>We carry out routine visits to traders, which takes into account the nature of 
  the business, past problems and the number of complaints received, thereby targeting 
  the problem traders where possible.</p><p>We investigates consumer complaints, where there might be a criminal breach, which 
  may involve visiting a trader.</p><p>In some cases we may consider 
  it necessary to take enforcement action as a result of problems found during 
  a routine visit or complaint in accordance with our enforcement policy. Where 
  possible the emphasis is placed on compliance through advice and assistance.</p><p>In many cases we find that 
  traders are not intentionally misleading the public, but are doing so due to 
  a lack of understanding of their legal obligations.</p><p> We are here to advise Consumers 
  and Businesses. We believe that by educating and informing traders of their 
  obligations many of the problems businesses encounter could be avoided, and 
  traders could benefit from good business practice.</p><p>In Trading Standards we 
  enforce numerous pieces of primary legislation, the most important ones being:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">The Trade 
      Descriptions Act - ensures that descriptions applied to goods or services 
      are accurate</li>
			<li title="*">The Consumer Protection 
      Act - covers the safety of goods and also is designed to ensure prices are 
      not misleading</li>
			<li title="*">The Consumer Credit 
      Act - promotes truth in lending</li>
			<li title="*">The Food Safety Act 
      - safeguards what we eat and drink </li>
			<li title="*">The Weights and Measures 
      Act - ensures we all receive the correct quantity when buying goods</li>
		</ul><p> If you are thinking of 
  starting a new business or are already running an existing one, are you confident 
  that you meet all the legal requirements of trading legislation? There is further 
  advice on the contractual and legal requirements of traders below.</p><h2>Are you a trader?</h2><p>Various laws concerning 
  the sale of goods govern how traders conduct their business. Some of these laws 
  still apply to persons who are not traders but sell goods.</p><p>
			<strong>When does the law 
  consider you to be a trader?</strong>
		</p><p>There is no hard and fast 
  rule, but ask yourself:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Are the 
      goods you are selling your personal property? If not and you buy goods in 
      specially to resell, for example from newspaper adverts or a cash and carry, 
      you are very likely to be a trader. </li>
			<li title="*">Do you attend boot 
      sales regularly - once every couple of months or more? If so, you are likely 
      to be a trader even if boot sales are not a major source of income.</li>
			<li title="*">Do you employ anyone 
      to help you with sales? If so, you are probably a trader.</li>
			<li title="*">Do you sell similar 
      goods at other venues, e.g. markets, in the street or from home? If so, 
      you are almost certainly a trader.</li>
		</ul><h2>Traders and The Law</h2><p>
			<strong>Business Names Act</strong> 
  - If you don't trade under your own name but as eg. &quot;Anytown Fruits&quot; 
  you must display clearly your name and address where legal documents could be 
  sent to you. </p><p>
			<strong> Consumer Protection 
  Act </strong>- Take great care that everything you sell is safe. Be particularly 
  careful with toys, electrical goods, upholstered furniture and clothing, especially 
  nightwear. </p><p>Where you show a price for 
  goods, it is an offence to charge a buyer more. It is also illegal to mislead 
  buyers in other ways about the price of goods, for example by using price comparisons 
  or 'sale' signs when the higher price you quote in comparisons is unfair or 
  meaningless. </p><p>
			<strong>Fair Trading Act 
  </strong>- It is an offence to display any sign which tries to limit a buyer's 
  rights. Do not use signs like 'No Refunds' or 'Sold as Seen'. As 
  well as being illegal, these signs do not, in fact, limit buyers' rights at 
  all. </p><p>
			<strong> Price Marking Order 
  </strong>- Traders must show a price in writing for all goods offered for sale. 
  This can be attached to the goods, or be placed adjacent to them. </p><p>
			<strong>Trade Descriptions 
  Act </strong>- Goods must not be misdescribed. Before selling recorded or branded 
  items such as cassettes, video films or t-shirts, satisfy yourself that they 
  are not counterfeit because heavy penalties can be imposed on anyone who breaches 
  copyright by selling fakes. </p><p>
			<strong>Video Recordings 
  Act </strong>- Selling video films is risky because the sale of films which 
  have not been properly classified by the British Board of Film Classification 
  can attract fines of up to &#xA3;20,000 per tape or a prison sentence. Certain 
  educational, sport and music videos are exempt from this requirement. You are 
  bly advised to take more detailed advice on the Video Recordings Act before 
  putting video films out for sale. </p><p>
			<strong>Sale and Supply 
  of Goods Act </strong>- If you sell something, whether new or second-hand, it 
  should be of satisfactory quality and fit for its purpose. It should also be 
  as you describe it. </p><p> If you sell something which 
  does not meet these requirements, your customer has a right to a refund provided 
  they reject goods promptly. S/he might agree to a replacement, but their right 
  is to a refund, and as a trader you should be ready to honour this right. If 
  you are selling something with defects, you can only escape your obligation 
  to provide a refund if you point out the fault at the time of the sale. Doing 
  this doesn't protect you from a claim if the item has further faults.</p><p>Unlike the other Acts mentioned, 
  you cannot be prosecuted by Trading Standards for breaking the Act, but you 
  could be sued by your customers.</p><h2>If You're Not A Trader</h2><p>If 
  you are a genuine 'non-trader' seller, you will be largely outside the controls 
  of consumer law, but there are exceptions: for example, if you describe goods 
  in any way, and that description proves to be false, you will be obliged to 
  give a refund.</p><p>There are things you can 
  do, however, which will help avoid problems and which we would recommend as 
  'good practice' during private sales.</p><p>
			<strong>Electrical Goods 
  </strong>- We advise consumers to steer clear of items such as electric fires 
  and irons at boot sales, so unless the item has a reputable, recent source we 
  would caution bly against its sale. </p><p>
			<strong>Clothes </strong>- 
  Think twice before selling nightwear. It might well not meet flammability requirements 
  that apply to nightwear sold by traders. Children's' coats with hood-cords can 
  also pose a hazard so beware of selling these if their source and safety is 
  uncertain. </p><p>
			<strong>Toys </strong>- 
  Look toys over to make sure there are no sharp points or small parts that can 
  be pulled off. Put the toy in a skip rather than a sale if it is in bad shape, 
  damaged or very old. If you still have packaging, sell the toy in it. </p><p>
			<strong>Other Danger Areas 
  </strong>- Caution should be exercised in the sale of the following types of 
  goods. All of them have their own safety standards when sold by traders and 
  you should have them checked carefully before you even think about selling them. 
  Prams and pushchairs. Paraffin heaters. Oil heaters. </p><p>Whether you are a regular 
  trader or not, you should be ready to co-operate with trading standards officers 
  who may visit boot sales at any time to carry out inspections, give advice and 
  investigate complaints.</p><p>You may wish to visit the 
  following websites that have a wide range of useful Business Advice leaflets 
  and information. </p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.hmso.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Her Majesty's Stationery Office (HMSO)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides full text of Acts of Parliament from 1988, plus access to Inforoute, 
      the Government's Information Asset Register.</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Department 
        for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
        Defra works for the essentials of life - water, food, air, land, people, 
        animals and plants</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/">Trading 
      Standards Central</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      A one stop shop for consumer protection information in the UK. Provides 
      information for businesses and consumers. </li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.hmce.gov.uk/">HM 
      Customs and Excise</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides information and advice for the public and for businesses.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/">Office 
      of Fair Trading (OFT)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      The OFT is designed with two purposes: to protect consumers and explain 
      their rights; and to ensure that businesses compete and operate fairly.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/">Department 
      of Trade and Industry (DTI)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Working with businesses, employees and consumers to drive up UK productivity 
      and competitiveness to deliver prosperity for all.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/">Food 
      Standards Agency (FSA)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      An independent food safety watchdog set up by an Act of Parliament in 2000 
      to protect the public's health and consumer interests in relation to food.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=401"> Providing Information
		(401)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
