<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=404}]"><cms:name>weights-and-measures-404</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Weights and Measures</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=404}]"><cms:name>weights-and-measures-404-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>weights, measures</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=404}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>All goods, whether pre-packed or not, should be of the correct weight or measure stated on the packaging or indicated on the premises</i></p><hr/><p> Part of our job is to ensure 
  that the public receive the correct amount of any product they buy. </p><p>Almost all goods today are 
  sold by some reference to either it's weight or measure, whether by the pint, 
  litre, gramme or metre. This includes everyday items such as bread, petrol, 
  beer, clothing material, sand or virtually anything else you can think of. Trading 
  Standards enforce a complex set of regulations designed to ensure that the public 
  and businesses can have confidence in their purchases and ensures fair competition. 
  We do this by:</p><ul>
<li title="*">Verifying that weighing 
      and measuring equipment is initially accurate </li>
      <li title="*">Routinely visiting 
      businesses and checking weighing and measuring equipment</li>
      <li title="*">Checking products already 
      in the shops</li>
      <li title="*">Reacting to complaints 
      of short measure</li>
</ul><p> A more in-depth view of 
  Weights and Measures legislation is given below.</p><p>If you think you have received 
  short measure from a business in <span class="gen">enter council name</span>, 
  would like further information or an information pack, please contact us.</p><h2>A review of weights and measures</h2><p> In the UK, it has been 
  estimated that goods to the value of a billion pounds are traded at retail level 
  by some form of measurement of their quantity. However, do consumers stop to 
  think why or how it is that they can have confidence in their purchases?</p><p>The law relating to weights 
  and measures today evolved so that:</p><ul>
<li title="*">security of uniform 
      system of units of weights and measures could be established;</li>
      <li title="*">controls could be placed 
      over weighing and measuring equipment in use for trade;</li>
      <li title="*">the public could be 
      protected against short quantity in the sale of goods.</li>
</ul><p> The system of weights and 
  measures has developed through:</p><ul>
<li title="*">legal frameworks</li>
  <li title="*">adequate and even handed 
      enforcement</li>
      <li title="*">technological advances 
      in equipment</li>
</ul><h2>There is a vast range of law governing 
  weights and measures; as technology, numbers and variety of goods have increased 
  so has legislation:</h2><p> Weighing originated as 
  man's first assessment of the weight of goods was the load his strength could 
  carry, length was determined in terms of parts of body: breadth of palm, arm's 
  length.</p><p>As things were made and 
  traded, more accurate means of measurement became necessary.</p><p>There is a system of traceability 
  in place to ensure that the kilogram and metre is the same throughout the nation. 
  The working standard weights and measures that Inspectors take out with them 
  to test weighing and measuring equipment are tested against local standards 
  that never leave the office. Weights are tested using equipment that the National 
  Weights and Measures Laboratory refer back to the copy of the international 
  prototype of the kilogram kept at their premises. The metre is defined by reference 
  to natural constant - the speed of light. It is therefore a more perfect reference. 
  All units are therefore defined by ultimate references to either the metre or 
  kilogram.</p><p>The National Weights and 
  Measures Laboratory examine patterns of weighing and measuring equipment (submitted 
  in the UK) to determine whether their design or manufacture is such to facilitate 
  fraud. Once such equipment has a certificate, it must conform to the pattern 
  and pass accuracy tests carried out by an Inspector. Once the equipment has 
  been verified or stamped by an Inspector it may be used for trade (this system 
  is known as verification). There is also a system of European Community approval 
  removing technical barriers to trade.</p><p>So, Inspectors of Weights 
  and Measures (or Trading Standards Officers as they are more commonly known) 
  visit trade premises and carry out inspections and verification of weighing 
  and measuring equipment. Examples include counter weighing machines, weighbridges, 
  weights, petrol pumps, spirit measuring instruments, wine and beer glasses, 
  metre measures to name some common examples. Prepacked goods, breads, textiles 
  etc., are tested to ensure correct weight or measure.</p><p>For further information 
  please contact us.</p><p>Other useful information 
  can be obtained from the following websites:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.hmso.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Her Majesty's Stationery Office (HMSO)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides full text of Acts of Parliament from 1988, plus access to Inforoute, 
      the Government's Information Asset Register.</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Department 
        for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
        Defra works for the essentials of life - water, food, air, land, people, 
        animals and plants</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/">Trading 
      Standards Central</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      A one stop shop for consumer protection information in the UK. Provides 
      information for businesses and consumers. </li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.hmce.gov.uk/">HM 
      Customs and Excise</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides information and advice for the public and for businesses.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/">Office 
      of Fair Trading (OFT)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      The OFT is designed with two purposes: to protect consumers and explain 
      their rights; and to ensure that businesses compete and operate fairly.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/">Department 
      of Trade and Industry (DTI)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Working with businesses, employees and consumers to drive up UK productivity 
      and competitiveness to deliver prosperity for all.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/">Food 
      Standards Agency (FSA)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      An independent food safety watchdog set up by an Act of Parliament in 2000 
      to protect the public's health and consumer interests in relation to food.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=404"> Providing Information
		(404)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
