<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=787}]"><cms:name>advice-to-consumers-787</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Advice to Consumers</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=787}]"><cms:name>advice-to-consumers-787-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>advice, consumers</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=787}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>When you buy goods from any business you have certain civil rights. </i></p><hr/><h2>What rights do 
  I have if I buy faulty goods?</h2><p> The goods must be:</p><ul>
<li title="*">must be 
      of 'satisfactory quality'. The goods must be free from defects except 
      when they have been brought to your attention</li>
      <li title="*">must be 'fit 
      for their purpose'. The product must be able to do what it was sold to do. 
      The product must also be able to do anything the seller says it will do. </li>
      <li title="*">must be 'as described' 
      on the package or display sign. If you buy a food product with a label stating 
      that it is 100% fat free, then that is what you should get.</li>
</ul><p> If the goods do not meet 
  these standards you are entitled to reject them and get your money back, if 
  the goods are returned within a &quot;reasonable&quot; period (normally a few 
  weeks). You do not have to accept a repair, a credit note or replacement (although 
  you may want to consider this if you've had the goods for some time).</p><p>You also have the right 
  to require the seller to repair or replace the goods within a reasonable time 
  and without causing you significant inconvenience. If this would be impossible 
  or disproportionate (eg. the cost of a repair would be more than you paid for 
  the item), or the retailer does not repair or replace without inconvenience 
  within a reasonable period you can require them to reduce the price of the goods 
  by an appropriate amount or rescind the contract.</p><p>Some retailers may argue 
  that any fault is a result of you damaging the goods in which case you would 
  need to prove that this is not the case, perhaps by obtaining an independent 
  expert opinion. Ultimately you might have to prove your case in Court. If you 
  had to pay for an expert opinion you can claim the cost of this as well as the 
  refund.</p><h2>What about services rather than 
  goods?</h2><p>When you purchase a service 
  such as having a car repaired or employing a builder to carry out some work, 
  you are legally entitled to certain minimum standards of service. The service 
  should be carried out:</p><ul>
<li title="*">with reasonable 
      care and skill </li>
      <li title="*">within a reasonable 
      time</li>
      <li title="*">for a reasonable price 
      - providing the cost was not agreed beforehand</li>
</ul><p> If these requirements are 
  not met, you may be able to sue the trader for compensation. Alternatively, 
  the person or organisation may be a member of a trade association or other professional 
  body to whom you can complain; be regulated; or have a Code of Practice which 
  they may have to abide by.</p><h2>The shop wants to carry out a repair 
  - What if they are still faulty?</h2><p>You 
  have the same rights as before you agreed to the repair - prior to having the 
  repair carried out, let the shop know you are reserving the right to reject 
  the goods if the repair is not carried out satisfactorily. You should give the 
  vendor a reasonable opportunity to repair goods - especially if the fault is 
  minor and the goods can be put into new condition.</p><h2>Do I need a receipt to get a refund? 
  </h2><p>Basically, the answer is 
  no but you will need another proof of purchase. This could be a bank statement 
  indicating the purchase, credit card counterfoil or even a witness who saw you 
  make the purchase. A receipt however is obviously the best proof of purchase 
  you can get so look after it until you are sure that the goods are okay.</p><h2>The goods I wanted were marked at 
  a low price but the shop refused to sell them to me. Can they do this? </h2><p>Yes. A shop is not required 
  to sell you anything, or at any price on display. They are making what's called 
  an 'invitation to treat', which can be withdrawn at any time. However, price 
  indications should not be misleading as it could be an offence under the Consumer 
  Protection Act 1987. If you think you are being mislead, you should report it 
  to Trading Standards.</p><h2>What if the shop tells me to 'get 
  lost'?</h2><p>If the shop ultimately refuses 
  to refund your money and you feel you have a good case you must take action 
  yourself. If the value you are claiming is less than &#xA3;5,000, you can use 
  the small claims procedure. This procedure is designed to be as simple and inexpensive 
  as possible. If the claim is over this amount, you can still take action to 
  recover the total claim through the County Courts.</p><p>It would be advisable to 
  seek advice first, either from the 
		<a href="http://www.nacab.org.uk/">
<strong>Citizens 
  Advice Bureau</strong>
</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>   or a Solicitor.</p><h2>What if someone else buys me a gift 
  and it's faulty?</h2><p>Strictly 
  speaking the contract for the sale of the goods is between the seller and the 
  purchaser, not you. Your friend will have to take the gift back. Generally, 
  most stores will deal with you if you have proof of purchase, out of goodwill.</p><h2>Are there any times when I will 
  not be entitled to my money back or to exchange the goods? 
  </h2><p>Yes:</p><ul>
<li title="*">If you 
      have held onto the goods for a long period of time, you may be deemed to 
      have 'accepted' them. </li>
<li title="*">If you were told about 
      any faults before you bought the goods.</li>
<li title="*">If you did the damage 
      yourself either by ignoring advice about using the goods or through lack 
      of care. </li>
<li title="*">If there is nothing 
      wrong with the goods and you have just changed your mind. (Some shops may 
      agree to accept the return of the goods as a gesture of goodwill).</li>
</ul><h2>What if I buy goods in a sale?</h2><p>If you buy goods in a sale 
  your statutory rights still apply, however if the shop draws specific defects 
  to your attention then you have no rights in relation to those defects. If there 
  are any signs stating no refunds, this should be reported to Trading Standards.</p><h2>Can I take secondhand goods back 
  if they are faulty?</h2><p>Yes, when you buy secondhand 
  goods you have the same rights as when you buy new, however you must remember 
  that you cannot expect the same quality or durability from secondhand goods, 
  and this must be taken into account.</p><h2>What rights do I have if I buy goods 
  from a private individual?</h2><p>Unfortunately, not many! 
  The Sale of Goods legislation does not apply, although if goods do not meet 
  the description given by the seller you may be able to take action for breach 
  of contract. You should be aware of traders who pretend to be private sellers 
  in order to avoid statutory liabilities, and if you suspect a private seller 
  is really a trader then Trading Standards should be contacted.</p><h2>Should I buy goods with a credit 
  card?</h2><p>Yes, if the goods cost between 
  &#xA3;100 and &#xA3;30,000 then the credit card company is equally liable 
  for any claim you have against the seller, which can be particularly useful 
  if the trader has gone out of business. You should first attempt to solve any 
  problems with the trader.</p><h2>I have bought something on credit. 
  Can I cancel it?</h2><p> You can usually only cancel 
  a credit agreement if it was made with the supplier in person (not over the 
  'phone), and if the agreement was signed 'off trade premises', for example if 
  it were signed at your home. The agreement will tell you whether you have a 
  right to cancel and how much time you have in which to do it.</p><h2>Can I get my money or deposit back 
  if I change my mind?</h2><p> No. Under the law a trader 
  only has to refund your money if the goods are faulty or not as described. You 
  have entered into a contract, and if you have just changed your mind and want 
  your money back the shop is under no legal obligation to refund it to you.</p><p>As a matter of company policy 
  and to retain customer goodwill many traders will let you exchange items or 
  offer a credit note, but they are not obliged to.</p><p>Similarly, if you have left 
  a deposit you are agreeing to a contract and unless it is stated on your receipt, 
  or on a notice in the store, it is not refundable unless the store is unable 
  to fulfil it's part of the contract. </p><h2>It's broken and the Guarantee has 
  just expired. What are my rights?</h2><p> When you purchased the 
  goods you entered into a contract with the Retailer not the Manufacturer. This 
  contract is governed by the Sale of Goods Act 1979 (as amended) which says that 
  you are entitled to expect the goods to be of &quot;satisfactory quality&quot;. 
  This means they should not be faulty or unsafe, and be reasonably durable etc. 
  The Act gives you rights for up to 6 years.</p><p>You can claim &quot;reasonable 
  compensation&quot; which is usually the cost of a repair (or the goods being 
  repaired by the retailer).</p><p>However, the retailer may 
  argue that any fault is a result of fair wear and tear in which case you would 
  need to prove that it is not, perhaps by obtaining an independent expert opinion. 
  Ultimately you might have to prove your case in Court. If you had to pay for 
  an expert opinion you can claim the cost of this as well as the refund.</p><h2>I have received a gift but it's 
  faulty. What are my rights?</h2><p> Historically, as the contract 
  for the sale of the goods is between the seller and the purchaser, only the 
  purchaser could exercise Rights in respect of faulty goods. Most stores will 
  deal with the receiver of a gift, if they have proof of purchase, out of goodwill.</p><p>A recent change in the law 
  has said that third parties, clearly identified at the time of sale, will have 
  Rights under the contract too. Therefore if you purchase a gift you should let 
  the seller know at the time of purchase, telling them the name of the receiver 
  of the gift. If possible, get the fact you have advised them acknowledged in 
  writing, perhaps by getting an appropriate note written on the receipt.</p><h2>The goods I ordered are late arriving. 
  What can I do?</h2><p> Traders are only required 
  to deliver goods within a &quot;reasonable&quot; time so it would be necessary 
  to take the matter to court to decide whether the time that has elapsed is unreasonable. 
  If it is the contract to purchase can be cancelled.</p><p>If you feel an unreasonable 
  time has passed you should &quot;make time of the essence&quot; by writing to 
  the company, quoting a fixed date by which time delivery should take place. 
  If this period elapses you would then be entitled to cancel the contract provided 
  you yourself have set a reasonable time limit (eg. don't write and demand delivery 
  the next day!).</p><p>You can of course avoid 
  the latter stage by making &quot;time of the essence&quot; when you originally 
  make the purchase.</p><h2>How can I find out about complaints 
  about a service or goods supplied by a private company? </h2><p>You 
  have basic legal rights when you buy goods or services. The acts of parliament 
  that cover your rights when you are buying goods or a service are the Sale of 
  Goods Act 1979 and the Supply of Goods and Services Act 1982.</p><h2>How can you help me?</h2><p>We may be able to give you 
  free advice on how to complain. We can also investigate false or misleading 
  descriptions or prices.</p><h2>What does the service do? </h2><ul>
<li title="*">We enforce a wide range 
      of legislation to protect consumers and honest traders</li>
<li title="*">We enforce laws covering 
      the quality, quantity, safety, price, description of good and services e.g. 
      short measure beer, unsafe toys, falsely described holidays and &quot;clocked&quot; cars.</li>
<li title="*">We enforce laws to 
      prevent children buying cigarettes and fireworks</li>
<li title="*">We investigate complaints 
      from the public about traders</li>
<li title="*">We advise consumers 
      and traders about their right and obligations e.g. refunds for faulty goods</li>
<li title="*">We visit trade premises 
      and projects to make sure they keep to the law</li>
<li title="*">Where appropriate, 
      we warn or prosecute traders</li>
      <li title="*">We also administer 
      street trading and markets. We give a range of licences including entertainment, 
      night cafes and fireworks. We deal with food premises, health and safety 
      and infectious diseases.</li>
</ul><h2>How can I help you?</h2><ul>
<li title="*">When you contact us, 
      have all your paperwork with you, which is relevant to the issue you are 
      enquiring about</li>
<li title="*">Keep all original documents 
      and items in a safe place in case they are need in future</li>
<li title="*">If you write to us, 
      please give us your daytime phone number, if you have one</li>
<li title="*">If you reply to our 
      letters, please use our reference number</li>
<li title="*">Please let us know 
      about any developments in your case</li>
</ul><h2>How can you contact us?</h2><p>By using the contact details at the top of this page. </p><h2>Who else can help me?</h2><p>If the company is a member 
  of a trade association, they are likely to set service standards. You should 
  contact them - they may run a mediation service.</p><p>You may also contact your 
  local 
		<a href="http://www.nacab.org.uk/">
<strong>Citizens Advice Bureau</strong>
</a>	 
  .<span class="gen">link to external website</span> They can help 
  you on shopping problems. They can also advise you about how to take court action.</p><p>You may also find the following 
  websites useful:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.hmso.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Her Majesty's Stationery Office (HMSO)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides full text of Acts of Parliament from 1988, plus access to Inforoute, 
      the Government's Information Asset Register.</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="http://www.defra.gov.uk/">
					<strong>Department 
        for Environment, Food and Rural Affairs (Defra)</strong>
				</a>	
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
        Defra works for the essentials of life - water, food, air, land, people, 
        animals and plants</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.tradingstandards.gov.uk/">Trading 
      Standards Central</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      A one stop shop for consumer protection information in the UK. Provides 
      information for businesses and consumers. </li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.hmce.gov.uk/">HM 
      Customs and Excise</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Provides information and advice for the public and for businesses.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.oft.gov.uk/">Office 
      of Fair Trading (OFT)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      The OFT is designed with two purposes: to protect consumers and explain 
      their rights; and to ensure that businesses compete and operate fairly.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/">Department 
      of Trade and Industry (DTI)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      Working with businesses, employees and consumers to drive up UK productivity 
      and competitiveness to deliver prosperity for all.</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>
					
		<a href="http://www.fsa.gov.uk/">Food 
      Standards Agency (FSA)</a>	
				</strong>
				<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
				<br/>
      An independent food safety watchdog set up by an Act of Parliament in 2000 
      to protect the public's health and consumer interests in relation to food.</li>
		</ul><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=787"> Providing Information
		(787)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
