<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=367}]"><cms:name>census-information-367</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Census information</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=367}]"><cms:name>census-information-367-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>census, information</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=367}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Miscellaneous</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Census is a count of all people and households and is the most complete source of information about the population that we have. The latest Census was held on Sunday 29 April 2001.
</i></p><hr/><p>A copy of the Census form, with all the questions that were asked, can be found at 
		<a href="http://www.statistics.gov.uk/census2001/censusform.asp">www.statistics.gov.uk/census2001/censusform.asp </a>	
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><h2>Why is the Census important? </h2><p>  The Census is important because it allows central and local Government, health authorities and many other organisations to target their resources more effectively and to plan housing, education, health and transport services for years to come. </p><p>  For the first time central Government will make information freely available to the public on the internet. </p><h2>  Confidentiality </h2><p>  Information on individual people is not released to any organisation. </p><p>  The confidentiality of personal information is of paramount importance. Disclosure of personal Census information is an offence. The Office for National Statistics have processed the Census forms in secure conditions. Paper copies will be destroyed. Digital images of individual responses will only be made public after 100 years. </p><p>  Measures are also taken to prevent inadvertent disclosure of information about individuals through the statistical results. For example, information will not be released for areas containing fewer than 100 households. </p><h2>  Warnings </h2><p>  There are a number of changes to the 2001 Census that all users should be aware of if they wish to compare results with those of the 1991 Census. </p><ul>
			<li title="*">2001 is the first Census that has made adjustments for &quot;missing&quot; people.</li>
			<li title="*">It will include students at their term time address - last time they were included at their home address.</li>
		</ul><p>There will be new information on relationships within households, the lowest floor level of accommodation, unpaid personal care and religion. </p><p>  There will be no information on income, but there will be information on socio-economic group. There is no information on disability, but there will be information on limiting long term illnesses and general health over the past year. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=367"> Providing Information
		(367)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
