<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=229}]"><cms:name>shared-care-229</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Shared Care</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=229}]"><cms:name>shared-care-229-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>shared, care</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=229}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Shared Care offers short term care to adults with a learning disability and the people who care for them. </i></p><hr/><p>The care can vary in length from a few hours up to a maximum of two weeks at a time and is provided by people approved by Social Services to be Shared Carers.</p><p>Shared Carers are supported by a social worker who aims to make sure all arrangements run smoothly.</p><h3> How Shared Care could work for you</h3><p>If your assessed needs include shared care, you will be linked with a shared carer who can offer planned, flexible support either by:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">welcoming the person with a learning disability into their home for a day, an occasional week-end or a longer stay or</li>
			<li title="*">going out with them on day trips, visits and leisure activities or</li>
			<li title="*">sitting with the person in their own home to enable the main carer(s) to go out</li>
		</ul><h3>What it might it cost?</h3><p>If you receive overnight stays you will be charged for the shared care provided. There is a financial assessment to work out how much you will have to pay for any activities arranged during the care break. The shared carer receives a small payment for providing 
  the care which varies according to the amount of time involved.</p><h3>Who are Shared Carers?</h3><p>Shared Carers can be people from a variety of backgrounds who have an interest in supporting people who have a learning disability.</p><p> Shared Carers might be single, married, or living with a partner: with or without children.</p><p>Social Services recruits and supports Shared Carers by:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">carefully assessing their suitability, making police and health checks and taking up personal references</li>
			<li title="*">providing training on a variety of topics including disability awareness and health and safety issues</li>
			<li title="*">keeping in regular contact by telephone calls, home visits and through newsletters</li>
		</ul><h3>More about Shared Care</h3><p>If you think you need the support shared care can offer contact Social Services, using the details above. A social worker will arrange to visit you to talk about your situation and make an assessment of your needs. Your carers' needs will also be taken into account.</p><p> If shared care can meet your assessed needs and the eligibility criteria, you will be introduced to a suitable Shared Carer, subject to availability.</p><p>You will then be given the opportunity to get to know each other at a pace that suits all those involved.</p><p>The social worker will arrange regular reviews of the Shared Care to make sure the service meets your needs.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=229"> Providing Information
		(229)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
