<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=230}]"><cms:name>sheltered-and-supported-housing-230</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Sheltered and Supported Housing</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=230}]"><cms:name>sheltered-and-supported-housing-230-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>sheltered, supported, housing</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=230}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Social Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Sheltered housing is a flat or bungalow especially designed and built with the needs of elderly people in mind. </i></p><hr/><h3>Who can Apply for Sheltered Housing?</h3><p>Any person of pensionable age who feels the need for some support. The Council's main responsibility is towards applicants who currently live within the Council's boundaries. Your application will also be considered if you used to live in the Council area, or if you have relatives who currently live here. If you do not have any connection with this area, you may still register as, from time to time, it is possible to allocate sheltered housing to those who wish to live in this area.</p><h3>How Do I Apply?</h3><p>This can be done in person (or someone else can do it for you, like a friend or social worker) by writing to the:	</p><p>
			<span class="gen">enter details.</span> Alternatively, you may prefer to telephone direct to the Housing Services Section</p><p>If you are already in the Council's Housing register you can simply request a revision form and indicate on it that you are interested in being considered for sheltered housing.</p><h3>What Will Happen When I Apply?</h3><p>Once your application has been accepted onto our housing register, it is awarded a number of points to reflect the conditions in which you live. Points are given for factors such as medical conditions, overcrowding and lack of modern facilities, as well as length of time on the housing register. The total points score of each applicant is then used as a guide in allocating properties. Whenever possible a housing officer will visit you in your own home to discuss your situation and talk to you about where you would like to live.</p><p>Your application from housing will be given every consideration and an offer of sheltered housing will be made when possible. This may not happen quickly and the Council's 
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=313">
				<strong>Community Alarm Service</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to pid 313</span> may bring peace of mind to you and your family in the mean time.</p><p>For more information about this service contact <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span>
		</p><h3>If I am Allocated a Sheltered Dwelling, What Then?</h3><p>Any offer of accommodation will be confirmed in writing. Should you wish to view the scheme and meet the warden this can be easily arranged.</p><p>Once you have signed the tenancy acceptance form you will enjoy all the rights and privileges of a secure tenant.
			</p><p>You will also have a secure tenant's responsibilities, paying your own rent, running your home and providing your own meals. You may be eligible for Housing Benefit to help towards your rent. Please contact the Housing Benefit Section <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span> for more details.</p><p>You are expected, with the help of your friends and relatives, to make your own arrangements for moving in, and to meet the cost of doing so - just like any other house move. You must also arrange for an electricity supply by applying to <span class="gen">enter company name</span>in the normal way. You may be asked to move in at short notice, possibly two weeks, although we do try to give as much advance notice as possible.</p><p>What this means is that you will keep; and for as long as possible be encouraged to maintain, your own independence. In sheltered housing you will not be a resident in an old people's home and you will be free at all times to come and go as you please. You are simply asked to let the warden know if you intend to be away overnight or if you will not be there at then time of the normal daily rounds when the warden calls regularly each morning.</p><h3>When is the Warden on Duty?</h3><p>Wardens work <span class="gen">enter details.</span>
		</p><p>Just like other members of staff, wardens are allowed time off for holidays. If they are unwell it is usually possible to arrange temporary cover.</p><p>Whenever the warden is off duty, unavailable, or away from the scheme and not being covered by a deputy, the alarm system is switched to the community alarm scheme, otherwise known as the central control office, where an operator will talk to you if you call for assistance.</p><h3>Does the Warden Hold Information About Me?</h3><p>Yes, the names, addressed and telephone numbers of your next-of-kin and close friends, your doctor and any relevant details of your health are kept by the warden, and the central control office. This is a confidential record and its purpose is to enable contact to be made with the appropriate person in the event of illness or an accident, or any other problem.</p><h3>What is the Warden's Role?</h3><p>Wardens are practical and understanding people, sympathetic to the problems of ageing. They are carefully recruited and trained to encourage you to look after yourself and to lead an active independent life. When on duty the warden's primary task is to respond to an emergency as quickly and efficiently as possible, so that in the event of an illness or a fall, or some other crisis, you can quickly get help.</p><p>In an emergency, it is the warden's job to take the first action. It may be something that can easily be put right there and then; if not the warden may have to call your relatives, your doctor; or other professional help that may be needed.</p><p>If you need home care services, meals on wheels or special household aids, the warden will try to help you obtain 
  them by contacting the local Social Services office for you. The duty warden will normally call on you once a day to ensure you are alright.</p><p>If you are unwell or in need of urgent assistance when a Warden is unavailable, a person at Central Control will contact a member of your family or a friend to visit you. If it is an emergency and you are in need of urgent assistance, they will quickly arrange this.</p><p>At Category II schemes the warden on duty will hold a pass key to open you door; but it is only used in an emergency or with your clear permission. Otherwise, no warden may enter your home unless you invite him or her to do so. At Category I schemes the warden will only hold keys at the tenant's request.</p><h3>Are There Things a Warden Does Not Do?</h3><p>Wardens are not employed to perform duties for which statutory or voluntary bodies exist, or which are the responsibility of relatives living nearby.</p><p>Wardens are not nurses - if you need regular medical treatment your doctor can arrange for you to have visits from a community Nurse. Neither are wardens permitted to administer drugs and medicines. Wardens are not there to do domestic chores such as cleaning, cooking, providing meals and shopping. They may help for residents to do these things for themselves, or to make arrangements. There is a strict instruction that wardens cannot look after you money valuables and money.</p><p>A warden may carry out some of these tasks on a purely temporary basis, as part of an emergency response. But he or she can only be expected to do so for a limited time until help is available from other sources. It is important to remember that generally only one warden is on duty at any one time and there are many other people in the scheme for whom the warden must offer a similar service.</p><h3>How Do I Contact the Warden in an Emergency?</h3><p>Each scheme is equipped with a modern warden alarm system. All you need to do is to pull one of the special alarm cords or press the button on your pendant alarm and the warden will speak to you. You need only to pull the cord, or press the button once and when the warden answers you can say what is wrong from wherever you are in your bungalow or flat. If you cannot speak you can be assured the warden will come quickly to see what has happened. The same applies if you have a mishap in one of the communal areas.</p><h3>What if the Warden is Away?</h3><p>If the warden is away at any time then the scheme alarm is switched to central control. In that case, an operator will, if they deem it necessary, call your doctor; relatives or friends to help you will answer your call.</p><h3>What is Contact Care?</h3><p>The Council has set up an alarm system to help any elderly and disabled people within the area who feel they need to be able to contact someone quickly in an emergency.</p><p>Most sheltered housing schemes are connected to the contact care; so whenever the warden is away, a single pull on your alarm cord will bring help.</p><p>Also anyone living in the area can have an alarm if they need one and it will be connected to contact care control where specially trained operators are on duty day and night throughout the year. There is always someone there to answer calls.</p><h3>Is There a Scheme Doctor?</h3><p>No. Each tenant has his or her own doctor. Of course if your are moving into the area you may have to change your present arrangements, but it is up to you which local doctors list you apply to join.</p><h3>What Other Facilities are Available?</h3><p>There is a pay-phone in the communal areas of some schemes. It is entirely up to residents whether or not they have a private telephone in their home. The tenant would be responsible for its cost.</p><p>Most schemes do not have a communal television set. However, if you have your own television you may qualify for a Concessionary Licence Fee. The warden will advise you if this is the case.</p><p>In most schemes you will be responsible for all internal decoration and cleaning, including your windows, although the outside of your windows will be cleaned by Council contractors. External decoration is the landlord's responsibility and will be done by this Council on a regular programme. The landscaped areas are also cared for by this Council. In some locations it is possible for tenants to have a small area of garden to tend outside their flat or bungalow, but please check with the warden first.</p><p>The Council is also responsible for most repairs to the property which should be reported to us on <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span> as soon as they are noticed. If a resident cannot report them themselves the warden will do it fro them.</p><h3>Who Will Pay My Rent?</h3><p>You are responsible for paying your rent.</p><p>You can pay your rent at:</p><p>
			<span class="gen">enter details</span>
		</p><p>You may be eligible for help to pay your rent. For further information contact the Housing Benefits Section on <span class="gen">enter telephone number.</span>
		</p><h3>How Secure is my Sheltered Home?</h3><p>The Council maintains its sheltered accommodation to very high standards. The doors are fitted with good quality locks.</p><p>Some people like to fix additional locks or chains, but you must be aware that by doing this they may keep the warden out in an emergency. The master key, when it has to be used, will open you door and admit the warden, but he or she cannot get in quickly to help you if there are other locks and chains on the door and you cannot release them yourself.</p><p>The warden-call alarm is there and should be used without hesitation if you are at all suspicious of anyone trying to gain admission to your home.</p><p>Legitimate callers and all Council visitors carry official identification. You should always ask to see this and check it carefully before admitting anyone you do not know.</p><p>
			<strong>Remember: If in doubt - do not open your door, pull the cord!</strong>
		</p><h3>Can I Keep a Pet?</h3><p>As a general rule, permission should be sought for a pet other than a caged bird such as a budgerigar. If you have a well behaved small dog or cat you may be able to bring it with you should you move to a sheltered bungalow with its own access 
  to the outside.</p><p>However, if you are going to a sheltered flat with an access corridor shared with your neighbour, conditions are not considered suitable for a dog or cat and if, you have one, you should make other arrangements for it before moving. If you have a pet it is your responsibility and you must make arrangements to have it adequately cared for if you go away or become ill. The warden will not look after your pet for you.</p><h3>Can I Invite Guests to Stay from Time to Time?</h3><p>At most schemes we are able to offer guest room accommodation to relatives and friends of sheltered housing tenants. There is a small charge for each night and short term facilities such as tea making and possible use of the laundry (if available) are provided.</p><p>If you would like to have details of the nearest scheme with a guest room please ask your warden who can make the necessary arrangements for booking.</p><h3>What Happens in the Communal Lounge?</h3><p>To some extent it is up to you. Tenants use the room for meetings, clubs, social and recreational activities, or just to meet up for a cup of tea and a chat. It is up to you and your neighbours to decide what you want and to arrange it if you wish. The wardens are willing to help in this and to encourage a wide range of activities and outings.</p><p>All schemes are encouraged to invite the elderly neighbours living outside sheltered housing to events in the communal lounge.</p><p>Most schemes have an Amenity Fund which is used to help pay for social occasions like parties and outings. Most of the money in the fund comes from various money raising activities in which you may wish to take part.</p><h3>Is My Dwelling Covered by Insurance?</h3><p>Insurance of buildings is, of course, the responsibility of the landlord. But you are solely responsible for insuring your household contents and possessions and you are strongly advised to take out household contents and insurance.</p><h3>What If I Want to Move?</h3><p>Again, it is your home. Like any other secure tenant you can give 28 days notice to terminate your tenancy and move out if you so wish. There may be a good reason why you wish to move to another Council dwelling. If so the Housing Services Section will try to help you through its Transfer Register, or if it is to another Council area through the Homes Nomination Scheme. However, because of difficulties of availability a swift move may prove difficult.</p><p>If you are living as a couple and one of you dies, the surviving partner will not be required to move, even if your dwelling is designed for two people. However, if the surviving partner is below pensionable age or if the accommodation is specifically designed for a disabled person and the surviving partner does not need those facilities, the Council may offer suitable alternative accommodation.</p><h3>What if I am Dissatisfied with the Sheltered Housing Service?</h3><p>If you are dissatisfied with the service you, should, in the firs instance, talk to the warden who may be able to put matters right there and then, if it is a more serious matter, the Housing Assistant (Sheltered Housing) who should regularly visit each scheme. Part of her / his job is to see the scheme runs smoothly in line with the Council's policies and you can arrange to see him or her at any time. The warden can help you to do this.</p><p>If you are still not satisfied you can write to the:	</p><p>
			<span class="gen">enter details</span>
		</p><p>where you could ask for your complaint to be investigated at a senior level.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=230"> Providing Information
		(230)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
