<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=630}]"><cms:name>education-1-630</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Complaints Procedures - something that has happened at school</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=630}]"><cms:name>education-1-630-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>complaints, procedure, something, happened, school</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=630}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Complaints about a school</i></p><hr/><p>All the schools in <span class="gen">enter council name</span> want their children to do well and be happy. They recognise that 
  you as a parent/guardian play an important part in making this happen. Therefore, 
  schools aim to provide as many opportunities to keep you informed and involved in 
  your child's progress as they possibly can. Regular reports, open days and visits 
  all helping the process. Questions and concerns are usually dealt with quickly and 
  helpfully.</p><p>However, we recognise there are time when things go wrong, when 
  concerns continue and differences of opinion develop. These can usually be resolved 
  by speaking to the right person. Most concerns can be settled without too much trouble, 
  but whatever the issue, even where you are seriously concerned about your child's 
  future at the school, it's always important to try to find an answer. Disruption 
  to a child's education would be the most damaging result of all.</p><h4>What to do first</h4><p>Take a few minutes to read this page. Then think the complaint 
  through</p><p>
				<strong>What actually happened?</strong>
			</p><p>Remember there is often more than one view about an incident 
  or situation. For example, your child may well be telling the truth but it may not 
  be the whole story.</p><p>
				<strong>What do you want to complain about?</strong>
			</p><p>What do you hope will happen as a result of your complaint? 
  It might help to talk this through with a friend or relative.</p><p>When you make a complaint, remember that although you want to 
  change a situation, you want it to end on a positive note with no bad feelings. 
  In order to do this you should try to follow the procedures carefully and always 
  try not to put yourself or anyone else into a corner.</p><p>
				<strong>What to do next</strong>
			</p><p>When you are clear in your own mind as to what you believe has 
  happened, you then need to speak to someone at the school. Contact the Headteacher 
  to arrange such a meeting.</p><p>Although some schools, particularly for younger children, can 
  arrange to see parents who just 'pop in', this is not generally possible. 
  It is always best to try to make an appointment where you can sit and talk things 
  through calmly and without interruption. Investigating complaints does take time 
  and the answers aren't always readily available, but you will at least be able to 
  decide whether the action taken (or not taken) was reasonable and whether any further 
  steps taken by the teacher would solve the problem.</p><p>
				<strong>If you are still unhappy</strong>
			</p><p>In most cases, the problem will have been solved by this stage. 
  However, if you are still unhappy, then you should contact the Chair of Governors. 
  The school will tell you how to make contact with this person who may help to resolve 
  the problem informally, possibly by arranging a meeting between those involved. 
  Once again you'll have the opportunity to talk through your concerns with an independent 
  party who is there to listen and to discuss what is being said. If, after this, 
  you are still not satisfied with the answer, then you should ask to make a formal 
  complaint to the Governing Body.</p><p>
				<strong>Complaints to the Governing Body</strong>
			</p><p>As this is a serious step to take, it is important that you 
  have thought things through carefully and that every possible attempt has been made 
  to solve your concerns by other means.</p><p>Normally, a panel of governors will be called to hear your case 
  and all sides will be asked to submit a written statement. You will also be invited 
  to attend any hearing that is held, to present your side of the story.</p><p>The decision of the governors' panel will then be sent in writing 
  to all parties. </p><p>
				<strong>If you are still unhappy...</strong>
			</p><p>If after the Governors have dealt with your complaints, you 
  are still unhappy with the decision that was taken, you can contact us for advice 
  on what to do next. For example, if you feel that the Governing Body has acted unreasonably, 
  you can consider complaining to the Secretary of State for Education.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=630"> Providing Information
		(630)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
