<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=11}]"><cms:name>education-2-11</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Special educational needs (SEN) - disabled students allowance</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=11}]"><cms:name>education-2-11-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Student</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>special, educational, needs, disabled, students, allowance</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=11}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>These allowances are intended to assist students with disabilities to benefit as fully as possible from their course. They are designed to cover special equipment, non-medical helpers and other general expenses.</i></p><hr/><p>Assistance with travel costs can be given under certain circumstances. 
  Some important notes on how to claim the Disabled Students' Allowance are included 
  at the end of this section.</p><p>Remember, these allowances are not means-tested.</p><h4>Special Equipment Allowance </h4><p>This allowance covers major items of equipment, the need for 
  which arises from a disability, and which are necessary to enable a student to benefit 
  fully from the course. It is payable at any time during the course, by one or more 
  instalments, provided that the aggregated total of the payments does not exceed 
  the maximum prescribed limit of &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span>
  for the course. If it is more economical, items of equipment should be leased rather 
  than purchased, especially if the claim is made during the latter stages of the 
  course. Disabled students may find <strong>

		<a href="http://www.abilitynet.org.uk/content/home.htm">AbilityNet</a>	
</strong>, <span class="gen">link to external website</span> an external site, of use and interest. 
  It provides impartial, expert advice about computer technology for people with disabilities.</p><h4>Non-Medical Personal Helper's Allowance</h4><p>This allowance reimburses students up to a maximum of &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span> per annum for expenditure 
  on personal helpers such as readers, lip speakers, note takers, non-medical carers, 
  necessary for the student to benefit fully from the course. The authority must be 
  satisfied that the expenses are in respect the student's disability, and arise as 
  a direct consequence of attendance on the course. The provision of these allowances 
  does not remove the duty of local Social Services to provide assistance 
  towards personal care costs which would have been incurred irrespective of a student's 
  attendance on a course.</p><h4>General Disability Allowance</h4><p>This allowance has a maximum of &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span> per annum and provides for supplementary payments for disability 
  related expenditure incurred because of attendance on the course. The allowance 
  may be used for miscellaneous expenditure not covered by the specific allowances 
  and to supplement expenditure on non-medical helpers and/or special equipment in 
  excess of the maxima of the specific allowances.</p><h4>Travel for Disabled Students</h4><p>Reimbursement of travel expenses may also be claimed if, by 
  reason of your disability, you incur additional expenditure. You will be asked to 
  show how your disability incurs additional cost, and to provide medical evidence 
  if necessary.</p><p>Notes On Claiming A Disabled Students' Allowance:</p><li title="*">Although they form part of Student Support in Higher Education, these allowances 
    are not means-tested.</li><li title="*">Items purchased under this provision become your own property. If you withdraw 
    from your course prematurely, however, you may be asked to repay part of the cost.</li><li title="*">Payment can be considered only for costs arising from attendance and from the 
    disability - not for expenditure which would have been incurred irrespective of 
    whether you were a student.</li><li title="*">We strongly recommend that suitable insurance is obtained. In the case of theft 
    or damage (however caused) we will not contribute towards the cost of repairs 
    or replacement. Reasonable insurance cover may be reimbursed under the Special 
    Equipment Allowance. For a small cost, it may be possible to add this equipment 
    to your own or your parent's all risks/extra cover home insurance policy.</li><li title="*">You should discuss your needs with your Course Tutor/ Head of Department or 
    College Disability Officer who must write in support of your claim. The letter 
    must confirm the nature and extent of your disability and the cost (excluding 
    VAT) together with the make, model and exact specification of the necessary equipment, 
    if appropriate. If your college is unable to provide this information, they may 
    refer you to an independent Access Centre for an assessment of your disability 
    related needs. The cost of this assessment will be met from the disabled students' 
    allowance.</li><li title="*">These allowances are intended to assist individual students and not to defray 
    the running and pastoral costs of colleges. This should be explained to your college 
    when your requirements are discussed.</li><li title="*">We will also require an assessment of the disability by a suitably qualified 
    person or body, such as an Educational Psychologist in the case of dyslexia. NB 
    The cost of this medical assessment cannot be met from the Disabled Students' 
    Allowance. This is not the assessment referred to in 5 above which is related 
    to your needs. The medical assessment will refer to the nature of your disability.</li><li title="*">It is likely that our own suppliers will be able to obtain any equipment on 
    your behalf. If this is the case, an order will be placed and the equipment delivered 
    to you.</li><li title="*">For security reasons, we will not deliver to a private address other than your 
    usual permanent address. If this is not suitable, you should arrange with your 
    college where the delivery can be made. A university/college department or faculty, 
    or warden of a hall of residence would be appropriate.</li><li title="*">When making an application for a Disabled Students' Allowance, please state 
    to whom and where the equipment should be delivered including a daytime contact 
    telephone number and ensure that they will take responsibility for the equipment 
    upon receipt. We will take no responsibility for loss after delivery.</li><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=11"> Providing Information
		(11)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
