<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=19}]"><cms:name>education-1-19</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Childcare arrangements - after and/or before school childcare</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=19}]"><cms:name>education-1-19-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>childcare, arrangements, after, before, school</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=19}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Out of school services are for school-age children to play and learn and have fun in groups.</i></p><hr/><p>They are usually based in or near schools and more are being 
  set up to help families where parents work. Out of school services can be registered 
  with the local authority and inspected each year. They are run outside school hours 
  by a team of staff, usually called playworkers. Activities should be planned to 
  help children learn, play and relax with their friends. Playworkers will often pick 
  children up from local schools. There are different types of out of school services 
  so look around to find one that suits you and your child.</p><p>
				<strong>Positives</strong>
			</p><ul>
				<li title="*">children can learn, relax after school and have fun with their friends</li>
				<li title="*">geared to the needs of children with working parents </li>
			</ul><h4>What are the different types of out of school service?</h4><ul>
				<li title="*">Breakfast clubs - open in the mornings before school so children can enjoy breakfast 
    there</li>
				<li title="*">After school clubs - open in the afternoons between <span class="gen">enter opening times</span>
				</li>
				<li title="*">Holiday playschemes - open during school holidays between  <span class="gen">enter opening times</span>
</li>
				
				<li title="*">Out of school services are also sometimes called kids' clubs.</li>
			</ul><h4>How do I know my child will be safe and secure?</h4><p>First of all you know your child best - look for an out of school 
  service you feel will be suitable for your child. Out of school services registered 
  with Ofsted Early Years are checked to make sure the staff are suitable to look 
  after children. At least half of them must be trained and there are rules on the 
  ratio of staff to children depending on the ages of the children catered for. A 
  check is also done on the premises of the out of school service to ensure it is 
  safe and suitable for children. After the out of school service is registered an 
  annual inspection is carried out to ensure a safe and suitable service is being 
  provided. Some out of school services do not currently need to be registered, for 
  example, those which only cater for children aged over eight. You can ask if they 
  are registered.</p><h4>How many children will there be?</h4><p>Most out of school services provide places for between 10 and 
  40 children although some are smaller and others are larger.</p><h4>What age range of children will be there?</h4><p>Most children attending out of school services are aged between 
  5 and 11. Some services provide places for three and four year olds to fit around 
  nursery or pre-school education. Some services provide places geared for older children 
  aged 10-14.</p><h4>When will services be open?</h4><p>Out of school services can open before school and care for children 
  after school until about 6pm.</p><p>During the school holidays they are likely to be open between 
<span class="gen">enter opening times</span>
			</p><h4>What about part-time childcare?</h4><p>Many out of school services will be happy to offer you part-time 
  childcare. You may need to book regular sessions to make sure a place is available 
  when you need it.</p><h4>How much will it cost?</h4><p>You can expect to pay between <span class="gen">enter amount</span> per child per week for an after school childcare 
  place and <span class="gen">enter amount</span>
  per child per week for a place at a holiday playscheme.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=19"> Providing Information
		(19)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
