<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=20}]"><cms:name>education-1-20</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Childcare arrangements - childminding</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=20}]"><cms:name>education-1-20-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>childcare, arrangements, childminding</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=20}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A childminder is a man or woman who looks after children from 
  birth to eight years, in his/her own home, for more than two hours a day, and receives 
  a reward for this service. This does not apply if the child is a close relative 
  i.e. grandchild, niece or nephew.</i></p><hr/><p>
				Childminders are required to register with the local authority 
  under the Children Act 1989. They must meet specified standards relating to their 
  suitability as carers of children, the safety of premises and facilities, insurance, 
  and record keeping, and checks are made on all members of the household over the 
  age of 16 yrs. to several agencies. Childminders are inspected every year. 
			</p><h2>
			How many children may childminders look after?
			</h2><p>
				The Children Act 1989 limits the number of children under 8yrs. 
  in the care of childminders at any one time to 6 children, this includes the childminders 
  own children. A childminder may not mind more than 3 children under 5yrs. The certificate 
  will state how many children a childminder will care for. </p><ul>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#1">How do you find a childminder?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#2">How do you choose a childminder?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#3">Some points to consider</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#4">How do you settle your child 
      with a childminder?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#5">How much do childminders charge?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#6">Contracts</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#7">Do you have to take anything 
      to the childminders?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#8">What other information will 
      the childminder need?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#9">What happens if your child 
      is ill?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#10">What happens if the childminder is ill?</a>	
			</li>
			<li title="*">
				
		<a href="#11">What do you do if you are 
      not happy about things at the childminders?</a>	
			</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			How do you find a childminder?
			</h2><p>
				'Word of mouth' is a good reference, ask friends or colleagues 
  if they have used a registered childminder they have been happy with.
			</p><p>
				We can put you in touch with childminders who have vacancies, who 
  live in your area or near your place of work or study. Alternatively fill in the 
					
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/20e">
				<strong>online form</strong>
			</a>	
			<span class="gen">link to online form</span>
  and we will post the relevant information to your home address.
			</p><h2>
			
			How do you choose a childminder?
			</h2><p>
				Where possible visit several childminders and talk to them to 
  see if the service they are offering is suitable for your child and your needs. 
  Take a list of questions and any issues you want to bring up before you make a choice, 
  tick them off, make notes as you go along. This will be a useful reminder for you 
  and also places the arrangement on an organised and professional footing from the 
  start.
			</p><h2>
			
			Some points to consider?
			</h2><ul>
			<li title="*">Take your child with you when you visit.</li>
			<li title="*">Always go to a registered childminder - ask to see their registration certificate.</li>
			<li title="*">Check they have up to date public liability insurance cover, ask for proof.</li>
			<li title="*">Look at the accommodation, is it safe, is there room to play?</li>
			<li title="*">Are there toys and books around?</li>
			<li title="*">Ask how many other children are in their care.</li>
			<li title="*">If there are children there, are they happy, settled and busy?</li>
			<li title="*">Will your child fit in?</li>
			<li title="*">Ask about the childminders typical day, do they take the children shopping, 
    attend toddler or playgroup, go on visits or outings etc.?</li>
			<li title="*">How do they deal with unacceptable behavior?</li>
			<li title="*">How do they ensure the children in their care are treated with equal concern?</li>
			<li title="*">What training or experience do they have in looking after other peoples children?</li>
			<li title="*">What plans do they have in the vent of an emergency?</li>
			<li title="*">Which school or playgroup do they take children to?</li>
			<li title="*">When is the service available, meals, snacks etc., and how much do they charge?</li>
			<li title="*">Do you need to provide any equipment such as a buggy?</li>
			<li title="*">Are there any extras to pay e.g. overtime. sickness or holidays?</li>
			<li title="*">When do you have to pay?</li>
			<li title="*">What safety equipment is used - including car restraints?</li>
			<li title="*">Is there appropriate car insurance cover?</li>
			<li title="*">What pets do they have?</li>
			<li title="*">What happens if your child is ill - will they contact you?</li>
			<li title="*">Will they mind a sick child?</li>
			<li title="*">Will you be able to meet the rest of the family?</li>
		</ul><h2>
			
			How do you settle you child with a childminder?
			</h2><p>
				Try to arrange several visits with the childminder for you and 
  your child. This will help them to become familiar with the new situation. Try leaving 
  your child for a short time to start with, so they gradually get used to being left 
  with the childminder.
			</p><h2>
			
			How much do childminders charge?
			</h2><p>
				All childminders are self-employed people, having responsibility 
  for their own income, expenses, equipment, tax and national insurance. They set 
  their own rates, therefore charges will vary from area to area and will be a private 
  agreement between you and the childminder.
			</p><h2>
			
			Contracts
			</h2><p>
				You must always have a contract with the childminder that states 
  the hours, fees, overtime rates, fees for non-attendance, meals provided, notice 
  to be given etc. agreed by you both, signed and dated by both, with a copy each.
			</p><h2>
			
			Do you have to take anything to the childminders?
			</h2><p>
				It might be a good idea to take a favourite toy, and if you 
  have a young baby the childminder may ask you to bring food, nappies etc. Make sure 
  your child is dressed adequately for the time of year, the childminder may want 
  to take your child out during the day. A change of clothes and shoes is a good idea 
  too.
			</p><h2>
			
			What other information will the childminder 
  need?
			</h2><p>
				Telephone numbers, names and addresses of:
			</p><ul>
			<li title="*">your place of work</li>
			<li title="*">your doctor and health visitor</li>
			<li title="*">an emergency contact number</li>
			<li title="*">what illnesses and immunisations your child has had</li>
			<li title="*">any allergies</li>
			<li title="*">what your child does / does not like to eat</li>
			<li title="*">your child's sleeping routine</li>
			<li title="*">any pet words or names</li>
			<li title="*">whether toilet trained</li>
			<li title="*">able to use a cup</li>
			<li title="*">eating implements etc.</li>
		</ul><p>
			<strong>
						Anything that will help your child 
  to settle. 
					</strong>
		</p><h2>
			
			What happens if your child is ill?
			</h2><p>
				Childminders do not normally look after sick children, as infection 
  may spread to other children and their families. If your child becomes ill whilst 
  in the care of the childminder you should be contacted Permission will also be needed 
  to administer any prescribed medicine to your child. 
			</p><h2>
			
			What happens if the childminder is ill?
			</h2><p>
				It is your responsibility to make alternative arrangements, 
  though some childminders help to make arrangements between you and another childminder 
  to cover for them
			</p><h2>
			
			What do you do if you are not happy about 
  things at the childminders?
			</h2><p>
				Try to discuss any difficulties as soon as they arise to work 
  out a solution. It is not a good idea to move your child from one person to another 
  unless you really have to - children need stability and consistent care. If you 
  are unable to resolve your difficulties and they relate to the quality of care, 
  contact Ofsted: <strong>
				
		<a href="http://www.ofsted.gov.uk">www.ofsted.gov.uk
</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=20"> Providing Information
		(20)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
