<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=40}]"><cms:name>education-2-40</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Special educational needs - (SEN) - transport</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=40}]"><cms:name>education-2-40-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>special, educational, needs, transport</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=40}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Local Education Authority is under a duty to provide free transport to a child's nearest suitable school provided it is beyond statutory walking distance from the child's home address. For a child with special educational needs however, the nearest suitable school may well be different than for other pupils, and walking may not be an option. </i></p><hr/><p>  The LEA provides a home to school transport service for pupils: </p><ul>
  <li title="*"> With special educational needs up to the age of 19 </li>
  <li title="*"> With medical needs up to the age of 19 </li>
  <li title="*"> Who are excluded from school </li>
  <li title="*"> Who have a diagnosed phobia of school </li>
  <li title="*"> Who are pregnant or schoolgirl mothers. </li>
</ul><p>The transport is provided in a number of ways: </p><ul>
  <li title="*"> Free travel permits for public transport </li>
  <li title="*"> Mini-bus from home to school </li>
  <li title="*"> Specialist mini-bus, e.g. tail-lift vehicle </li>
  <li title="*"> Taxi/people carrier </li>
  <li title="*"> Wheelchair accessible taxi </li>
</ul><h2>  Entitlement to and review of transport provision </h2><p>Entitlement to transport for children is based on an assessment of individual need. The LEA has produced a standard form for completion as part of the assessment process. The professionals involved in the assessment of children will complete this form in discussion with parents and carers. The information provided allows the transport staff to make an informed decision on the type of vehicle to be provided, the correct restraint and clamping systems to be used and the level of supervision/care. </p><p>
  If it is decided that the child's special needs do not require special transport arrangements then the general home to school distance policy will apply. </p><p>
Transport arrangements will be regularly kept under review. The annual review required for those children with a statement of special educational needs provides a formal opportunity to review any transport arrangements. </p><h2>  Parental preference and transport </h2><p>  If parents choose to send their child to a school that the Local Education Authority does not consider to be the nearest suitable school, there is no duty to provide free transport. In such circumstances parents will be required to make their own transport arrangements or pay to access services. </p><p>
The LEA does, however, retain its discretion to provide free transport or to make a contribution to parents towards the cost. </p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=40"> Providing Information
		(40)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
