<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=627}]"><cms:name>education-2-627</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Becoming a mentor</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=627}]"><cms:name>education-2-627-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>becoming, mentor</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=627}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Learning mentors usually work mainly in the primary or secondary school to which they are attached. They also spend a good deal of time visiting clients and their families in their home. They may also accompany children on school outings. </i></p><hr/><p>
Learning mentors provide an additional service to teachers and pastoral staff in schools to help children overcome barriers to learning, both inside and outside the school, and to achieve their full potential. They work closely with teachers, classroom assistants, special needs assistants and classroom volunteers to identify children who are making less progress than their potential, and develop action plans to meet learning goals. They then support the children to help them achieve these goals. </p><p>
Mentors may work with children in a one-to-one relationship, or with small groups. Most of their work involves working with these children to help them progress in the classroom or other school activities, e.g. lunchtimes or outings. They may provide support with truancy/absence, in the playground or developing social skills. They also keep in contact with the children's family or carers to try and get support and involvement from them in meeting the child's needs and helping their progress. </p><p>
Learning mentors often refer the children they are supporting onto other agencies, courses, organisations, activities or individuals for extra support. Referrals could be to social and youth services, education welfare services, probation and careers services, out of school study support and business and community voluntary mentors. They need to share information between all the different people and organisations involved in supporting the children they are mentoring. </p><p> The main requirements are: </p><ul>
  <li title="*">an ability to form good relationships with a wide range of young people and their families/carers and with a variety of organisations</li>
  <li title="*">ability to gain the confidence of children, schools, agencies and people in the community and business </li>
  <li title="*">skills in negotiating, planning and managing activities. </li>
</ul><p> Learning mentors need good listening skills and an understanding of health and social issues that affect children's development. They will need to understand the school curriculum and the needs of learners. Mentors need competence in literacy and numeracy and may require GCSE/S grade (A-C/1-3) or equivalent in English and maths. They may also be required to have a professional qualification in education, social work or nursing. </p><p>
Training is usually on-the-job, although occasionally outside training may be available to address a particular need of the school, for instance, cross-cultural issues.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=627"> Providing Information
		(627)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
