<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=8}]"><cms:name>education-2-8</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Special educational needs - (SEN) - statement</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=8}]"><cms:name>education-2-8-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Parents</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>special, educational, needs, statement</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=8}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Education</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A statement of Special Educational Needs is a legal document laying out the details of Special Needs which your child is considered to have.</i></p><hr/><p>The statement then goes on to outline the specific help which 
  will be made available to meet your child's Special Needs. This is called Special 
  Educational Provision. A Statement of Special Educational Needs is set out in six 
  parts:</p><h4>Part 1 - Introduction</h4><ul>
			<li title="*">The child's name and address and date of birth. </li>
			<li title="*">The child's home language and religion.</li>
			<li title="*">The names and address(es) of the child's parents.</li>
		</ul><h4>Part 2 - Special Educational Needs</h4><p>Details of each and every one of the child's Special Educational 
  Needs as identified by the LEA during Statutory Assessment from the advice received 
  and attached as appendices to the statement.</p><h4>Part 3 - Special Educational Provision</h4><p>The Special Educational Provision which the LEA consider necessary 
  to meet the child's Special Educational Needs.</p><li title="*">The objectives which the Special Educational Provision should aim to meet.</li><li title="*">The Special Educational Provision which the LEA consider appropriate to meet 
    the needs specified in part 2 and to meet the specified objectives.</li><li title="*">The arrangements for monitoring progress in meeting those objectives, particularly 
    for setting short-term targets for the child's progress on a regular basis.</li><h4>Part 4 - Placement</h4><p>The type and name of school where the Special Educational Provision 
  specified in part 3 is to be made or the arrangements for the education to be made 
  otherwise than in school</p><h4>Part 5 - Non-Educational Needs</h4><p>All relevant non-educational needs of the child as agreed between 
  the Health Services, Social Services or other agencies and the LEA</p><h4>Part 6 - Non-Educational Provision</h4><p>Details of relevant non-educational provision which will be 
  made available to meet the non-educational needs of the child as agreed between 
  the Health Services and/or the Social Services and the LEA, including the agreed 
  arrangements for its provision.</p><p>If it has been decided to issue a Statement of Special Educational 
  Needs, then you will first be sent a 'Proposed Statement'. All sections will be 
  completed except Part 4 (describing the type and name of the school) which is left 
  blank. Along with the copy of the Proposed Statement, you will receive a letter 
  from the Sheffield Education Service telling how you can give your views on the 
  Proposed Statement before a Final Statement is issued. Details of LEA mainstream 
  and special schools in the area are sent to you at this point, along with details 
  of all non-maintained and independent schools approved by the Secretary of State 
  for Education as suitable for children with Special Educational Needs.</p><p>You have a right to express a preference for the LEA maintained 
  school you want you child to go to. This may be the school that your child is already 
  attending.</p><p>We will agree with your preference providing:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">The school you choose is suitable for your child's age, ability and Special 
    Educational Needs.</li>
			<li title="*">Your child's attendance there will not effect the efficient education of other 
    children already at the school.</li>
			<li title="*">Placing your child in the school will be an efficient use of resources</li>
		</ul><p>You may also make any representations in respect of seeking 
  a place at a non-maintained independent school outside the LEA, although the Authority 
  is not obliged to fund a place in one of these schools. The LEA normally tries to 
  make provision for children in one of its own schools. Deciding which school you 
  would prefer your child to attend is a very important matter and we will be pleased 
  to talk to you and provide you with additional information to assist you with making 
  your decision.</p><p>You may wish to visit schools in order to familiarise yourself 
  with the provision made by the Local Education Authority. You have 15 days in which 
  to make any comments and express your preference of school you want for your child. 
  Usually the Local Education Authority will send you the Final Statement within 
  8 weeks of issuing the Proposed Statement. You will be informed of your right of 
  appeal against the Authority's decision to an independent Special 
  Needs Tribunal if you do not agree with the Final Statement issued by the Authority.</p><p>An assessment should take no longer than 6 months. (There are 
  exceptions to this time limit e.g. when professional advice is received late).</p><p>Parents or carers can help by replying quickly whenever the 
  Local Education Authority contacts you.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=8"> Providing Information
		(8)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
