<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=127}]"><cms:name>batch-16-127</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Property demolition - services for council tenants affected by - tenants responsibilities</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=127}]"><cms:name>batch-16-127-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>property, demolition, services, council, tenants, affected, responsibilities</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=127}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><p><i>Once you know the date you will be moving, you need to let the Area Housing Office know as soon as possible.</i></p><hr/><p>Disconnecting appliances 
If you have any gas appliances, you should contact a Corgi registered gas engineer to arrange for the disconnection.  This is because supply pipes must be property sealed.  Similarly, a qualified electrician should disconnect any electrical appliances, such as showers or washing machines.  You can claim this payment back within your Disturbance Claim as long as you have a valid receipt.</p><p>Don't forget to arrange for final readings to be taken of gas and electricity meters.  You will probably need to give at least 48 hours notice to the gas and electricity companies.</p><h3>Housing benefit and council tax</h3><p>You must inform the Benefits Service of any change of address.  If you already receive housing benefit or council tax benefit, you must tell the Benefits Service your new address as soon as possible, to make sure you continue to receive all that is due to you.  Remember, housing benefit is payable on your principal address, so you must move into your new property as soon as possible.</p><h3>Handing in keys</h3><p>You will need to agree with your local Housing Office the date to hand in keys to your old property.  It is important that you hand your keys in as soon as possible after you leave so that we can arrange to have certain services like your water supply, disconnected.</p><h3>Home loss and disturbance payment</h3><p>You can claim a cash advance once you know you are moving.  This is to help with payments you might need to make to removal firms, or to have your telephone disconnected and reconnected at your new home.  You must save all your receipts so that you can claim back the cost of moving home.  A cheque will be sent to your new address.</p><p>When you hand in your keys to your old home you need to complete the home loss form so that the Housing Office can arrange to have your compensation processed.  A cheque for this will be sent out to your new address.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=127"> Providing Information
		(127)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
