<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=130}]"><cms:name>housing-3-130</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Home improvements - adaptations in a council property</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=130}]"><cms:name>housing-3-130-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>home, improvements, adaptations, council property</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=130}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Tenants of the Council have what is known as a 'secure tenancy'. This means as a tenant you have the right to carry out improvements to your home, provided that you first get permission from the Director of Housing.</i></p><hr/><p>Each application is considered separately and permission is usually given, subject to any conditions that may be appropriate.</p><p>If permission is not given we will write to you, giving you the reasons. If you are not satisfied with the decision you have the right to appeal. Appeals should be sent to the Director of Housing in the first place, and then to the County Court if you are still not satisfied.</p><p>You also have the right to appeal if you think that the conditions under which permission is given are unreasonable.</p><p>You must not start any improvement work until written permission has been given by the Director of Housing.</p><p>The Council provides adaptations to Council properties to suit the needs of disabled people or people with mobility problems. These can include providing a rail, lever taps, ramp, shower or stairlift. If your needs cannot be met in your current home we will also discuss alternative housing options with you.</p><p>If you require a simple rail, banister or lever taps, please contact us using the details above.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=130"> Providing Information
		(130)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
