<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=136}]"><cms:name>housing-2-136</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Home improvements - home repair assistance grant</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=136}]"><cms:name>housing-2-136-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>home, improvements, repair, assistance, grant</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=136}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>An applicant must be an owner-occupier or tenant with a tenancy of more than five years. The applicant must be aged 18 or over and live in the dwelling as their only or main residence or care for an elderly (aged 60 or over) or infirm person.</i></p><hr/><p>If the applicant is under 60, they must be in receipt of an income-related benefit (ie. income support, and income-based job seekers allowance, Family Credit, housing benefit, Council tax benefit (not single occupancy reduction) or disability working allowance.)</p><h3>Eligible Works </h3><p>Assistance is available in the form of a grant for carrying out works of repair, improvement or adaptations to a dwelling by a builder or if you choose to carry out the work yourself you may be able to get assistance towards the cost of materials.</p><h3>Repair and Improvement</h3><p>The Local Authority may consider grants for repairs to secure the basic fabric of the property from the entry of wind or rain, or to protect the occupants from immediate exposure to dangerous building elements or foul drainage.</p><h3>Adaptations</h3><p>Where an applicant is elderly/disabled and the work is assessed as being urgent and necessary by the Occupational Therapist, a Home Repair Assistance Grant may be considered appropriate, to adapt a dwelling to enable an elderly, disabled or infirm person who lives or proposes to live in the dwelling as his or her only main residence, to be cared for.</p><h3>Energy Efficiency</h3><p>Home Repair Assistance may be given for energy efficiency works, including loft, hot water tank and pipe insulation, draught proofing and secondary glazing. The applicant may be eligible for grant assistance under the Home Energy Efficiency Scheme (HEES) and should apply for a HEES Grant to see the extent to which a HEES Grant would be able to cover the works concerned. A separate leaflet is available for the HEES Grant.</p><h3>Amount of Assistance</h3><p>Home Repair Assistance Grants are intended for small scale works.</p><h3>Prior Residence Requirement for a House Boat or Mobile Home</h3><p>The applicant must have occupied the boat or mobile home, as their only or main residence for a period of at least three years immediately preceding the date of the application.</p><p>To apply for a Home Repair Assistance Grant, you will need to complete a provisional grant application form to assess your eligibility for a survey.</p><p>A <strong>provisional</strong> form does not constitute a valid application or give you permission to commence or complete any of the work required.</p><p>You will not get any financial assistance if you start work before the council provide you with a formal written grant approval.</p><p>For an application form please contact us using the details above.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=136"> Providing Information
		(136)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
