<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=138}]"><cms:name>batch-16-138</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Home improvements - housing renovation grant for a private property</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=138}]"><cms:name>batch-16-138-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>home, improvements, housing, renovation, grant, private, property</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=138}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>A Renovation Grant is a discretionary grant which is available where larger scale works are required to make a house fit for habitation or to put a dwelling into reasonable repair.</i></p><hr/><p>The type of work that might qualify for grant aid is work to remedy instability, serious disrepair, severe dampness and to provide adequate heating, lighting and ventilation, adequate water supplies, cooking and food preparation facilities, a suitable WC, bath or shower and wash basin and adequate drainage</p><h3>Who can apply?</h3><p>Applicants must be over 18 and be in receipt of an income related benefit or tax credit to apply for a Renovation Grant. However, applicants aged over 60 or who are disabled or infirm and who are applying for grant to carry out adaptation works do not have to be receipt of benefit or tax credits.</p><p>The applicant must have been an owner-occupier or occupying tenant for 3 years or more on the date of the application.</p><p>First time buyers buying a property for less than &#xA3;35,000 which is unfit do not have to fulfil the 3-year occupancy rule.</p><p>All applicants including joint property owners will be subject to a test of resources that calculates the financial contribution they will be required to make towards the eligible costs of the works required.</p><p>You should not assume that you will automatically qualify for a grant, as they are means tested.</p><h3>How much is the grant?</h3><p>The maximum assistance available is &#xA3;20,000 for unfit properties in Council Tax band A or B and &#xA3;10,000 for unfit properties in Council Tax band C or above.</p><p>If the costs of the eligible works are less than the applicant's calculated contribution no grant will be paid. If the cost of the work exceeds the maximum grant payable the applicant must pay the balance.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=138"> Providing Information
		(138)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
