<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=145}]"><cms:name>batch-16-145</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Council initiatives</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=145}]"><cms:name>batch-16-145-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>council, initiatives</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=145}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Housing</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Government requires all local housing authorities to achieve a new 'decent homes' standard by 2010 and to consult with tenants, leaseholders and other stakeholders about how best to achieve this and other wishes for service improvements.</i></p><hr/><p>The decent homes standard relates to the physical condition of the home, but the review of the options must look at work on dwellings as well as improvements to services and the local environment.</p><p>There are four options that are theoretically available</p><h3>1. The Private Finance Initiative</h3><p>- involves entering into a 30 year or so contract with the private sector to refurbish, manage and maintain the homes. Government subsidy would be needed to help pay the operator, and may be available. PFI is unsuitable for whole housing stocks. It works best where a large amount of initial investment (involving 1,000 homes or more) saves on subsequent management and maintenance costs. The size and condition of the Council's housing stock suggests that PFI is unlikely to be appropriate.</p><h3>Staying with the Council</h3><p>Staying with the current arrangements with the council owning and managing the housing stock - this is only feasible if there are enough resources to achieve decent homes standards and keep the stock in a reasonable state of repair without additional support. The survey of the housing stock has identified a shortfall in funding, to needed housing stock and estates in the region of &#xA3;2 million each year. Additionally, it appears that as Government policy on rent convergence is implemented, there will not be enough income annually to maintain current service levels. In these circumstances one of the three options that offer additional investment will need to be chosen.</p><h3>Arms Length Management Organisation Initiative</h3><p>The ownership of the properties remains with the Council and a new organisation is set up to manage the housing stock. There would be no change to current or new tenancy agreements and extra funds could be accessed to meet decent homes standards. However, the funds would not be sufficient to develop local housing services and carry out improvement works over and above the decent homes standard, such as soundproofing, energy efficiency and estate improvements. In addition, the shortage of income noted in 1 above would apply and it would be difficult to maintain existing services.</p><h3>Transfer to a Housing Association</h3><p>This option involves the transfer of ownership of the Council's homes to a non-profit making organisation registered with the Housing Corporation. Existing tenants' rights, such as the right to buy and succession, do not change. There is also no change to the way that rents are set or increased. The existing Council staff who manage the service now, including sheltered housing scheme managers, would continue to do so and would transfer to the new housing association. Funding under this option would become available to the new housing association to meet and exceed the decent homes standards and develop and improve your local housing service. The borough council would also receive substantial funding from the transfer of ownership, which could be utilised to develop services and fund the provision of new homes for local people.</p><p>The new landlord can be an existing housing association, or a newly created local organisation. Tenants would be fully consulted on which choice to make. Tenant representatives will be included on the board of any new organisation. The Council have carefully considered all of the options and these have been discussed at tenant participation compact and tenant panel meetings. The Council have indicated that Option 4, the transfer to a housing association, is currently the preferred option. It has now been agreed to seek the views of all tenants and leaseholders in relation to the two most feasible options. OPTION 3 - Arms Length Management Organisation OPTION 4 - Transfer to a Housing Association.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=145"> Providing Information
		(145)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
