<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=472}]"><cms:name>batch-8-472</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>On street parking enforcement - wheel clamps</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=472}]"><cms:name>batch-8-472-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>street, parking, enforcement, wheel, clamps</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=472}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Because a Penalty Charge Notice (PCN) is not always a sufficient deterrent to prevent 'illegal' parking, the Council also uses vehicle clamps to immobilise vehicles. In other cases where the illegally parked vehicle is taking up much needed space we remove the vehicle to our Vehicle Pound. We also use the same methods against persistent offenders who flout the law and do not pay for their PCN's.</i></p><hr/><h4>Vehicle Clamping</h4><p>The present charge for release from a wheel clamp is &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount.</span> This charge and the cost 
  of the PCN must be paid before the vehicle will be released back to you.</p><p>To obtain release, telephone the number given on the notice attached to your vehicle. We will accept your credit/debit card details over the telephone or go to your nearest Customer Service Centre.</p><p>If you feel that you were wrongly clamped you must still pay the charges for release of your vehicle but you will be offered a Representation Form on which to challenge the PCN and wheel clamp charge. This form must be sent in within 28 days of issue of the PCN.</p><h4>Vehicle Removal</h4><p>If you parked your vehicle illegally it may have been removed by the Council to our Vehicle Pound. The current charge to recover your vehicle is &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span> which must be paid in addition to the PCN applicable to your vehicle's removal.</p><p>To check if your vehicle has been removed you can call the Transport Committee on <span class="gen">enter telephone number</span>
</p><p>They will tell you if your car has been removed and, if it has, how to get it back. This is a 24-hour service.</p><p>The Vehicle Pound is currently located <span class="gen">enter location</span>
</p><p>If you feel that you were not parked 'illegally' you must pay the charges and then make a formal challenge. You will be offered a form on which to make your Representation and this must be submitted within 28 days - as per the instructions on the form.</p><p>If you do not collect the vehicle from the pound within 24 hours, storage charges of &#xA3; <span class="gen">enter amount</span> 
  per day will be incurred.</p><p>If you do not claim your vehicle then the Council will take steps to dispose of the vehicle. Disposal does not mean that any charges are waived. The Council will take action to recover any unpaid PCN charges, removal fees and 
  storage charges.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=472"> Providing Information
		(472)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
