<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=419}]"><cms:name>batch-7-419</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Health and Safety at work - regulation and inspection</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=419}]"><cms:name>batch-7-419-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>Businesses</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>health, safety, work, regulation, inspection</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=419}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>The Health and Safety Unit within the Council carries out regular checks on offices, shops, warehouses, places used for leisure activities and other non-industrial premises. (The Health and Safety Executive deal with factories and other industrial operations). This ensures that safe and healthy working conditions are provided for all employees, the self-employed and members of the public visiting these premises.</i></p><hr/><p>As with food safety, inspections are carried out on a routine basis without prior notification and the high risk premises are visited more frequently.</p><p>During an inspection, Officers will need to be satisfied that any hazards to people's health, safety and welfare, which arise out of or in connection with work have been identified and the associated risks adequately controlled. They will look at the 
  level of health and safety training of managers and employees to ensure that it is suitable. Checks will also be made on the adequacy of structural and environmental conditions and that plant and equipment are safe.</p><p>Where work practices or conditions fall short of what is regarded as satisfactory every attempt will be made to resolve the situation by informal means, but if this is not possible, or if the danger posed gives rise to a risk of serious personal injury, then officers will resort to formal action. This could involve either the service of a legal notice, prosecution, or in situations where serious personal injury could arise, a prohibition notice requiring immediate action.</p><p>To request an inspection use the <strong>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/419a">on-line form</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link to online form.</span>
</p><h3>Health and Safety Complaint Investigation</h3><p>Complaints about working conditions are always investigated sensitively and the complainant's confidentiality is assured. Such matters are usually resolved by giving advice to the employer, but as with accident investigation, if formal action is needed then this will be taken.</p><h3>Health and Safety Accident Investigation</h3><p>The investigation of dangerous occurrences and accidents at work also forms an important part of the Section's work. The outcome of these enquiries usually involves the giving of advice to the employer. If a blatant breach of requirements is identified 
  as the main reason for an accident happening, then formal action will be taken.</p><p>In the event that someone who has been injured as a result of a work related accident wishes to pursue a compensation claim their legal advisor may wish to obtain a factual statement from us. This details the investigation into the accident and the findings. This can be provided at a cost of <span class="gen">enter amount</span> + VAT.</p><h3>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=707">Cooling Towers</a>	 <span class="gen">link to pid 707</span>
</h3><p>All premises where cooling towers and evaporative condensers are situated must register with the local authority under The Notification of Cooling Towers and Evaporative Condensers Regulations 1992.</p><p>The prime purpose of this is to identify potential areas that could give rise to spread of infectious disease e.g. legionella and to ensure preventative measures 
  are taken to eliminate the risk of such infection arising to employees and the public.</p><p>Click here to complete the <strong>

		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=forms/419c">registration form</a>	
</strong> <span class="gen">link 
  to online form</span> that can be filled out and e-mailed to the local authority.</p><h3>Information and Advice</h3><p>The Council is committed to working together with proprietors and managers to achieve high standards and prevent problems. We are always willing to give advice on legislation, or practical problems, so if you are considering setting up a business, or wish to discuss anything in relation to your existing premises, please feel free to contact us.</p><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=419"> Regulation
		(419)
		</a></h3><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=419"> Applications for services
		(419)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
