<?xml version="1.0"?>
<cms:item xmlns:cms="http://www.arsdigita.com/cms/1.0" xmlns="http://www.esd.org.uk/standards/esdbody" oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.contenttypes.ESDService:{id=426}]"><cms:name>batch-7-426</cms:name><cms:language>en</cms:language><cms:title>Fireworks</cms:title><cms:dublinCore oid="[com.arsdigita.london.cms.dublin.DublinCoreItem:{id=426}]"><cms:name>batch-7-426-dublin-metadata</cms:name><cms:dcAudience>General Public</cms:dcAudience><cms:dcCoverage>content=&quot;99XX&quot; scheme=&quot;ONS SNAC&quot;</cms:dcCoverage><cms:dcCoveragePostcode/><cms:dcCoverageSpatialRef/><cms:dcCoverageUnit/><cms:dcDateValid/><cms:dcDisposalReview/><cms:dcLanguage>en</cms:dcLanguage><cms:dcTemporalBegin/><cms:dcTemporalEnd/><cms:dcCreatorOwner>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorOwner><cms:dcCreatorContact>LAWS Project - Starter Kit - http://www.laws-project.org.uk</cms:dcCreatorContact><cms:dcPublisher>Tameside MBC - LAWS project - http://laws.tameside.gov.uk</cms:dcPublisher><cms:dcRights/><cms:dcKeywords>fireworks, safety</cms:dcKeywords></cms:dublinCore><cms:textAsset oid="[com.arsdigita.cms.TextAsset:{id=426}]"><cms:content><![CDATA[<h2>Environmental Services</h2><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><p><i>Fireworks are a traditional part of enjoying celebrations such as Bonfire Night or New Year but they are the cause of many hundreds of serious accidents every year - it should be remembered that they are dangerous explosives. The safest way to enjoy them is to go to a professionally organised event.</i></p><hr/><p>The government's <strong>
				
		<a href="http://www.dti.gov.uk/homesafetynetwork/fw_pandr.htm">Fireworks 
  Safety Campaign (DTI)</a>	
			</strong> <span class="gen">link to external website</span> provides downloadable guidance leaflets and materials 
  for organisers of firework displays for the public, retailers selling fireworks, 
  schools and the media, including the Firework Safety Code.</p><p>Professionally organised displays are regulated by the <strong>
				
		<a href="http://www.hse.gov.uk/spd/explosives/xpl_dis.htm">Health 
  and Safety Executive (HSE)</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span> who publish two booklets 
  - 'Giving Your Own Firework Display' and 'Working Together', aimed at organisers 
  of events where a professional firework display company fires the display, available 
  from 
		<a href="http://www.hsebooks.co.uk">
				<strong>HSE Books.</strong>
			</a>	 <span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><p>For more advice about firework safety, go to the following websites:</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Fire Service UK - Bonfire and Firework Safety</li>
			<li title="*">Advice for organisers of Public Displays</li>
			<li title="*">National Campaign for Firework Safety</li>
			<li title="*">UK Firework Safety Pages</li>
			<li title="*">Fire Kills - Safety tips for Celebrations</li>
			<li title="*">Royal Society for the Prevention of Accidents (ROSPA)</li>
		</ul><p>Remember that pets are frightened of fireworks - always keep them indoors.</p><p>You can download a leaflet Fireworks and Pets in PDF format 
  from the <strong>
				
		<a href="http://www.bluecross.org.uk/content/publications/publications.html">Blue 
  Cross - All About Pets website</a>	
			</strong>
			<span class="gen">link to external website</span>
		</p><p>Retailers selling fireworks must be registered with <span class="gen">enter council name</span> Trading 
  Standards who investigate problems with unsafe products.</p><h3>Follow the Firework Code</h3><p>If you buy fireworks, always make sure they comply with BS 7114 and are clearly 
  marked for their intended use 'Indoor, Garden or Display'</p><ul>
			<li title="*">Keep fireworks in a sealed box or tin</li>
			<li title="*">Use them one at a time, replacing the lid immediately</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Never</strong> put fireworks in your pocket</li>
			<li title="*">Read the instructions carefully, using a torch or hand lamp <strong>never</strong> use 
    a naked flame</li>
			<li title="*">Light fireworks at arms length using a taper or a firework lighter</li>
			<li title="*">Stand well back and <strong>never</strong> return to a firework after it has been lit, 
    it could explode in your face</li>
			<li title="*">Ensure that all children with fireworks are well supervised</li>
			<li title="*">
				<strong>Never</strong> throw fireworks</li>
			<li title="*">Keep all pets and animals indoors</li>
			<li title="*">Take care of sparklers, wear gloves to hold them and dispose of sparklers in 
    a bucket of water as soon as they are finished</li>
			<li title="*">Despite annual safety warnings, Bonfire Night week still ends in disaster for 
    far too many families. Fireworks can provide fun and entertainment, but only if 
    everyone follows the right safety procedures and remembers that fireworks can 
    be very dangerous if misused. </li>
		</ul><p>Remember to be careful with bonfires too. It's much better to manage without one. 
  But if you insist make sure it's well away from your house and any trees, hedges, 
  fences or sheds.</p><p>Never use a flammable liquid like petrol or paraffin to get one going. If lighting 
  your bonfire is difficult, use only domestic firelighters to help. Check very carefully 
  that there's no animal (or even a young child) hidden inside the bonfire.</p><p>Don't light it until after all your fireworks have been let off. Keep everyone 
  a safe distance away, and don't allow anyone to throw anything onto it.</p><p>Loose clothing (like shell-suits) can very easily catch alight and should never 
  be worn near any fire. Long scarves can be risky too.</p><h3>Remember Fireworks are explosives - get wise or get hurt!</h3><span class="gen">email address here</span><span class="gen">phone number here</span><span class="gen">sms phone number here</span><span class="gen">fax number here</span><span class="gen">minicom number here</span><span class="gen">postal address here</span><h3>
		<a href="/ccm/services/pid.jsp?pid=426"> Providing Information
		(426)
		</a></h3>]]></cms:content></cms:textAsset></cms:item>
